<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@feasdfeasfgefge3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="992">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’d <em>probably</em> trust Disroot a little more</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="992">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I wouldn’t be opposed to adding Disroot’s SearXNG instance to the Kicksecure start page</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>They are so called “antifa”. I don’t see how you could trust anything they would do.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 18:50:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2559</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello. Your conclusion about the Startpage is interesting. Essentially, the Startpage is Google with a proxy, but also with a large amount of annoying ads. I think the value of this lies only in the proxy, as services like Searx or 4get.ca can replace it without displaying ads. However, I just conducted a test in Searx (Startpage only) and Startpage with the same query and settings, but the results were slightly different.</p>
<p>P.S. I was also surprised by the presence of Perplexity, and I thought they had fully open-sourced the code. Perhaps the presence of a non-open-source service will confuse those who will install Librewolf, Mullvad or Brave browsers in the future through the “Choose Browser” feature. But this raises the question - will Kicksecure-welcome-page be added to all browsers in the “Choose Browser” list?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 10:21:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2555</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think it’s unnecessary and not worth spending time on it. If you’re going to add new buttons to the panel (such as a journal search, system monitor, firewall…), then the panel will increase in size and will overlap any background.<br>
By the way, have you considered changing the color for Livecheck on the panel: green for live, and yellow/orange/red for persistent mode, to warn users that everything they do will be saved to the system, in order to increase the level of responsibility. When clicking on the circle, you can add a hint “if you’re not sure about your actions, test it in live mode”.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 09:58:41 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2554</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>To rephrase… This is more of a practical consideration. Do you find yourself using that search engine because you find results that you don’t find on other search engines?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 08:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2553</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="992">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s alternative search engines which provide less censored / more interesting search results</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If we are discussing this criterion, what do you think about Mojeek? <a href="https://www.mojeek.com/about/why-mojeek" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Why Mojeek?</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Mojeek’s web search results are 100% independent. They come from our crawler (<a href="https://www.mojeek.com/bot.html" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">MojeekBot</a>) and index of the web, and are ordered using our own ranking algorithms.</p>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 08:10:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2552</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>What do you think about search engine 4get.ca? I have not used it, but on searchengine.party it have good ratings. 4get.ca is very interestingly described here <a href="https://git.lolcat.ca/lolcat/4get" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">lolcat/4get: 4get is a proxy search engine that doesn't suck - 4get - lolcat's git serber</a>. After reading this, I already to think that SearxNG and 4get.ca are future of protected search engines.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 08:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2551</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Wow this is very interesting! I used Startpage because of the Tor browser - Tor browser has 2 default search engines: Duckduckgo and Startpage. I thought Tor team chose it for enhanced privacy and security. Startpage has been added to list of default search engines in the secure browsers Mullvad and Librewolf. And also, the guys from<br>
Privacy Guides <a href="https://www.privacyguides.org/en/tools/" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Ad-Free Privacy Tool/Service Recommendations - Privacy Guides</a> also recommend Startpage as a safe search engine after their analysis. And the author of searchengine.party put Startpage above Brave, Duckduckgo, and Qwant. It seems, Snowden gave an interview to Startpage and recommended their search engine in this video <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7_RnBX3l124" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7_RnBX3l124</a> I liked Startpage for search results and anonymous viewing. At same time your list includes proprietary Perplexity, although this is a very convenient service. for example, it seems to me that Startpage looks more secure than a proprietary service.<br>
As for SearXNG - choice of service is up to you. I just checked that Librewolf uses searx.be server. It seems that in this search engine you can configure search results output from Startpage and then SearXNG can be an alternative if you don’t like Startpage</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 07:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2550</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>related:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Transparency">Kicksecure Project Transparency</a> wiki page chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Transparency#Search_Engines">Search Engines</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First">Utilize Search Engines, Documentation and AI</a> chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First#Search_Engines">Search Engines</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Quote <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/local-browser-homepage-for-tor-browser-in-whonix/347/101" class="inline-onebox">Local browser homepage for Tor Browser in Whonix - #101 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>My arbitrary criteria:<br>
It’s alternative search engines which provide less censored / more interesting search results. Whonix doesn’t receive payment for any listings. Considered candidates are those having good quality, less censored search results.</p>
<p>Privacy by policy / ownership / location / hosted by which data center is not considered. There is no escape from cloudshare / AWS:</p>
<p>[…]</p>
<p>Non-javascript support isn’t considered either. Impractical. <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/whonix-forums-and-javascript/6390">Even these forums here require javascript.</a></p>
<p>High risk of <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/law-of-triviality-bikeshed/6739">law of triviality / bikeshed</a>. There’s no way to optimize for all goals at once. I don’t intent to spend a lot time debating favorite colors (choice of search engines).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Main question is, do they provide great search results?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 05:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2549</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Installation methods</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Once based on Debian 13 / trixie, we’ll have top notch cryptsetup settings in calamares. See:<br>
<a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/iso-cryptsetup-full-disk-encryption-fde-set-more-secure-default-encryption-settings/588" class="inline-onebox">ISO - cryptsetup Full Disk Encryption (FDE) - set more secure default encryption settings</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/installation-methods/1026#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 04:09:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2548</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thinking about it more, I think even if we do want to implement some form of background customization for sysmaint sessions, it should be rather limited (i.e., we shouldn’t allow making an arbitrary image the desktop background). Reasons for this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Getting an image into the sysmaint account is unsafe almost no matter how you do it:
<ul>
<li>You could launch Firefox and download an image, but the web browser offers a substantial amount of attack surface. One of the main reasons for creating <code>sysmaint-panel</code> in the first place was to discourage the user from launching Firefox in a sysmaint session.</li>
<li>You could download an image into <code>/home/user/Downloads</code> and then copy it into the <code>sysmaint</code> account in a sysmaint session, but that’s tricky due to user account separations in Kicksecure, and you’re still trusting an arbitrary image from a user account that may be compromised. (Obviously you don’t want your <code>user</code> account compromised, but we try to assume it and other user accounts <em>are</em> compromised and design the sysmaint session accordingly.)</li>
<li>You could overcome the clunkiness of having to copy files into the <code>sysmaint</code> account by making there be some way to change the <code>sysmaint</code> account’s background from a user session, but that’s even worse from a security standpoint because now the <code>user</code> account can push arbitrary images into the <code>sysmaint</code> account at will.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Image files are a well-known exploit vector due to the complexity of most common image file formats. There probably are zero-days in the image file parsing code used by Qt, if history is any indicator. Therefore image files aren’t something you want to just blindly trust if you can help it.</li>
</ul>
<p>That being said, implementing some form of background customization might be neat, but I’d want to limit it to setting a solid color or gradient background. Currently the background you see in a sysmaint session isn’t an image at all, it’s created on the fly with a Qt CSS theming trick. Allowing the user to choose the start and end colors of the gradient would allow some customization without any of the dangers of images. I’m not sure if that’s something <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/patrick">@Patrick</a> is interested in at the moment, but that’s a theoretical way of doing this.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 03:51:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2547</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>SearXNG looks neat as a project, but simply “adding the SearXNG search engine” is tricky since SearXNG itself is an open-source project, not a service. Individuals may run public SearXNG services, but in that instance if you use those services, you are trusting whoever runs them with the info you’d be entrusting Google with if you use their search engine. SearXNG’s documentation even warns:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Always use an instance which is operated by people you trust.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So the question then becomes what instance to trust. Personally I’m leery of personal instances because, well, we have no idea who’s running them. It could be a respectable privacy advocate who wants to do the world a favor, it might be the head of the intelligence agency of (insert a nation you dislike here). If an individual was very well-known in the open-source or privacy and security communities, and was able to sustainably run the search engine on their own, it would probably be fine, but otherwise, I’d steer clear there.</p>
<p>Company-run instances are a lot easier to trust ironically, because the entity behind them is known or at least more likely knowable. If they do something shady, it’s also more likely to become publicly known. The searchengine.party site linked by rico lists two company-run SearXNG instances, one run by /e/, and the other one ran by Disroot. Of the two, /e/ is known for <a href="https://www.golem.de/news/datenschutz-e-will-google-ersetzen-2004-147396-4.html" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">selling smartphones with an outdated and probably insecure version of Android, among other security failures</a>, so if I had to pick between them I’d <em>probably</em> trust Disroot a little more. Granted, I don’t necessarily think either of them are going to shuttle your data off to a large corporation, this is just my initial reaction looking at things.</p>
<p>My first impression of Startpage isn’t great:</p>
<ul>
<li>Looking at <a href="https://www.startpage.com/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">their home page</a>, they claim to quote a few (presumably) high-profile people in the privacy space supporting them, including Edward Snowden, but with no links to the articles they’re (presumably) quoting.</li>
<li>They’re <a href="https://system1.com/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">owned by System1</a>, an advertising company that, in their own words, “<a href="https://system1.com/what-we-do" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">monetizes internet traffic by putting the right ads in front of the right people at the right time.</a>” This is obviously more than a little worrying.</li>
<li>Their search engine solution isn’t open-source, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StartpageSearch/comments/lge9n0/comment/gmtig3v/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">at least partially because they’re using intentionally proprietary anti-spam algorithms</a>, which I guess is <em>reasonable</em> but still non-ideal.</li>
<li>On the plus side, I didn’t see any third-party analytics links when looking through the client-side source code of the home page, so that was good.</li>
</ul>
<p>Ultimately it seems like they’re making a bunch of claims you have to blindly trust, and some claims that, in a worst-case scenario, could technically be true while still leaving the platform privacy-invasive. (I.e., if they’re owned by an advertising company, they don’t exactly have to sell your data to monetize it. Just because they “block 3rd parties from accessing your personal data to target you”, doesn’t mean they can’t use your personal data to target you themselves.)</p>
<p>I took a look at the searchengine.party code, it looks reasonable at first glance, and the code deployed on the website itself is identical to the code from their <a href="https://gitlab.com/nitrohorse/search-engines-compare" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Git repository</a>. They were last updated ten months ago, which is a bit worrying, and <a href="https://gitlab.com/nitrohorse" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">the maintainer hasn’t been very active on Gitlab this year</a>, so I’m not sure how well-maintained of a resource it is. Then again, it went a year and two months without an update and then received a bunch of updates ten months ago so maybe that’s just the speed at which it needs to be updated. Some way of automatically re-checking the various data points to ensure it’s accurate would be neat, not sure if that exists yet.</p>
<p>Anyway, in conclusion, I wouldn’t be opposed to adding Disroot’s SearXNG instance to the Kicksecure start page, and think that adding the searchengine.party page might be a good idea too. I don’t think adding Startpage is a good idea at the moment.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2546</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="3" data-topic="1027">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It seems that old, outdated information is present after systemcheck in user session mode. If there are new updates, it is recommended to open the terminal in Start menu and enter ‘upgrade-nonroot’.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Good catch, we should fix that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 20:01:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2545</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1027">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Currently most (if not all?) of Kicksecure and Whonix’s codebase is English-only.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is not a problem. The panel requires only a minimal knowledge of English + there is a live mode for testing, where users from different countries can try out what they are unfamiliar with or do not understand.<br>
Thank you very much for your work!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 19:33:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2544</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It seems that old, outdated information is present after systemcheck in user session mode. If there are new updates, it is recommended to open the terminal in Start menu and enter ‘upgrade-nonroot’. However, the current accurate information is to reboot and start a sysmaint session for updates. This information is also not relevant for the sysmaint session, as there is no Start menu there. Otherwise, the system works perfectly - I have installed programs, uninstalled programs, tried various settings, run programs under different users, and tested all the panel buttons.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 19:27:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2543</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>The only issue is that I couldn’t change theme and background in sysmaintenance mode. Only the theme in the window manager changes. But maybe that’s how you intended it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Right now the background is hardcoded, though it differs between Kicksecure, Whonix-Gateway, and Whonix-Workstation. In theory it could be made configurable, I’m not sure if that’s a good idea though since right now the background allows easy identification of the underlying OS (which is useful if you have multiple VMs of different kinds running at the same time).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The panel is very convenient! It just lacks buttons for viewing the log and searching the log by keyword. This would make the panel perfect and improve the convenience of administration - it’s convenient to administer the system in a few clicks.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oooh, that’s not a bad idea. <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/patrick">@Patrick</a>, what do you think? That would in theory be easy to add.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Will the maintenance panel be translated into other languages in the future?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Currently most (if not all?) of Kicksecure and Whonix’s codebase is English-only.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 18:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2542</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Testing Kicksecure 17.3.9.2</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I tested the new version. It seems to be working great. The only issue is that I couldn’t change theme and background in sysmaintenance mode. Only the theme in the window manager changes. But maybe that’s how you intended it.<br>
The panel is very convenient! It just lacks buttons for viewing the log and searching the log by keyword. This would make the panel perfect and improve the convenience of administration - it’s convenient to administer the system in a few clicks.<br>
Will the maintenance panel be translated into other languages in the future?<br>
Thank you</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/testing-kicksecure-17-3-9-2/1027#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 18:24:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2541</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Installation methods</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Reason why asking for this</p>
<p>Debian live calmares inataller still uses Luks1 for years</p>
<p>Debian graphical installer uses luks2 when using guided partition lvm</p>
<p>Kicksecure calamares installer uses luks2</p>
<p>Seems debian as secure windows do not bother</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/installation-methods/1026#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 17:21:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2540</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Installation methods</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Not planned.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/installation-methods/1026#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 15:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2539</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Installation methods</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Request documented wiki to install kicksecure manually alongside calamares incl FDE</p>
<p>Possible in future?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/installation-methods/1026#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 15:01:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2538</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Browser choice</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Context:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746437431" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:42AM - 03 May 2025">Kicksecure – 3 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice" target="_blank" rel="noopener">browser choice</a></h3>

  <p>Design and implementation overview of the browser selection interface, featuring randomized presentation, plugin architecture, and inclusion criteria.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="4" data-topic="1025">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>You can add that this is a list of open-source browsers.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That’s a good idea.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/browser-choice/1025#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 14:11:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2537</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Browser choice</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You can add that this is a list of open-source browsers. You might be surprised, but many linux users consider Vivaldi the best secure browser. They will be surprised not to see it on the list</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/browser-choice/1025#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 13:51:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2536</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Browser choice</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1025">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The current plan is to not include proprietary browsers in the list at all.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/+1.png?v=12" title=":+1:" class="emoji only-emoji" alt=":+1:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/browser-choice/1025#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 13:48:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2535</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live Kicksecure Host, Live Whonix VM</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi, friend. I think you’ve already checked this, but I’ll add it for new users: yes, 32 gb is enough to run Whonix (this will even be enough to run an additional Kicksecure VM). If you have 16 gb - only cli version</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-kicksecure-host-live-whonix-vm/779#post_15</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 13:45:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2534</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Browser choice</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks for the feedback! One note:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Add a signature “proprietary” or “not open source” if there are proprietary browsers in the list.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The current plan is to not include proprietary browsers in the list at all.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/browser-choice/1025#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 13:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2533</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Browser choice</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello. browser choice - brilliant solution! This will close discussions about a secure browser, and new users will be able to get acquainted with new browsers that they did not know about. I would like to add 2 sentences for consideration:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Add a signature “proprietary” or “not open source” if there are proprietary browsers in the list. I agree that describing browsers will be redundant due to possible bias, but information about the code is not biased and is very important in assessing security (browsers do not write about proprietary code on their own sites). This will allow new users to assess the risks of installing Google Chrome, Vivaldi, Opera, Yandex Browser… This information can be taken from the site <a href="http://alternativeto.net" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">alternativeto.net</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Add a browser selection to open-link-confirmation. Users will be able to choose Tor Browser or Mullvad Browser with VPN for suspicious links. To have Tor Browser in the list, you can pre-install torbrowser-launcher in Kicksecure or use only torbrowser-launcher for Tor Browser installation from “browser choice” (manual installation from the site <a href="https://www.torproject.org/download/" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Tor Project | Download</a> does not add the browser to bin)</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Thank you!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/browser-choice/1025#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 13:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2532</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 17.3.9.2 - Testers Wanted!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Expected. See <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Systemcheck#Build_Version">Build Version</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-3-9-2-testers-wanted/1023#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 10:06:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2531</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 17.3.9.2 - Testers Wanted!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@kicksecure]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b" title="VirtualBox_Kick_05_05_2025_12_12_24.png"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b_2_690x334.jpeg" alt="VirtualBox_Kick_05_05_2025_12_12_24.png" data-base62-sha1="5VP1RT7YJAQap4BQvJcCssSyu39" width="690" height="334" srcset="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b_2_690x334.jpeg, https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b_2_1035x501.jpeg 1.5x, https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/29942ba6ba94187a037f56e43fdc3b4b249a1a0b.jpeg 2x" data-dominant-color="404040"></a></div><p></p>
<p>I have tried to use all of Kicksecure repositories (including Testers and Developers) I switched using GUI tool but full-upgrade haven’t chabged anything - Kicksecure version is still 17.2.8.5. Was I doing something wrong?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-3-9-2-testers-wanted/1023#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 09:19:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2530</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello</p>
<p>Yes, please add Startpage button. I love Startpage and Kicksecure homepage. Its great to have arsenal of the best search engines on homepage - its faster and easier then bookmarks with different search engines. Many users hide bookmarks on startup tab.<br>
Homepage background is too bright and hurts eyes when launching browser in the evening or at night - at night want to close page faster to save eyes. Maybe elephant at sunset? And you can add ‘<em>functionality, reviews, cybersecurity manuals , solutions to known problems</em>’ to doc search. Kicksecure documentation and wiki are very cool - its more than just technical documentation. There is a lot of unique info about cybersecurity and privacy. New users will not only see in browser where to look for error solutions, but they will also want to learn more about cybersecurity - perhaps they will change their views on many topics, as happened to me. In various chats users often ask where they can read in detail about cybersecurity and I recommend Kicksecure / Whonix wiki. Patrick, you’ve done an excellent job!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 09:07:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2529</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>So in summary:</p>
<ul>
<li>We don’t have a list of things to shred;</li>
<li>the list keeps changing over time;
<ul>
<li>for example, this had been identified <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/304" class="inline-onebox">Disable PStore by raja-grewal · Pull Request #304 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a>;</li>
<li>unknown unknowns;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Computer storage hardware is not designed with non-persistence and anti-forensics as a primary goal in mind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Conclusion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The most secure way to avoid data persistence is to avoid data ever being written, ideally combined with <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Read-only">Read-Only: Setting Hard Drives to Read-Only</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="9" data-topic="1021" data-full="true">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I saw comparison of Tails and grub-live. Does this table apply only to Kicksecure on host and vm? Or does it also apply to Kicksecure-usb in grub-live mode?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Added to <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live" class="inline-onebox">grub-live - boot an existing Host OS or VM into Live Mode</a> documented just now:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This wiki page documents grub-live mostly as a standalone software package outside the context of Kicksecure. Any elements related to Kicksecure are clearly marked as such (“Kicksecure feature”).</p>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:24:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2528</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I failed to provide enough context for wear leveling. Disk damage is not the main issue. The main issue is, that disk shredding can be ineffective.</p>
<p>The problem is that the hard drive is not just a hard drive. It’s a its own “computer” with a complex firmware (operating system).</p>
<p>The issue with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wear_leveling" class="inline-onebox">Wear leveling - Wikipedia</a> is that the disk controller tells the kernel “file deleted” while in reality the sector has been marked unusable but still contains data, which can be recovered by data recovery professionals with low level disk controller commands. This is documented here in more detail:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Full_Disk_Encryption#Advice_for_Solid-state_Drives_and_USB_Storage">Advice for Solid-state Drives and USB Storage</a></p>
<p>(And that’s the link I should have used.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:10:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2527</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I saw comparison of Tails and grub-live. Does this table apply only to Kicksecure on host and vm? Or does it also apply to Kicksecure-usb in grub-live mode?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:09:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2526</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Shredding is effective against forensics - military uses it. but yes, frequent shredding damages ssd</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 05:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2525</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>As for the search engine websites, I am inviting comments.</p>
<p>As for the style, our web developer will look into this.</p>
<p>Thank you for all your support!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 05:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2524</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>As stated in <a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Technical_Introduction#Forensics">Forensics</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Unfortunately, these methods are not a sufficient substitute. It is manifestly unsafe to try and deal with data by wiping it after it has already been stored, so this is a poor design principle to implement.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wear_leveling" class="inline-onebox">Wear leveling - Wikipedia</a> is one reason for that.</p>
<p>The most secure way to avoid data persistence is to avoid data ever being written, ideally combined with <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Read-only" class="inline-onebox">Read-Only: Setting Hard Drives to Read-Only</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 03:57:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2523</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Yes, that would be a very convenient solution, since firefox esr does not have startpage search by default. And <a href="https://searx.space/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://searx.space/</a> is also very useful. It is very convenient to have such buttons at hand when launching browser.</p>
<p>And maybe it would be worth changing elephant pic to a darker one so that buttons at top and  doc search are more contrasting and stand out better agains white clouds? Perhaps this way users will more often search for solutions to popular documented problems in documentation (visual memory will remember doc search on the homepage). Sorry if I am too picky about aesthetic. I love elephants and I greatly appreciate your fantastic work. All my friends are using Kicksecure now. Sometimes my friends (new users to Linux and Kicksecure) ask me about some problem. I tell them, “on browser’s homepage, there is a search for documentation, and it seems there is an instruction there to solve your problem”, and they respond “Yeah, right, I hadnt paid attention to this search before. It blends with background”</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 16:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2522</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Can practice of deleting VMs and clearing host log with overwriting (shredding) be called antiforensic? I understand that deleting log has two sides - logs are important for finding possible errors, but it is also metadata for forensic experts</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 15:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2521</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 17.3.9.2 - Testers Wanted!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <h1><a name="p-2519-download-1" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-download-1"></a>Download</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/ISO#testers_Xfce">ISO: testers-only</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/VirtualBox#testers_Xfce">VirtualBox: testers-only</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/KVM#testers_Xfce">KVM: testers-only</a></li>
<li>Qubes: <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-template-for-qubes-testers-wanted/1020" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure Template for Qubes - Testers Wanted!</a></li>
</ul>
<p>(<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Point_Release">What is a point release?</a>)</p>
<p>Testers wanted!</p>
<hr>
<h1><a name="p-2519-upgrade-2" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-upgrade-2"></a>Upgrade</h1>
<p>Already using Kicksecure? No need to reinstall — perform an in-place upgrade using the <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Project-APT-Repository">Kicksecure repository</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>This milestone was made possible thanks to the incredible support from our community. Thank you!</p>
<hr>
<p>Please Donate!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:43AM - 10 October 2024">Kicksecure – 10 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/432;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/83/Payment.jpg?version=82f3e45ee49a6c0df81431424ee3fc2f" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="432"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Donating to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>PayPal, Bitcoin (BTC), Monero (XMR), Ethereum (ETH) or Token, Credit Card, Bank Wire, Others</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>Get Involved — Please Contribute!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:02AM - 15 August 2024">Kicksecure – 15 Aug 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:483/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/07/Computer_n_screen.png?version=b6cc9963027950ad5fd1793106674efb" class="thumbnail" width="483" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contribute to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Spread, Follow, Develop, Testing, Donate. Contribute to Freedom Software / Open Source.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<h1><a name="p-2519-major-changes-3" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-major-changes-3"></a>Major Changes</h1>
<h2><a name="p-2519-user-sysmaint-split-4" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-user-sysmaint-split-4"></a>user-sysmaint-split</h2>
<p>Kicksecure Xfce now defaults to a safer split-user model: one account for daily use (<code>user</code>) and another for admin tasks (<code>sysmaint</code>). This limits the impact of potential malware and strengthens system security. Power users can opt into Unrestricted Admin Mode if needed.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="11:45AM - 01 May 2025">Kicksecure – 1 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:296/309;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/b/b6/Usersysmaint-clipart.svg?version=c0aee9a72c0744c445d88f4771b19f69" class="thumbnail" width="78" height="81"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sysmaint - System Maintenance User</a></h3>

  <p>sysmaint</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/user-sysmaint-split">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/user-sysmaint-split" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="01:31PM - 02 May 2025">Kicksecure – 2 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:603/431;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/d/da/Grub-boot-icon.jpg?version=8fdbc5daa071a656285f5e8da945d797" class="thumbnail" width="603" height="431"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/user-sysmaint-split" target="_blank" rel="noopener">user-sysmaint-split</a></h3>

  <p>user-sysmaint-split - Role-Based Boot Modes - USER Session / SYSMAINT Session (system maintenance)</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:42PM - 25 April 2025">Kicksecure – 25 Apr 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unrestricted Admin Mode</a></h3>

  <p>Kicksecure allows configuration for unrestricted admin mode, enabling the default user account to access privilege escalation tools like sudo and pkexec.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<h2><a name="p-2519-system-maintenance-panel-5" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-system-maintenance-panel-5"></a>System Maintenance Panel</h2>
<p>A user-friendly interface for essential system tasks: update software, manage user accounts, configure autologin, change passwords, and run systemcheck, all in one place and designed for sysmaint sessions.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-sudoless-6" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-sudoless-6"></a>sudoless</h2>
<p>The <code>user</code> account no longer has access to <code>sudo</code> or other privilege escalation tools. Only dedicated admin accounts like <code>sysmaint</code> can perform such actions, reducing the attack surface and improving security.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-privleap-7" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-privleap-7"></a>privleap</h2>
<p>A new security-focused privilege escalation framework replacing <code>sudo</code>. It allows only specific, pre-approved actions to be executed with elevated rights, reducing the risk of misuse or exploitation. SUID-free.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-updatecheck-8" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-updatecheck-8"></a>updatecheck</h2>
<p>A new background service periodically checks for software updates and alerts users via passive popups. (<a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/notifications-about-new-updates/774" class="inline-onebox">Notifications about new updates</a>)</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-dummy-dependency-9" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-dummy-dependency-9"></a>dummy-dependency</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian_Packages#dummy-dependency">dummy-dependency</a>: Ever wanted to uninstall, for example, Firefox or Thunderbird but ran into the meta package issue? <code>dummy-dependency</code> allows the uninstallation of packages that are normally not uninstallable, without removing a (meta) package that depends on the original package.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-systemcheck-10" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-systemcheck-10"></a>systemcheck</h2>
<p>Now provides more guidance for <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks">Protection against Physical Attacks</a>. New checks include: detection of user-sysmaint-split; on host systems, notification if <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Full_Disk_Encryption">full disk encryption (FDE)</a> is set up or missing; bootloader password status; and a login security table highlighting passwordless or autologin accounts.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-virtual-hard-disk-size-increase-11" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-virtual-hard-disk-size-increase-11"></a>Virtual Hard Disk Size Increase</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grow_Virtual_Harddisk" class="inline-onebox">Virtual Hard Disk Size Increase</a> is now easier.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-permission-hardener-improvements-12" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-permission-hardener-improvements-12"></a>Permission Hardener Improvements</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SUID_Disabler_and_Permission_Hardener" class="inline-onebox">SUID Disabler and Permission Hardener</a> v2: major overhaul and improved reliability when adding/removing SUID binaries, which is important for user-sysmaint-split installation/removal.</p>
<h2><a name="p-2519-source-code-hardening-13" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-source-code-hardening-13"></a>Source Code Hardening</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unicode">unicode</a> verification</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Git#git_symlinks">git symlinks</a> verification</li>
</ul>
<h1><a name="p-2519-upcoming-changes-14" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-upcoming-changes-14"></a>Upcoming Changes</h1>
<p>It is planned to no longer install Firefox and Thunderbird by default for the next release.</p>
<p>Rationale:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Default_Browser" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure Default Browser - Development Considerations</a></p>
<p>User documentation:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Browser" class="inline-onebox">Web Browser</a></p>
<p>Instead, there will be a local browser choice application looking similar to <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/e/e2/BrowserChoice.gif">this</a>. (Not a website.) Development plan:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice" class="inline-onebox">browser choice</a></p>
<h1><a name="p-2519-changelog-15" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-changelog-15"></a>Changelog</h1>
<ul>
<li>anon-apt-sources-list:
<ul>
<li>Add Fasttrack backports-staging suite (Thanks to Ben Grande!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>anon-connection-wizard:
<ul>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>apparmor-profile-dist:
<ul>
<li>Improve live mode detection</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>debug-misc:
<ul>
<li>Remove <code>efi_pstore.pstore_disable=1</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Enable pstore processing by systemd-pstore service (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Update coredumps enabling documentation (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dist-base-files:
<ul>
<li>Add systemd-repart support (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Don’t enable systemd-repart on existing systems, ISOs, or Qubes OS (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Don’t enable systemd-repart on existing systems (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Re-organize GRUB boot menu (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>No longer adding user <code>user</code> to groups <code>cdrom</code>, <code>audio</code>, <code>dip</code>, <code>plugdev</code> as this should no longer be required</li>
<li>Set default shell to <code>zsh</code> also for <code>root</code> user</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>genmkfile:
<ul>
<li>Fix <code>genmkfile install</code> permissions</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>grub-live:
<ul>
<li>Ensure update-grub is called when switching initramfs generators (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Avoid ending up with GRUB_DEVICE being set to an invalid path (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Live mode rename: <code>For daily use.</code> → <code>disposable use</code></li>
<li>Implement <code>LIVE Mode | SYSMAINT Session</code> <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-sysmaint/979" class="inline-onebox">LIVE mode SYSMAINT</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>helper-scripts:
<ul>
<li>Add <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/use_pkexec.sh</code></li>
<li><code>stecho</code>, <code>stprintf</code>, <code>stcat</code>, <code>stcatn</code> (Thanks to Ben Grande!)</li>
<li>Rewrite append-once in Python, with enhanced error and edge case handling (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li><code>append</code>, <code>append-once</code>, <code>override</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Implemented <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unicode-show"><code>unicode-show</code></a></li>
<li><code>unicode-show</code>: enhance efficiency, show trailing whitespace (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Improved <code>grep-find-unicode-wrapper</code> to find more ASCII control characters; created test script <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/write-suspicious-ascii</code></li>
<li>Polish <code>pwchange</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li><code>crypt-pwchange</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Implement <code>grub-password-status-check</code> and <code>grub-pwchange</code></li>
<li>Use log function in terminal wrapper to show exit code status</li>
<li>Improve sanitize_variable</li>
<li>Implement <code>autologinchange</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/temp.sh</code></li>
<li>Avoid expected error message in case a Tor consensus has not been downloaded yet:
<ul>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p>ERROR: Variable ‘vstart’ is empty or contains only whitespace/newlines.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/marmarek">@marmarek</a> for the bug report! <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/systemcheck-fails-for-unclear-reason/21424/14" class="inline-onebox">Systemcheck fails for unclear reason - #14 by marmarek - Qubes-Whonix - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Add <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/live-mode.sh</code></li>
<li>anondate: Improve error handling</li>
<li>Add <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/use_sudo.sh</code></li>
<li>Add utility and library to manage accounts. Query account state, check password state, and query any entry from supported databases. (Thanks to Ben Grande!)</li>
<li>Implement <code>dummy-dependency</code></li>
<li>str_replace: improved error handling if file is not UTF-8</li>
<li>Fix <code>apt-get-update</code> for non-English locale, fixes <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/systemcheck-reports-warning-debian-package-update-check-result-apt-get-reports-that-packages-can-be-updated-but-system-is-already-fully-upgraded/785" class="inline-onebox">Systemcheck reports `WARNING: Debian Package Update Check Result: apt-get reports that packages can be updated.` but system is already fully upgraded</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>kicksecure-meta-packages:
<ul>
<li>Add xfce4-notifyd to essential GUI packages (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add sysmaint-panel to kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix Thunar icons in Kicksecure Qubes template (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make kicksecure-qubes-cli and kicksecure-qubes-gui suitable for use with qubes-whonix (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>legacy-dist:
<ul>
<li>Remove deborphan (outdated dependency) (Thanks to Jeremy Rand!)</li>
<li>Avoid auto removal of <code>qubes-core-agent-passwordless-root</code>, if it was already installed (which was previously a <code>Depends:</code>). This is to avoid breaking existing users’ workflows.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>libvirt-dist:
<ul>
<li>Improve live mode detection</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>live-config-dist:
<ul>
<li>Instruct Calamares to save GRUB configuration into /etc/default/grub.d (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make install-host compatible with classic permissions model, and take into account a sysmaint mode edge case (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Improve UX when launching the installer from a sysmaint-enabled ISO in live mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add unrestricted admin mode to ISO (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Properly install GRUB to the fallback bootloader configuration if debconf is configured for this (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>msgcollector:
<ul>
<li>msgdispatcher: add systemd watchdog support</li>
<li>Port msgdispatcher process management to systemd for code simplification, fixes <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/systemcheck-fails-for-unclear-reason/21424/19" class="inline-onebox">Systemcheck fails for unclear reason - #19 by marmarek - Qubes-Whonix - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>open-link-confirmation:
<ul>
<li>Refuse to open links in sysmaint mode and show an error message if this is attempted (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Hook web browser launch attempts via XDG on generic non-XFCE desktops (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>privleap:
<ul>
<li>New package <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/privleap" class="inline-onebox">GitHub - Kicksecure/privleap: Limited Privilege Escalation Framework</a> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ram-wipe:
<ul>
<li>Simplified installation (fixes <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/ram-wipe/issues/2#issuecomment-2813767529" class="inline-onebox">Clarify ram-wipe dependencies · Issue #2 · Kicksecure/ram-wipe · GitHub</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>repository-dist:
<ul>
<li>Output repository-dist-wizard error messages also on console in case GUI does not work (such as when starting it as root by mistake)</li>
<li>Improved error handling (such as when pkexec is unavailable)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>sdwdate:
<ul>
<li>Re-enable log watching in sdwdate-log-viewer (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add faccessat2 syscall to the whitelist (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>sdwdate-gui:
<ul>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Use a safe directory outside of /run/user/1000 for inter-qube sdwdate status communication (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>security-misc:
<ul>
<li>Fix umask for pkexec-run commands (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make <code>/usr/libexec/security-misc/apt-get-update</code> more reliable</li>
<li>/usr/libexec/security-misc/apt-get-update</li>
<li>Set <code>efi_pstore.pstore_disable=1</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Disable pstore processing by systemd-pstore service (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>No longer disable <code>vivid</code> kernel module by default, because it breaks Qubes Video Companion. Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/marmarek">@marmarek</a> for the bug report! <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/testing-qubes-video-companion-on-whonix/21393" class="inline-onebox">Testing Qubes Video Companion on Whonix - Qubes-Whonix - Whonix Forum</a> fixes <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/298" class="inline-onebox">Qubes Video Companion broken due to missing vivid kernel module · Issue #298 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>Update docs on kernel panics (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Don’t handle files with multiple hardlinks (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make permission-hardener always apply changes to real files, not symlinks (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>README.md: List CPU mitigations (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Add info on DBX updates via the UEFI Revocation List (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Add print-diagnostics command to permission-hardener (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Permission hardener: disable SUID for <code>chrome-sandbox</code></li>
<li>Permission hardener: disable SUID for <code>ssh-agent</code>, <code>ssh-keysign</code>, <code>/lib/openssh/*</code>. This might break SSH host-based authentication.</li>
<li>Enable smooth migration from permission-hardener-v1 to permission-hardener-v2 (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>README.md: Note importance of microcode updates (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Add comment about microcode updates (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Increase priority of pam wheel so it is checked even before pam faillock in case of attempting to use <code>su</code> without being a member of the required group <code>sudo</code>. It’s useful to abort the PAM stack as early as possible to avoid needlessly prompting for a password to later be rejected due to lack of group membership.</li>
<li>Fix: apply PAM wheel only to <code>su</code> PAM service</li>
<li>Adjust pam-info messaging for sysmaint mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add warning about using non-sysmaint accounts in sysmaint mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Move from <code>/etc/permission-hardener.d</code> to <code>/usr/lib/permission-hardener.d</code></li>
<li>Permission hardener: also parse <code>/usr/lib/permission-hardener.d/*.conf</code> folder</li>
<li>Add link to tabular comparison of CPU mitigations (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Set <code>net.ipv4.conf.*.drop_gratuitous_arp=1</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Set <code>net.ipv4.conf.*.arp_ignore=2</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Set <code>net.ipv4.conf.*.arp_filter=1</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Set <code>net.ipv4.conf.*.shared_media=0</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Add sysmaint account lock detection (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Update presentation on user namespaces (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Enable <code>kvm.mitigate_smt_rsb=1</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Enable <code>kvm-intel.vmentry_l1d_flush=always</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Refactor CPU mitigations (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li><code>arp_ignore</code>: Add reference to 2024-12-10 Mullvad VPN audit details (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Permission hardener: treat <code>mount</code> the same way we treat <code>umount</code>. Thanks to <span class="mention">@the-moog</span> for the bug report! fixes <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/284" class="inline-onebox">default SUID for umount (un-mount) may be incorrect · Issue #284 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>Permission hardener: <code>mount</code> chmod change from <code>745</code> to <code>755</code>, fixes <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/284" class="inline-onebox">default SUID for umount (un-mount) may be incorrect · Issue #284 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>Enable <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Strong_Linux_User_Account_Isolation#umask_hardening">umask hardening</a> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Provide option to deny sending and receiving shared media redirects (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Provide option to harden response to ARP requests (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Provide option to enable ARP filtering (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Provide option to drop gratuitous ARP packets (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>setup-dist:
<ul>
<li>Add warning about passwordless users (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Remove bitrotten easyorca code (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>setup-wizard-dist:
<ul>
<li>Remove distutils (outdated dependency) (Thanks to Jeremy Rand!)</li>
<li>Simplify Kicksecure version detection code</li>
<li>Do not start in live mode</li>
<li>Improve detection of which Kicksecure version to run setup-wizard-dist</li>
<li>Improve grub-live detection</li>
<li>Enable wizard for Kicksecure, refuse to run in live mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add autologin documentation; make links actually work rather than just wiping the text view when clicked (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>swap-file-creator:
<ul>
<li>Improve live mode detection code</li>
<li>Fix printf error message on non-English locales by setting <code>LC_ALL=C</code> environment variable. Thanks to <span class="mention">@Decidable3</span> for the bug report! <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/swap-file-creator-error/21128" class="inline-onebox">swap file creator error - Support - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>sysmaint-panel: (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)
<ul>
<li>repository-dist-wizard button</li>
<li>Linux user account password change button</li>
<li>Disk passphrase management button</li>
<li>Bootloader password changer button</li>
<li>Data persistence info</li>
<li>APT software management features (install, remove, purge, dummy-dependency, search)</li>
<li>Screenlock button</li>
<li>autologinchange button</li>
<li>systemcheck button</li>
<li>Open terminal emulator button</li>
<li>Remove user-sysmaint-split support if booting into remove user-sysmaint-split</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>systemcheck:
<ul>
<li>Detect user versus sysmaint session</li>
<li>Check if user-sysmaint-split is installed</li>
<li>Improve offline support (for example, if networking has not been set up yet):
<ul>
<li>Check if external network interface can be detected. This is done by checking the output of the command <code>ip -o addr show scope global</code>.</li>
<li>This is only a local command; it does not connect to any servers on the internet</li>
<li>This avoids waiting for a long systemcheck timeout</li>
<li>If there is an external network interface but actual internet connectivity is broken (for example due to router issues), this is not detected yet</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>No longer terminate early if:
<ul>
<li>Unsupported virtualizer has been detected</li>
<li>Control port filter proxy could not be found</li>
<li>Clock issues</li>
<li>Firewall issues</li>
<li>Tor not running</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Add updatecheck</li>
<li>Check if full disk encryption (FDE) is enabled</li>
<li>Check if a bootloader password has been set, if running on host operating system only (not inside VMs), see also <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Bootloader_Password">bootloader password</a></li>
<li>Add login security table (point out passwordless and autologin accounts) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Exit non-zero when unexpected non-freedom packages are found (function <code>check_non_freedom</code> only runs when using <code>--verbose</code>)</li>
<li>Exit non-zero if derivative repository is disabled</li>
<li>Ignore false positive messages, fixes <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/systemcheck-fails-for-unclear-reason/21424/2" class="inline-onebox">Systemcheck fails for unclear reason - #2 by Patrick - Qubes-Whonix - Whonix Forum</a> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/marmarek">@marmarek</a>)</li>
<li>Add a new test to check if TMP and TMPDIR environment variables are correctly set when running privleap</li>
<li>Show output of <code>vrms</code> only if using verbose level 2 and above</li>
<li>Exit non-zero when using <code>--verbose</code> and when unexpected error log files exist or unexpected messages in the systemd journal exist</li>
<li>Improve output of check journal (when using <code>--verbose</code>)</li>
<li>Check privleap configuration (<code>privleap --check-config</code>)</li>
<li>Check sudo using privleap</li>
<li>Test both <code>sudo</code> and <code>leaprun</code></li>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tb-starter:
<ul>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tb-updater:
<ul>
<li>OCSP is deprecated upstream</li>
<li>Ensure the user’s .cache folder isn’t owned by root (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>No longer supporting Heikki Lindholm SourceForge Tor Browser ARM64 version because it is unmaintained. <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/arm64-tor-browser/11806/21" class="inline-onebox">ARM64 Tor Browser - #21 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>timesanitycheck:
<ul>
<li>Update minimum_unixtime</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tirdad:
<ul>
<li>Declare tirdad only available for Intel/AMD64 <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/tcp-isn-cpu-information-leak-protection-tirdad/8552/33" class="inline-onebox">TCP ISN CPU Information Leak Protection - tirdad - #33 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tor-control-panel:
<ul>
<li>Port to privleap (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tor-ctrl:
<ul>
<li>Hardening (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Hardcode Tor cookie path to <code>/run/tor/control.authcookie</code> for better security</li>
<li>tor-ctrl-onion: fix <code>-k</code>, <code>-u</code>, <code>-x</code></li>
<li>Disable colors in tor-ctrl-stream for better security</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>usability-misc:
<ul>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Do not hide xtrace when started with bash -x (xtrace). It is therefore no longer required to get xtrace from debug file.</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Fix Fedora 42 package installation (Thanks to Ben Grande!)</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Fix VirtualBox downgrade (Thanks to Ben Grande!)</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Install fasttrack keyring only if needed, because it fails on testing and unstable, where the package is unavailable</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Fix install failure when using <code>--onion</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: Bugfixes, cleanup shellcheck overrides, improve robustness (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add error message when trying to run upgrade-nonroot as a normal user when user-sysmaint-split is installed (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>user-sysmaint-split:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint" class="inline-onebox">sysmaint - System Maintenance User</a></li>
<li>Tint sysmaint terminal red (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add PERSISTENT mode SYSMAINT Session boot mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Lock the sysmaint account on system shutdown (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Minimal sysmaint-boot.target (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>vm-config-dist:
<ul>
<li>Only if ‘OpenGL renderer string’ is ‘llvmpipe’ according to ‘glxinfo’, then set environment variable <code>QMLSCENE_DEVICE=softwarecontext</code>.
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/monero-integration-in-whonix/5949/93" class="inline-onebox">Monero Integration in Whonix - #93 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/monero-project/monero-gui/issues/2878" class="inline-onebox">Automatic fallback to softwarecontext renderer · Issue #2878 · monero-project/monero-gui · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/monero-project/monero-gui/pull/4419" class="inline-onebox">Enforce whonix opengl renderer by everoddandeven · Pull Request #4419 · monero-project/monero-gui · GitHub</a></li>
<li>Thanks to <span class="mention">@everoddandeven</span> for mentioning <code>glxinfo</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>derivative-maker:
<ul>
<li>Development towards ARM64 support (work in progress)</li>
<li>Remove GNU/Linux, CPU architecture references from live ISO boot menu (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Improve build speed: avoid unnecessary initramfs builds</li>
<li>Error out earlier when building workstation without corresponding gateway, because otherwise the build would fail very late at dm-prepare-release during creation of the unified image <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/whonix-on-mac-m1-arm-development-discussion/14136/67" class="inline-onebox">Whonix on Mac M1 (ARM) - Development Discussion - #67 by LoftyGoals - Development - Whonix Forum</a></li>
<li>Delete no longer required <code>help-steps/vm-exists-test</code></li>
<li>Add systemd-repart support (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make sure apt-cacher-ng configuration option <code>PassThroughPattern: .*</code> is set</li>
<li>Remove libpam-tmpdir from include_opt because grml-debootstrap is nowadays functional if libpam-tmpdir is installed on the host, thanks to its clean_chroot function</li>
<li>Remove grub2-common from include_opt because grml-debootstrap handles that nowadays</li>
<li>Delete utm folder after utm archive creation to save disk space</li>
<li>Sudo setup: write <code>Defaults:%$USER runcwd=*</code> to <code>/etc/sudoers.d/derivative-maker</code> to fix sudo error when using <code>$SUDO_TO_VBOX_TEMP</code>
<ul>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p>sudo: you are not permitted to use the -D option</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Use <code>sudo</code> with <code>-D $HOMEVAR_VBOX_TEMP</code> (<code>--chdir</code>) to avoid <code>VBoxManage</code> error: &gt; VBoxManage: error: Could not create the directory ‘.’ (VERR_ACCESS_DENIED)</li>
<li>Implement function <code>chroot_run</code></li>
<li>Replace <code>chroot</code> command with <code>chroot_run</code> function</li>
<li>Replace <code>$CHROOT</code> variable with <code>chroot_run</code> function</li>
<li>Add <code>help-steps/apt-cacher-ng-reset</code></li>
<li>Disable no longer needed workaround use_vmefi_maybe</li>
<li>Make compatible with latest grml-debootstrap code (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Use flavor_meta_packages_to_install for ISO builds (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix <code>--remote-derivative-packages true</code></li>
<li>Attempt installing GRUB with env var (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Add debug block for command failure (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Rework build script for UTM build (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Check for apt-cacher-ng start with netcat (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Rework entrypoint script to run as builder (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Handle systemctl service for Docker Apple Silicon builds (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Add working solution with entrypoint script instead of service manager (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Attempt to run apt-cacher-ng with supervisord (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Remove apt-cacher-ng for Docker (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Attempt apt-cacher-ng without systemd (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Add initial Dockerfile (Thanks to Rob Stringer!)</li>
<li>Fix construction of PATH variable. Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a> for the bug report!</li>
<li>Add isomd5sum to the live package list for the Kicksecure ISO (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Support unusual PATH variables</li>
<li>Fix PATH variable if it lacks sbin</li>
<li>Update for newer live-build (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Improve check for stray mounts</li>
<li>Expand PATH environment variable so grml-debootstrap will use help-steps/mmdebstrap wrapper</li>
<li>Turn on user-sysmaint-split on ISO images (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Install <code>user-sysmaint-split</code> by default on Kicksecure Xfce</li>
<li>Add Qubes templates submodules</li>
<li>Add Qubes templates source code git modules qubes/qubes-template-kicksecure and qubes/qubes-template-whonix to make them easier to discover / search the source code</li>
<li>Remove --hard-links from rsync_opts</li>
<li>Kicksecure VM build process: make sure host system files such as <code>/etc/resolv.conf</code> do not leak into the image</li>
<li>ARM64 build fix: install qemu-user-static from backports</li>
<li>VirtualBox 7.0 → 7.1 version upgrade (only when using opt-in to use Oracle repository)</li>
<li>Fix compatibility with umask hardening (<code>umask 027</code>)</li>
<li>Create Debian package and install live-build instead of using “make install” to avoid permission issues</li>
<li>Configure GRUB to install itself to the fallback bootloader location (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>No longer install dracut-config-rescue as it actually does not have any effect</li>
<li>Enable checksumming for Kicksecure ISO (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>grml-debootstrap:
<ul>
<li>Fixed <a href="https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/issues/297" class="inline-onebox">UEFI bootloader updates seem broken · Issue #297 · grml/grml-debootstrap · GitHub</a> (<a href="https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/pull/299" class="inline-onebox">Make bootloader updates on UEFI-based systems work by ArrayBolt3 · Pull Request #299 · grml/grml-debootstrap · GitHub</a>) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/issues/219" class="inline-onebox">avoid unicode in source code if reasonably avoidable · Issue #219 · grml/grml-debootstrap · GitHub</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h1><a name="p-2519-full-difference-of-all-changes-16" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2519-full-difference-of-all-changes-16"></a>Full difference of all changes</h1>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.2.8.5-developers-only...17.3.9.2-developers-only">https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.2.8.5-developers-only…17.3.9.2-developers-only</a></p>
<hr>
<p>(This testers wanted announcement might in future be <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/transform-whonix-testers-wanted-forum-news-post-into-whonix-release-forum-news-post-ok/11405">transformed</a> into a stable release announcement if no major issues are found during the testing period.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-3-9-2-testers-wanted/1023#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:35:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2519</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Kicksecure for Qubes: For Qubes OS, the process may not work as expected. For further details, refer to the related Qubes feature request <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/4982">Implement live boot by porting grub-live to Qubes - amnesia / non-persistent boot / anti-forensics</a><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/4982"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/73/Internet_Archive_logo.png" alt="archive.org icon" width="14" height="16"></a><a href="https://archive.today/https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/4982"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/8f/Archive-today-logo-homage.svg" alt="archive.today icon" width="12" height="16"></a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="4" data-topic="1021">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Does this mean snapshots can solve problem with amnesia?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<ul>
<li>Non-persistence, yes. You can easily delete App Qubes.</li>
<li>Anti-forensics, no. Disposable VMs, App Qubes, snapshots are not an anti-forensics features. Qubes - to my knowledge - does not make any claims about anti-forensics.</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="4" data-topic="1021">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>and how much can this script replace live mode for Kicksecure in Qubes?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It’s just a simple shell script running commands. If something goes wrong, cleanup will not be done. Quote from the script source code:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">qvm-run -a "${QUBE_NAME}" "${BROWSER}"
wait
</code></pre>
<p>If something happens and the script does not continue (such as power loss), data will persist and not be automatically cleaned up. Commands such as:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">qvm-remove -f "${QUBE_NAME}"
qvm-pool rm shadowy
sudo umount shadowy
sudo rm -rf "${TMP_DIR}" \
        /var/log/libvirt/1ibx1/new.log \
</code></pre>
<p>Will not be executed.</p>
<p>Writing data to the disk and cleaning up later is an insecure approach to non-persistence and anti-forensics.</p>
<p>I don’t know if there are any reviews of that script and it also seems it’s not part of Qubes and hasn’t been attempted to upstream to Qubes. Therefore I would be cautious.</p>
<p>There are no shortcuts. The only serious solution would be for Qubes to properly implement functionality to not write data that should not persist to the disk.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 06:02:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2515</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Patrick, can you explain this question - in wiki is written that Qubes has problems with amnesia for Whonix and Kicksecure due to problems with launching live mode. But it is also written in wiki that VM snapshots work better than live mode, and in Qubes snapshots are simple and convenient. Does this mean snapshots can solve problem with amnesia? or did I misunderstand something?</p>
<p>and how much can this script replace live mode for Kicksecure in Qubes? <a href="https://github.com/kennethrrosen/qubes-shadow-dvm" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - kennethrrosen/qubes-shadow-dvm: Simple dom0 bash script inspired by Unman's 'Really Disposable Qubes' scripts</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 13:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2514</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you Patrick. Using Kicksecure-host seems to be the best solution for protecting amnesic VM from forensic analysis. Kicksecure has kernel dump disabled by default, swap is not enabled by default, and in future you will add user-session mode (read-only). And host log deletion.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="1" data-topic="1021">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think that the metadata in log does not pose a threat, otherwise you would not created Whonix and Kicksecure as virtual machines</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I meant that if live function in VM didn’t make sense, you wouldn’t have added this to Whonix and Kicksecure. Yes, this is not full protection from forensic, but it significantly complicates it. Otherwise, you would simply recommend using VM snapshots or USB-live.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 08:46:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2513</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="1" data-topic="1021">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think that the metadata in log does not pose a threat, otherwise you would not created Whonix and Kicksecure as virtual machines.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>No, that doesn’t follow. See history:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/History" class="inline-onebox">History - Kicksecure</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/History" class="inline-onebox">History - Whonix</a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>The foundational vision for Whonix was to employ (virtual) machines in a manner that would guarantee all internet traffic was reliably and exclusively channeled through Tor, offering robust protection against IP address and DNS leaks.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Whonix was founded in 2012.</p>
<p>Discussions on <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/whonix-live-mode-amnesia-amnesic-non-persistent-anti-forensics/3894" class="inline-onebox">Whonix live mode / amnesia / amnesic / non-persistent / anti-forensics - Development - Whonix Forum</a> started in 2017.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="1" data-topic="1021">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If I delete these virtual machines, what level of danger exists in case of forensic examination?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>See:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Live_Mode#Anti-Forensics">VM Live Mode chapter Anti-Forensics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Anti-Forensics_Precautions" class="inline-onebox">VM Live Mode: Anti-forensics Precautions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live#Security_Considerations">grub-live wiki pager chapter Security Considerations</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 04:02:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2512</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Forensic after deleting VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello. I am using Kicksecure and Whonix on a virtual machine. Usually, I use live mode. If I delete these virtual machines, what level of danger exists in case of forensic examination? Or do these metadata not pose any danger? I understand that the best option would be to use Kicksecure-host in live mode, but I am interested in your opinion on virtual machines. Disk of course encrypted. There are many opinions on this topic. But you are the best security experts and I am very interested in your opinion. I think that the metadata in log does not pose a threat, otherwise you would not created Whonix and Kicksecure as virtual machines. But your answer is very important to me. Thank you</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/forensic-after-deleting-vms/1021#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 18:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2511</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Newer VirtualBox setting interface looks ugly on xfce</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1019" data-full="true">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>This is probably a Qt 6 configuration problem, as newer versions of VirtualBox use Qt 6. It’s likely not VirtualBox’s fault.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It has already been posted on vbox forum . The answers are far from the solution</p>
<p><a href="https://forums.virtualbox.org/viewtopic.php?t=113399" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://forums.virtualbox.org/viewtopic.php?t=113399</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/newer-virtualbox-setting-interface-looks-ugly-on-xfce/1019#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 14:14:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2510</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Newer VirtualBox setting interface looks ugly on xfce</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>always problems after solved problems<br>
very sad</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/newer-virtualbox-setting-interface-looks-ugly-on-xfce/1019#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 21:03:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2509</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Newer VirtualBox setting interface looks ugly on xfce</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>This is probably a Qt 6 configuration problem, as newer versions of VirtualBox use Qt 6. It’s likely not VirtualBox’s fault.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/newer-virtualbox-setting-interface-looks-ugly-on-xfce/1019#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 12:43:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2508</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Newer VirtualBox setting interface looks ugly on xfce</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Report to upstream <code>virtualbox.org</code> as per:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1745919025" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:10AM - 06 September 2024">Kicksecure – 6 Sep 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:250/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/74/Booster132.png?version=45557debf593fbb24d26970c477f16db" class="thumbnail" width="250" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Potential Solutions Beyond Kicksecure!</a></h3>

  <p>Explore resources outside of Kicksecure to address unspecific questions or issues.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1745919025" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:21AM - 25 October 2024">Kicksecure – 25 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:666/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/c/c6/Self-support.jpg?version=ff7bb4e369079801406f79a2ab8db191" class="thumbnail" width="666" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Definition of the Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/newer-virtualbox-setting-interface-looks-ugly-on-xfce/1019#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 11:06:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2507</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Template for Qubes - Testers Wanted!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Testers wanted!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Qubes">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Qubes" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:11PM - 27 April 2025">Kicksecure – 27 Apr 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/2/2a/Download-qubes.jpg?version=b32bca55e3a831e51fc67de6018efa96" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Qubes" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kicksecure for Qubes</a></h3>

  <p>Using Kicksecure-Qubes</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> This Template now includes a new security feature, <code>user-sysmaint-split</code>, enabled by default.</p>
<p>It is <strong>strongly recommended</strong> to review the feature’s documentation:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="11:45AM - 01 May 2025">Kicksecure – 1 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:296/309;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/b/b6/Usersysmaint-clipart.svg?version=c0aee9a72c0744c445d88f4771b19f69" class="thumbnail" width="78" height="81"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sysmaint - System Maintenance User</a></h3>

  <p>sysmaint</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p><strong>About <code>user-sysmaint-split</code>:</strong><br>
This security enhancement separates daily user activities from system maintenance tasks. The regular <code>user</code> account can no longer use <code>sudo</code>, <code>su</code>, or <code>pkexec</code> by default. Instead, administrative rights are reserved for a dedicated system maintenance account (<code>sysmaint</code>), reducing security risks during daily use.</p>
<p>Attempting to use <code>sudo</code> as the regular user will result in an error message:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">sudo test
</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p>zsh: permission denied: sudo<br>
zsh: exit 126   sudo test</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To gain administrative (“<code>root</code>”) rights, users can either use a <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Root#Qubes_Root_Console">Qubes Root Console</a> or disable <code>user-sysmaint-split</code> by enabling unrestricted admin mode:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:42PM - 25 April 2025">Kicksecure – 25 Apr 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unrestricted Admin Mode</a></h3>

  <p>Kicksecure allows configuration for unrestricted admin mode, enabling the default user account to access privilege escalation tools like sudo and pkexec.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>This release would not have been possible without the numerous supporters of Kicksecure!</p>
<hr>
<p>Please Donate!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:43AM - 10 October 2024">Kicksecure – 10 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/432;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/83/Payment.jpg?version=82f3e45ee49a6c0df81431424ee3fc2f" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="432"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Donating to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>PayPal, Bitcoin (BTC), Monero (XMR), Ethereum (ETH) or Token, Credit Card, Bank Wire, Others</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>Please Contribute!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1746351024" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:02AM - 15 August 2024">Kicksecure – 15 Aug 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:483/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/07/Computer_n_screen.png?version=b6cc9963027950ad5fd1793106674efb" class="thumbnail" width="483" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contribute to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Spread, Follow, Develop, Testing, Donate. Contribute to Freedom Software / Open Source.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>(This testers wanted announcement might in future be <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/transform-whonix-testers-wanted-forum-news-post-into-whonix-release-forum-news-post-ok/11405">transformed</a> into a stable release announcement if no major issues are found during the testing period.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-template-for-qubes-testers-wanted/1020#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:35:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2506</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Newer VirtualBox setting interface looks ugly on xfce</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/7437b35a23d9e26f0be24663be6634a4b2fc4fe6.png" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/7437b35a23d9e26f0be24663be6634a4b2fc4fe6" title="ugly"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/7437b35a23d9e26f0be24663be6634a4b2fc4fe6.png" alt="ugly" data-base62-sha1="gA6IV9isqfCjSVBDShfIcyTaabQ" width="376" height="335"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Virtualbox 7.1 display issue with unselected boxes</p>
<p>Older version looks better</p>
<p>Boxes looks normal only when selected.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/newer-virtualbox-setting-interface-looks-ugly-on-xfce/1019#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 09:13:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2505</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Update VirtualBox guest additions</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>In the VirtualBox UI, click <code>Devices -&gt; Insert Guest Additions CD image</code></p>
<p>Is this the ISO that shipped with host vbox software?</p>
<p>There is another option in vbox<br>
In the VirtualBox UI, click `Devices → <strong>Update</strong> Guest<br>
Additions</p>
<p>Will this just update the ISO or update installed additions inside guest?</p>
<p>Its not clear on vbox user guide</p>
<p>On host synaptic manager there is another guest addition iso .not installed. Version not known .h</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/update-virtualbox-guest-additions/1018#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 15:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2504</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Update VirtualBox guest additions</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Optional usablity feature: <code>vbox-guest-installer</code></p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/VirtualBox/Guest_Additions#vbox-guest-installer">vbox-guest-installer</a> is an installation helper created by Kicksecure developers. It is a helper utility for better usability that allows to install <em>VirtualBox guest additions</em> from Debian’s (<code>packages.debian.org</code> ) package <a href="https://packages.debian.org/sid/virtualbox-guest-additions-iso"><code>virtualbox-guest-additions-iso</code></a><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/https://packages.debian.org/sid/virtualbox-guest-additions-iso"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/73/Internet_Archive_logo.png" alt="archive.org icon" width="14" height="16"></a><a href="https://archive.today/https://packages.debian.org/sid/virtualbox-guest-additions-iso"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/8f/Archive-today-logo-homage.svg" alt="archive.today icon" width="12" height="16"></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But due to the issue of VirtualBox and virtualbox-guest-additions-iso being outdated in <a href="http://packages.debian.org">packages.debian.org</a> at the time of writing (issue described here in detail: <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/whonix-virtualbox-integration-and-upgrades/11705/39" class="inline-onebox">Whonix VirtualBox Integration and Upgrades - #39 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a>)…</p>
<p><code>vbox-guest-installer</code> might get a feature / documentation to support installing VirtualBox guest additions using an ISO downloaded from the <a href="http://virtualbox.org">virtualbox.org</a> website.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/update-virtualbox-guest-additions/1018#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 11:05:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2503</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
