<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>Failed to start systemd-repart.service - Repartition Root Disk</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nOrphf]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi</p>
<p>Can anyone help, with why my VM’s show this error on boot?<br>
Everything works as expected though, except, but might not be related, many reboots hang on the “Invalid DMI field header” and I have to reset/stop-start the VM.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/49a61e63cbe03d7de7eafa43c178b1706859401e.png" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/49a61e63cbe03d7de7eafa43c178b1706859401e" title="image"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/49a61e63cbe03d7de7eafa43c178b1706859401e.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="avwLj7luISzYzWqaK9ep4hO5EK2" width="690" height="438" data-dominant-color="050505"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Running VirtualBox on Windows 11.<br>
Guest OS is newest Kicksecure/whonix</p>
<p>Please let me know what info I can provide. I still new to Linux troubleshooting, so not sure what makes sense to post as info.</p>
<p>[EDIT]<br>
I noticed the Swap file notice, and have since given the VM more memory.<br>
The info is gone, but the error is still present.<br>
[/EDIT]</p>
<p>Regards Lars</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/failed-to-start-systemd-repart-service-repartition-root-disk/1211#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 21:40:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3189</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live mode in Qubes 4.3?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you!!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-in-qubes-4-3/1207#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 17:20:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3186</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live mode in Qubes 4.3?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I was hopeful it would allow that, but unfortunately it doesn’t <em>yet</em>. Live mode requires using an in-VM kernel with Dracut, and boot modes are only supported when using a dom0-provided kernel right now. There is ongoing work to get in-VM kernel support for boot modes, but it requires a GRUB patch which I’m still working on getting upstreamed and integrated into Qubes OS.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-in-qubes-4-3/1207#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 14:07:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3185</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live mode in Qubes 4.3?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@arraybolt3</a> Hello!<br>
The new feature will allow selecting the Kicksecure and Whonix boot modes in Qubes OS. Will it enable selecting live mode in AppVM?<br>
<a href="https://qubes-doc--1504.org.readthedocs.build/en/1504/developer/releases/4_3/release-notes.html#security-features" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://qubes-doc--1504.org.readthedocs.build/en/1504/developer/releases/4_3/release-notes.html#security-features</a></p><aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9920">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9920" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9920" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Allow VMs to specify boot modes as being only intended for AppVMs or templates</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-04-27" data-time="22:20:50" data-timezone="UTC">10:20PM - 27 Apr 25 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/104878738?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          ArrayBolt3
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          C: core
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          release notes
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          ux
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          P: default
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          targets-4.3
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">[How to file a helpful issue](https://www.qubes-os.org/doc/issue-tracking/)

###<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden"> The problem you're addressing (if any)

Right now any boot modes advertised by a template will be visible for both that template and any AppVMs derived from it. This might not make sense for all boot modes - Kicksecure would like to implement an "unrestricted admin" boot mode that removes the user-sysmaint-split package during early boot to allow the user full `sudo` access for that boot only. This would take advantage of the fact that rebooting an AppVM resets most of its root filesystem to make this change temporary, so that users can switch between safe and unrestricted modes. This boot mode only makes sense for AppVMs, it would be detrimental for a Kicksecure template to be booted in this way.

### The solution you'd like

Add another boot mode qvm feature class, `boot-mode.restrict.(boot-mode-name)`, which can be set to either `AppVM` or `TemplateVM`. The boot mode will then be restricted to that VM type (i.e. if the feature is set to `AppVM`, that boot mode will only be available for AppVMs, not TemplateVMs).

This could potentially be made more flexible by allowing the feature to be set to a comma-separated list of the VM types the boot mode should be supported in (AppVM, TemplateVM, DispVM, RemoteVM, etc.), but I fear that might cause problems because of the presence of AppVM default boot modes. If a template sets a boot mode that isn't supported by DispVMs as the AppVM default boot mode, what should a DispVM based upon that template do? Thus why I believe this should only allow two restriction choices. "AppVM" in the context of this option really would only mean "anything other than a TemplateVM". Perhaps the wording should be adjusted accordingly, not sure.

The only problem I can see 

### The value to a user and who that user might be

Less confusing in the user interface, users won't see boot modes that they shouldn't be using.

### Completion criteria checklist

(This section is for developer use only. Please do not modify it.)</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9750">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9750" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/9750" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Improve support for booting qubes with custom kernel command line parameters (useful for Kicksecure and Whonix user-sysmaint-split)</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-01-31" data-time="23:19:01" data-timezone="UTC">11:19PM - 31 Jan 25 UTC</span>
      </div>

        <div class="date">
          closed <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-03-26" data-time="23:12:31" data-timezone="UTC">11:12PM - 26 Mar 25 UTC</span>
        </div>

      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/104878738?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          ArrayBolt3
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          C: other
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          release notes
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          P: default
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          targets-4.3
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">### The problem you're addressing (if any)

(This is somewhat of a followup to a<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden"> conversation I had with Demi and Marek in the Qubes OS Matrix room.)

Currently, Qubes OS allows booting a Qube with special kernel command line parameters by using a special cli-only feature (sadly I can't remember the name of the tool used for this). If you don't do this, each qube is simply booted with some default command-line parameters, which are sufficient to allow the VM to boot and be usable. Thus far, this has been good enough, since each OS booted in Qubes generally doesn't have multiple boot modes that need to be supported.

With the introduction of the [user-sysmaint-split](https://github.com/kicksecure/user-sysmaint-split) feature into Kicksecure and Whonix, things have changed somewhat. As a form of defense-in-depth on top of the security Qubes and Kicksecure already provide, Kicksecure will soon offer a package (really a set of packages) that will allow separating user and root responsibilities much more strongly than usually done. The current implementation uses file permissions on the `sudo` and `pkexec` executables that makes them only able to be run by a special `sysmaint` user, which is locked by default and cannot be signed into normally. This makes `sudo` and `pkexec` completely unable to be run during a normal user session, greatly reducing the risk of a root compromise. To gain access to the `sysmaint` account, the user must physically reboot the machine and select "PERSISTENT mode SYSMAINT" from the list of boot options - doing so triggers a systemd unit that unlocks and automatically logs into the sysmaint account. For added security, most if not all non-essential services are suppressed while booted into sysmaint mode, and a very minimal desktop named [sysmaint-panel](https://github.com/kicksecure/sysmaint-panel) is provided to discourage the user from launching potentially dangerous applications like Firefox while in this mode. Users can run privileged commands even when not booted into sysmaint mode through an SUID-less privilege escalation framework called [privleap](https://github.com/Kicksecure/privleap).

This is all well and good, but right now this only works on physical hardware and traditional virtual machines (virt-manager, VirtualBox), because it requires the user to be able to boot into "sysmaint mode", which requires access to a GRUB console. Qubes VMs don't usually even use GRUB (since they share the dom0 kernel which is directly booted by Xen), and even when they do for some reason, you don't get access to the console during bootup unless you're using an HVM. This puts Qubes OS users in a bit of a sticky spot if they want to take advantage of the features offered by user-sysmaint-split. In UX terms, basically the end result is that `sudo` and `pkexec` become permanently unusable, and to get root access the user has to open up a root console either via `qvm-run` (which is dangerous because of X11) or via the "Open console in qube" feature of Qube Manager (which is secure and neat but also slow and somewhat difficult to use). Most of the "nice bits" of user-sysmaint-split are not accessible. In addition, Kicksecure templates will *also* be basically "locked down" by this, making it tricky to make changes or install software in the templates without resorting to one of the above solutions. Only AppVMs really need `sudo` and `pkexec` locked down, ideally a Kicksecure template should have full root access out of the box.

Last but not least, Qubes OS only supports specifying custom kernel parameters for a qube if that qube shares dom0's kernel. If you use a VM-internal kernel, you can't set the kernel parameters because those are hardcoded into a GRUB config file within the qube. This is a problem since Kicksecure has some interest in using qube-internal kernels by default, and obviously users may want to use custom kernels or the like without losing the ability to control (or even use) user-sysmaint-split.

### The solution you'd like

The solution I have in mind here isn't really one solution, but rather a set of them that fixes all of the paper cuts here:

* Templates should be able to specify auxiliary kernel parameters that Qubes OS should use when booting them and AppVMs based on them. Each template should be able to specify more than one set of kernel parameters, one per boot mode it supports.
* These boot modes should somehow be exposed to the end user. How exactly this should look I'm unclear on - an easy solution would be to provide a drop-down in Qube Manager's settings window that would allow selecting the boot mode the VM should use on next bootup. A potentially more usable solution would be to integrate the boot modes into the application menu somehow, but this could overcomplicate the user interface and might also be a massive pain to implement.
* Templates should be able to specify the default boot mode for themselves and the default boot mode for derived AppVMs separately. This way the Kicksecure template could be set up so that it would boot in sysmaint mode by default, while AppVMs would be booted in user mode by default. This would allow the Kicksecure template to be used in an intuitive fashion similar to most existing templates.
* There should be some way to boot a VM with dom0-specified kernel parameters *even if* you're booting using a qube-internal kernel. Demi, Marek, and I had a pretty long discussion about how this could be done, ultimately it seems that pvgrub is the best tool to use for this, but will need some extra features for it to work.
* In a perfect world, the user should be able to define their own boot modes. That would make this rather complex suite of features be useful for much more than just Kicksecure and Whonix.

None of this is set in stone, I'm definitely open to alternate ways of implementing things that would be easier. This is obviously a very large list of features, which I intend to contribute or at least help contribute.

### The value to a user and who that user might be

user-sysmaint-split will work really, really nicely in Qubes OS. Additionally, with the ability to specify auxiliary kernel parameters in templates, Kicksecure and Whonix could use the extensive hardening parameters they use on the desktop within Qubes as well. Users who need or want to tweak their kernels and kernel config will also have much more freedom to do so, which could benefit Qubes OS devs as well as highly advanced users.

### Completion criteria checklist

_No response_</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-in-qubes-4-3/1207#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 05:11:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3183</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside KVM/qemu,Linux mint HOST OS</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nolimit]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hey I solved the problem with a guide  but it took a couple of hours  honestly, I created a bridge network setup and somehow it worked finally !</p>
<p>Thanks!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-kvm-qemu-linux-mint-host-os/1206#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 16:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3182</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>This has been implemented a while ago.</p>
<p>Documented just now. Quote <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Dracut_Emergency_Shell">Dracut Emergency Shell</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dracut">dracut</a> <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724">emergency shell is disabled by default in Kicksecure for security reasons.</a> This is implemented in file <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/blob/master/etc/default/grub.d/41_recovery_restrict.cfg"><code>/etc/default/grub.d/41_recovery_restrict.cfg</code></a>.</p>
<p>To re-enable the dracut emergency shell, which can be useful for debugging, see wiki chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Recovery_Mode">Recovery Mode</a>.</p>
<p>related forum discussion:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171" class="inline-onebox">No Rescue Mode</a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>One could say, it’s easy for a physical attacker to re-enable dracut recovery console using a kernel parameter change - which is even documented - hence defeating the purpose. That is correct - at time of writing. Protecting the kernel command line is the job of verified boot. Related:</p>
<ul>
<li>wiki: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a></li>
<li>forum: <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a></li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="6" data-topic="724">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="724">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We should make sure this doesn’t break Recovery Mode, that’s the only thing wrong I can think of with that.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Actually i would argue against that, why do we need to rely on recovery mode?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Developers need it sometimes to debug boot issues, unbootable systems or instruct users on how to do that.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="6" data-topic="724">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think of recovery mode ability is like backdooring your own OS,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Once verified boot is implemented, only the device owner shall have this capability.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 12:40:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3181</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside KVM/qemu,Linux mint HOST OS</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Which KVM libvirt XML file did you use?</p>
<p>Can be a KVM configuration issue on the host operating system.</p>
<p>Try running Debian or some other non-Kicksecure based operating system inside the VM - same issue?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-kvm-qemu-linux-mint-host-os/1206#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 09:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3180</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside KVM/qemu,Linux mint HOST OS</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>kicksecure as ISO installed or the libvirt version?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-kvm-qemu-linux-mint-host-os/1206#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 02:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3179</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside KVM/qemu,Linux mint HOST OS</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nolimit]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>hey I cant configure to get a network connection with KVM even tho It says I have a active connection and an ip but when starting the browser no internet at all… , When i run system check this error comes up</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto"> "ERROR: check network interfaces Result: No external network interface found.

Debugging information:
Command
ip -o addr show scope global
did not show any output

If this error happens only during upgrading or is transient this error can be safely ignored. 
If you know what you are doing, feel free to disable this check. Create a file /etc/systemcheck.d/50_user.conf and add: " 


And when i run systemctl this is what I get --

UNIT FILE                                                                           STATE           PRESET  
proc-sys-fs-binfmt_misc.automount                                                   static          -       
-.mount                                                                             generated       -       
boot.mount                                                                          generated       -       
dev-hugepages.mount                                                                 static          -       
dev-mqueue.mount                                                                    static          -       
proc-sys-fs-binfmt_misc.mount                                                       disabled        disabled
sys-fs-fuse-connections.mount                                                       static          -       
sys-kernel-config.mount                                                             static          -       
sys-kernel-debug.mount                                                              static          -       
sys-kernel-tracing.mount                                                            static          -       
acpid.path                                                                          enabled         enabled 
systemd-ask-password-console.path                                                   static          -       
systemd-ask-password-wall.path                                                      static          -       
session-1.scope                                                                     transient       -       
accounts-daemon.service                                                             enabled         enabled 
acpi-support.service                                                                enabled         enabled 
acpid.service                                                                       disabled        enabled 
apparmor.service                                                                    enabled         enabled 
apt-daily-upgrade.service                                                           static          -       
apt-daily.service                                                                   static          -       
autovt@.service                                                                     alias           -       
blk-availability.service                                                            enabled         enabled 
bootclockrandomization.service                                                      enabled         enabled 
canary.service                                                                      enabled         enabled 
console-getty.service                                                               disabled        disabled
console-setup.service                                                               enabled         enabled 
container-getty@.service                                                            static          -       
cryptdisks-early.service                                                            masked          enabled 
cryptdisks.service                                                                  masked          enabled 
dbus-fi.w1.wpa_supplicant1.service                                                  alias           -       
dbus-org.freedesktop.hostname1.service                                              alias           -       
dbus-org.freedesktop.locale1.service                                                alias           -       
dbus-org.freedesktop.login1.service                                                 alias           -       
dbus-org.freedesktop.nm-dispatcher.service                                          alias           -       
dbus-org.freedesktop.timedate1.service                                              alias           -       
dbus.service                                                                        static          -       
debug-shell.service                                                                 disabled        disabled
display-manager.service                                                             alias           -       
dist-skel-first-boot.service                                                        enabled         enabled 
dm-event.service                                                                    static          -       
dpkg-db-backup.service                                                              static          -       
dracut-cmdline.service                                                              static          -       
dracut-initqueue.service                                                            static          -       
dracut-mount.service                                                                static          -       
dracut-pre-mount.service                                                            static          -       
dracut-pre-pivot.service                                                            static          -       
dracut-pre-trigger.service                                                          static          -       
dracut-pre-udev.service                                                             static          -       
dracut-shutdown-onfailure.service                                                   static          -       
dracut-shutdown.service                                                             static          -       
e2scrub@.service                                                                    static          -       
e2scrub_all.service                                                                 static          -       
e2scrub_fail@.service                                                               static          -       
e2scrub_reap.service                                                                enabled         enabled 
emergency.service                                                                   static          -       
flatpak-system-helper.service                                                       static          -       
fstrim.service                                                                      static          -       
fwupd-offline-update.service                                                        static          -       
fwupd-refresh.service                                                               static          -       
fwupd.service                                                                       static          -       
gdomap.service                                                                      generated       -       
getty-static.service                                                                static          -       
getty@.service                                                                      enabled         enabled 
harden-module-loading.service                                                       disabled        disabled
haveged.service                                                                     enabled         enabled 
hide-hardware-info.service                                                          disabled        disabled
hwclock.service                                                                     masked          enabled 
initrd-cleanup.service                                                              static          -       
initrd-parse-etc.service                                                            static          -       
initrd-switch-root.service                                                          static          -       
initrd-udevadm-cleanup-db.service                                                   static          -       
jitterentropy-rngd.service                                                          alias           -       
jitterentropy.service                                                               enabled         enabled 
keyboard-setup.service                                                              enabled         enabled 
kmod-static-nodes.service                                                           static          -       
kmod.service                                                                        alias           -       
leapctl@.service                                                                    enabled         enabled 
legacy-dist.service                                                                 enabled         enabled 
lightdm.service                                                                     enabled         enabled 
live-config.service                                                                 enabled         enabled 
live-mode-apparmor.service                                                          enabled         enabled 
livecheck-lsblk.service                                                             enabled         enabled 
lm-sensors.service                                                                  enabled         enabled 
lvm2-lvmpolld.service                                                               static          -       
lvm2-monitor.service                                                                enabled         enabled 
man-db.service                                                                      static          -       
modprobe@.service                                                                   static          -       
NetworkManager-dispatcher.service                                                   enabled         enabled 
NetworkManager-wait-online.service                                                  enabled         enabled 
NetworkManager.service                                                              enabled         enabled 
nm-priv-helper.service                                                              static          -       
nvmefc-boot-connections.service                                                     enabled         enabled 
nvmf-autoconnect.service                                                            enabled         enabled 
nvmf-connect@.service                                                               static          -       
openvpn-client@.service                                                             disabled        enabled 
openvpn-server@.service                                                             disabled        enabled 
openvpn.service                                                                     enabled         enabled 
openvpn@.service                                                                    disabled        enabled 
orca-kill-at-shutdown.service                                                       disabled        disabled
pam_namespace.service                                                               static          -       
panic-on-oops.service                                                               enabled         enabled 
permission-hardener.service                                                         disabled        disabled
polkit.service                                                                      static          -       
privleapd.service                                                                   enabled         enabled 
proc-hidepid.service                                                                disabled        disabled
procps.service                                                                      alias           -       
quotaon.service                                                                     static          -       
rads-block-display-manger.service                                                   enabled         enabled 
rads.service                                                                        enabled         enabled 
rc-local.service                                                                    static          -       
rc.service                                                                          masked          enabled 
rcS.service                                                                         masked          enabled 
remount-secure.service                                                              disabled        disabled
remove-system-map.service                                                           enabled         enabled 
repository-dist-initializer.service                                                 enabled         enabled 
rescue.service                                                                      static          -       
rtkit-daemon.service                                                                disabled        enabled 
sdwdate-gui-shutdown-notify.service                                                 enabled         enabled 
sdwdate-pre.service                                                                 enabled         enabled 
sdwdate-start-anondate-set-file-watcher.service                                     enabled         enabled 
sdwdate.service                                                                     enabled         enabled 
serial-getty@.service                                                               disabled        enabled 
smartd.service                                                                      alias           -       
smartmontools.service                                                               enabled         enabled 
spice-vdagent.service                                                               alias           -       
spice-vdagentd.service                                                              indirect        enabled 
sudo.service                                                                        masked          enabled 
swap-file-creator.service                                                           enabled         enabled 
sysfsconf.service                                                                   alias           -       
sysfsutils.service                                                                  generated       -       
system-update-cleanup.service                                                       static          -       
systemd-ask-password-console.service                                                static          -       
systemd-ask-password-wall.service                                                   static          -       
systemd-backlight@.service                                                          static          -       
systemd-binfmt.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-boot-check-no-failures.service                                              disabled        disabled
systemd-cryptsetup@luks\x2d1e928d4d\x2d106e\x2d42ab\x2db638\x2d220de0196d7c.service generated       -       
systemd-exit.service                                                                static          -       
systemd-firstboot.service                                                           static          -       
systemd-fsck-root.service                                                           enabled-runtime enabled 
systemd-fsck@.service                                                               static          -       
systemd-fsckd.service                                                               static          -       
systemd-halt.service                                                                static          -       
systemd-hibernate-resume@.service                                                   static          -       
systemd-hibernate.service                                                           static          -       
systemd-hostnamed.service                                                           static          -       
systemd-hybrid-sleep.service                                                        static          -       
systemd-initctl.service                                                             static          -       
systemd-journal-flush.service                                                       static          -       
systemd-journald.service                                                            static          -       
systemd-journald@.service                                                           static          -       
systemd-kexec.service                                                               static          -       
systemd-localed.service                                                             static          -       
systemd-logind.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-machine-id-commit.service                                                   static          -       
systemd-modules-load.service                                                        static          -       
systemd-network-generator.service                                                   disabled        enabled 
systemd-networkd-wait-online.service                                                disabled        disabled
systemd-networkd-wait-online@.service                                               disabled        enabled 
systemd-networkd.service                                                            disabled        enabled 
systemd-pcrphase-initrd.service                                                     static          -       
systemd-pcrphase-sysinit.service                                                    static          -       
systemd-pcrphase.service                                                            static          -       
systemd-poweroff.service                                                            static          -       
systemd-pstore.service                                                              enabled         enabled 
systemd-quotacheck.service                                                          static          -       
systemd-random-seed.service                                                         static          -       
systemd-reboot.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-remount-fs.service                                                          enabled-runtime enabled 
systemd-repart.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-rfkill.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-suspend-then-hibernate.service                                              static          -       
systemd-suspend.service                                                             static          -       
systemd-sysctl.service                                                              static          -       
systemd-sysext.service                                                              disabled        enabled 
systemd-sysusers.service                                                            static          -       
systemd-time-wait-sync.service                                                      disabled        disabled
systemd-timedated.service                                                           static          -       
systemd-tmpfiles-clean.service                                                      static          -       
systemd-tmpfiles-setup-dev.service                                                  static          -       
systemd-tmpfiles-setup.service                                                      static          -       
systemd-udev-settle.service                                                         static          -       
systemd-udev-trigger.service                                                        static          -       
systemd-udevd.service                                                               static          -       
systemd-update-utmp-runlevel.service                                                static          -       
systemd-update-utmp.service                                                         static          -       
systemd-user-sessions.service                                                       static          -       
systemd-volatile-root.service                                                       static          -       
timesanitycheck.service                                                             enabled         enabled 
tor.service                                                                         enabled         enabled 
tor@.service                                                                        indirect        enabled 
tor@default.service                                                                 enabled-runtime enabled 
udev.service                                                                        alias           -       
udisks2.service                                                                     enabled         enabled 
upower.service                                                                      disabled        enabled 
user-runtime-dir@.service                                                           static          -       
user@.service                                                                       static          -       
uuidd.service                                                                       indirect        enabled 
virtualbox-guest-utils.service                                                      enabled         enabled 
wpa_supplicant-nl80211@.service                                                     disabled        enabled 
wpa_supplicant-wired@.service                                                       disabled        enabled 
wpa_supplicant.service                                                              enabled         enabled 
wpa_supplicant@.service                                                             disabled        enabled 
x11-common.service                                                                  masked          enabled 
machine.slice                                                                       static          -       
system-systemd\x2dcryptsetup.slice                                                  static          -       
user.slice                                                                          static          -       
acpid.socket                                                                        enabled         enabled 
dbus.socket                                                                         static          -       
dm-event.socket                                                                     enabled         enabled 
lvm2-lvmpolld.socket                                                                enabled         enabled 
spice-vdagentd.socket                                                               static          -       
syslog.socket                                                                       static          -       
systemd-fsckd.socket                                                                static          -       
systemd-initctl.socket                                                              static          -       
systemd-journald-audit.socket                                                       static          -       
systemd-journald-dev-log.socket                                                     static          -       
systemd-journald-varlink@.socket                                                    static          -       
systemd-journald.socket                                                             static          -       
systemd-journald@.socket                                                            static          -       
systemd-networkd.socket                                                             disabled        enabled 
systemd-rfkill.socket                                                               static          -       
systemd-udevd-control.socket                                                        static          -       
systemd-udevd-kernel.socket                                                         static          -       
uuidd.socket                                                                        enabled         enabled 
basic.target                                                                        static          -       
blockdev@.target                                                                    static          -       
bluetooth.target                                                                    static          -       
boot-complete.target                                                                static          -       
cryptsetup-pre.target                                                               static          -       
cryptsetup.target                                                                   static          -       
ctrl-alt-del.target                                                                 alias           -       
default.target                                                                      alias           -       
emergency.target                                                                    static          -       
exit.target                                                                         disabled        disabled
factory-reset.target                                                                static          -       
final.target                                                                        static          -       
first-boot-complete.target                                                          static          -       
getty-pre.target                                                                    static          -       
getty.target                                                                        static          -       
graphical.target                                                                    static          -       
halt.target                                                                         disabled        disabled
hibernate.target                                                                    static          -       
hybrid-sleep.target                                                                 static          -       
initrd-fs.target                                                                    static          -       
initrd-root-device.target                                                           static          -       
initrd-root-fs.target                                                               static          -       
initrd-switch-root.target                                                           static          -       
initrd-usr-fs.target                                                                static          -       
initrd.target                                                                       static          -       
initrd.target                                                                       static          -       
integritysetup-pre.target                                                           static          -       
integritysetup.target                                                               static          -       
kexec.target                                                                        disabled        disabled
local-fs-pre.target                                                                 static          -       
local-fs.target                                                                     static          -       
multi-user.target                                                                   static          -       
network-online.target                                                               static          -       
network-pre.target                                                                  static          -       
network.target                                                                      static          -       
nss-lookup.target                                                                   static          -       
nss-user-lookup.target                                                              static          -       
nvmf-connect.target                                                                 static          -       
paths.target                                                                        static          -       
poweroff.target                                                                     disabled        disabled
printer.target                                                                      static          -       
reboot.target                                                                       disabled        enabled 
remote-cryptsetup.target                                                            disabled        enabled 
remote-fs-pre.target                                                                static          -       
remote-fs.target                                                                    enabled         enabled 
remote-veritysetup.target                                                           disabled        enabled 
rescue.target                                                                       static          -       
rpcbind.target                                                                      static          -       
runlevel0.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel1.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel2.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel3.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel4.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel5.target                                                                    alias           -       
runlevel6.target                                                                    alias           -       
shutdown.target                                                                     static          -       
sigpwr.target                                                                       static          -       
sleep.target                                                                        static          -       
slices.target                                                                       static          -       
smartcard.target                                                                    static          -       
sockets.target                                                                      static          -       
sound.target                                                                        static          -       
suspend-then-hibernate.target                                                       static          -       
suspend.target                                                                      static          -       
swap.target                                                                         static          -       
sysinit-post.target                                                                 enabled         enabled 
sysinit.target                                                                      static          -       
system-update-pre.target                                                            static          -       
system-update.target                                                                static          -       
time-set.target                                                                     static          -       
time-sync.target                                                                    static          -       
timers.target                                                                       static          -       
umount.target                                                                       static          -       
usb-gadget.target                                                                   static          -       
veritysetup-pre.target                                                              static          -
</code></pre> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-kvm-qemu-linux-mint-host-os/1206#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 00:43:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3178</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Is zsh the default shell globally for useradd?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>See <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/About_Debian_Packaging#Modifying_Default_Configuration_of_Third_Party_Packages">Modifying Default Configuration of Third Party Packages</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/is-zsh-the-default-shell-globally-for-useradd/1200#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 05:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3175</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Is zsh the default shell globally for useradd?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>That comes with the same difficulties as modifying the adduser.conf file. There isn’t a directory where we can put configuration overrides for either file, so it makes it more difficult to change those settings.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/is-zsh-the-default-shell-globally-for-useradd/1200#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:36:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3174</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Almost certainly yes. If it doesn’t, that would be a bug.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_23</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:33:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3173</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I believe TEMPEST-resistant fonts should be its own forum topic. It was only brought up in passing because of my comment about radiation-hardened software.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/10/8/2828" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/10/8/2828</a> has some research done as to whether these fonts are effective or not. I can see an argument for including them, they do seem to help. There don’t seem to be any packaged in Debian yet, and I can’t even find them available for download, so I don’t think it’s something we can do soon (if at all). It does seem like a cool idea though.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139?page=2#post_25</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:33:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3172</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Will it work in LIVE ISO and LIVE Mode in general?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_22</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:10:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3171</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Does Kicksecure use “TEMPEST” resistant or hardened fonts like <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/desi_fubu">@desi_fubu</a> mentioned above?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139?page=2#post_24</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3170</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure distro specific keyboard shortcuts</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>That being said, there’s a good chance we will switch desktops from Xfce to LXQt</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok then whisker menu will not be used. I think these shortcuts should be added to Kicksecure in the meantime via dconf which would be easier to change over from <code>xfce4-popup-whiskermenu</code> → “command to launch LXQT’s menu” when a switch over from enviroments happens.</p>
<p>The super key or “windows key” is commonly used as a shortcut to launch menu like it is on Windows taskbar.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-distro-specific-keyboard-shortcuts/1147#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:07:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3169</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Is zsh the default shell globally for useradd?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Could Kicksecure ship with a custom /etc/default/useradd ? <br>
Something that modifies it during the build or something?</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto"># comment out SHELL=/bin/sh
sed -i '/^SHELL=\/bin\/sh$/d' /etc/default/useradd

# Append and set SHELL=/bin/zsh
echo -e '\n# Use ZSH as the default shell for newly created users\nSHELL=/bin/zsh' | tee -a /etc/default/useradd
</code></pre> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/is-zsh-the-default-shell-globally-for-useradd/1200#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 22:04:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3168</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Sdwdate design enhancements</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Not sure there’s much to discuss here, this is just me doing a brain-dump of my research so that it’s not lost and so that others can comment on it as desirable.</p>
<p>The current iteration of sdwdate does a pretty good job of keeping the system’s clock accurate but skewed just enough to provide better anonymity under Whonix. However, it has a few shortcomings we’d like to resolve:</p>
<ul>
<li>It only sets the time for the (virtual) machine it runs on, it isn’t able to act as a server for helping other virtual machines running on the same system to also synchronize their time securely. This is something that would be nice to fix in Qubes OS, allowing sys-whonix (or more likely, sys-ops-whonix once that exists) to act as a master time-keeper for all VMs.</li>
<li>The current way it adjusts the clock is somewhat awful - it does a large clock jump or two to get the time close enough to accurate to allow connecting to Tor, then does a large number of small clock jumps to get the time to a final “good” value. Clock jump confuse software in multiple ways, and the small clock jumps we do currently can result in systemd journal being flooded, so they’re best avoided, and if they’re needed, it’s best to do one clock jump and then slew the clock to the correct time using something like <code>adjtimex</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The core sdwdate code is good and should probably not change too much. What should probably change is the <code>sclockadj</code> tool that is used for doing small clock jumps, and we need a way to allow sdwdate to provide time values for other VMs to sync themselves to.</p>
<hr>
<p>The below is my research into using adjtimex, The tl;dr: is that <strong>we probably should not use adjtimex for initial clock synchronization after boot, but it may be usable to keep the clock in sync thereafter.</strong></p>
<p>Properly adjusting a clock using <code>adjtime</code> or <code>adjtimex</code> (slewing it to the correct value using in-kernel support) is very, very slow. According to <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/188620/535873" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">time - How long will NTP take to adjust the clock if it doesn't immediately set it? - Unix &amp; Linux Stack Exchange</a> it takes approximately 4.17 minutes to adjust the clock by 128 milliseconds, or at least it did in 2015. In my testing with adjtimex, this is still approximately correct - it appears that adjtimex adjusts the clock by 500 microseconds per second. This means it takes a little over 33 minutes to adjust the clock by one second.</p>
<p>The problem with this is that Tor (and therefore sdwdate) only allow us to resolve time to within a second at best because that’s the resolution of the HTTP headers we get. On top of that, we get the time from three different servers at once when using sdwdate and then go with the median value of those three times, meaning that in practice we’re not going to be within a second of accuracy because of network lag and all sorts of other things NTP is designed to work around and Tor isn’t. On top of that, we also randomize the clock a bit for greater anonymity, meaning that we might change the clock several seconds on each invocation of sdwdate. When it takes over half an hour to move the clock by one second, making a multi-second change will take <em>hours</em>. Now if we assume that the system’s clock is fairly accurate, and we only ever have <em>one</em> time randomization offset per session (generated randomly each session but never changed until the next reboot, I guess), we can probably skew the clock by a second or two on each sdwdate invocation without too much trouble. But if the network is shaky (for instance, the user is using cellular internet in bad conditions), it’s likely sdwdate will be trying to make much larger changes.</p>
<p>(Note, anecdotally it seems that sdwdate doesn’t see any particular need to change the clock in my KVM virtual machine when I restart sdwdate, at least while my network is working well. The median time difference keeps being 0. That being said, other time differences were frequently reported that were not the median, so I assume that users won’t always get this lucky.)</p>
<p>The current <code>sclockadj</code> code adjusts the clock by 5 million nanoseconds per second. This is <em>ten times</em> faster than adjtimex, which adjusts by 5 hundred thousand nanoseconds per second. Thus sclockadj can handle multi-second adjustments without too much grief, but only by doing clock jumps. Switching to clock slewing with adjtimex will slow down our time adjustments very much.</p>
<p>The 500 microseconds per second adjustment rate is not configurable, it is unfortunately hardcoded in the kernel’s NTP code, which the <code>adjtimex</code> system call uses to do its work of slewing the clock. There isn’t any way to do a “fast slew” to my awareness, unless we want to try to contribute a feature for this to the kernel (which… might be possible?).</p>
<p>Based on the above, I think we might get away with using adjtimex to keep the clock in sync once it is initially synchronized. For making an adjustment of a second or two, it’s probably enough. But on first boot, when the clock is most likely to be several seconds slow or fast (especially on machines with no BIOS battery or a broken battery), we probably need to just use a clock jump. This is similar to the behavior of ntpd.</p>
<hr>
<p>For making sdwdate able to act as a server under Qubes OS, there are a couple of issues to deal with:</p>
<ul>
<li>Qubes OS currently synchronizes all VMs to dom0’s time, at least when resuming after suspend. But we would like for dom0 to be able to synchronize itself to sys-(ops-)whonix also.</li>
<li>Every VM on the system should ideally have slightly different time, and should get their time values from a different sdwdate time sync invocation (to avoid one bad sync affecting all VMs on the system).</li>
</ul>
<p>To work with the first issue, we can simply have all VMs (including sys-(ops-)whonix) blindly trust dom0’s time to begin with. Once a successful sdwdate sync is done however, the VM should record how its time differs from dom0’s time. Then, on resume-from-suspend, the VM can take the time given to it by dom0, and adjust it by the offset before syncing the clock. Any time dom0’s clock changed, it would have to announce this to all running VMs so they could recalculate their offsets from dom0.</p>
<p>To work around the second issue, we need some way for a virtual machine to get “whatever the current time is +/- some fixed offset” each time they synchronize their clock with the ClockVM. The fixed offset should be unique per-machine and per-boot, but should be constant between boots to avoid needing lots of clock jumps forward and backward. To acheive this, the client process that gets the time from the ClockVM should create a random identifier on launch, and present that identifier to sdwdate every time it syncs the clock. When sdwdate sees an identifier it hasn’t seen previously, it should generate a new random offset, but if it sees an identifier it’s seen previously, it should use the same offset it presented last time. This way each VM can have its time a little bit different, but that “little bit different” will be static for each virtual machine (until the client VM or ClockVM is rebooted, at least).</p>
<p>We don’t have to tack a bunch of code onto the existing sdwdate code base in order to make it able to act like a server. We should just create a new server process that serves whatever the ClockVM’s current time is (+/- the fixed offset described earlier) to clients. This probably won’t be very difficult to do at all. We will need this server process to NOT serve time until after sdwdate has synced the clock, but thankfully sdwdate already reports its status to other processes on the same VM, so we can rely on that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/sdwdate-design-enhancements/1203#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 19:24:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3167</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="9" data-topic="1197">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Sure? This contradicts what we’re currently writing in chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Strong_Linux_User_Account_Isolation#Console_Login_Attacks" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Console Login Attacks</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t believe so. That documentation explicitly warns that one way to be able to switch virtual terminals is to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>…be running under a user account that has logged in at a virtual terminal already. In this … instance, software running as the logged-in user could <em>switch</em> to a different virtual terminal, but it would not be able to attempt to login at that terminal. That would require read/write access to the virtual terminal that was switched to. Virtual terminals that have a login prompt are only able to be read from and written to by root or a person with physical access to the machine.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The reason this is a problem in the context of a SAK is that even if we switch to a TTY presenting an authentic login screen, malware could immediately switch us back to the TTY it was on a second ago and display a fake login screen. It’s not a danger when it comes to logging into other accounts, it is a problem when it comes to stealing user data.</p>
<p>(Worthy of note, once we switch to Wayland, the compositor will almost certainly run as a user other than root, and thus the TTY it runs on will have its permissions set to a non-root user. Thus this issue will start affecting graphical sessions as well, not just text-only VT logins. I think though that’s a small price to pay, especially since there’s a mitigation.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:13:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3166</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="6" data-topic="1197">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>it would be fairly trivial for malware running as a user in a graphical session to simply force the user back to the original TTY, using a console file descriptor.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Sure? This contradicts what we’re currently writing in chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Strong_Linux_User_Account_Isolation#Console_Login_Attacks">Console Login Attacks</a>.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="6" data-topic="1197">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>SIGSTOP</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Another advantage of this might be that misbehaving processes (such as clogging up all CPU due to a bug) would stop doing that so the user has system resources available to investigate this and to terminate misbehaving processes.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 09:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3165</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure distro specific keyboard shortcuts</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1147">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>here’s a good chance we will switch desktops from Xfce to LXQt when we port to Trixie (which we’re working on), since Xfce’s Wayland support is rather lacking, LXQt’s is more mature, and switching to Wayland is a goal for Kicksecure 18.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>related: <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/port-to-wayland/17380" class="inline-onebox">port to Wayland - Development - Whonix Forum</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-distro-specific-keyboard-shortcuts/1147#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 08:49:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3164</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Based on some quick testing using the fsfreeze technique described in an earlier shared link, it looks like it is <em>not</em> possible to immunize a process to SIGKILL or SIGSTOP by using a stuck thread.</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto"># Set up
mkdir stickyfs
fallocate -l 8M sticky.img
mkfs.ext4 sticky.img
sudo mount sticky.img stickyfs
sudo chmod 777 stickyfs

# Write a simple multithreaded C program that will get one thread stuck
cat &lt;&lt;EOF &gt; test.c
#include &lt;pthread.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;fcntl.h&gt;
#include &lt;unistd.h&gt;
#include &lt;string.h&gt;
#include &lt;errno.h&gt;

void *sticky_func(void *arg) {
  const char *stuckstr = "I'm stuck, help!\n";
  int stuckfd = open("stickyfs/sticky.txt", O_RDWR | O_CREAT);
  write(stuckfd, stuckstr, strlen(stuckstr));
}

int main() {
  pthread_t sticky;
  pthread_create(&amp;sticky, NULL, sticky_func, NULL);
  int i = 0;
  while (1) {
    printf("%d\n", i++);
  }
}
EOF

gcc test.c

# Lock the stickyfs filesystem
sudo fsfreeze -f stickyfs

# Run the newly created application
./a.out

# Numbers will scroll down the screen indicating that the process is doing something. Open another terminal to do other work in.

# Look at the contents of stickyfs, verify sticky.txt does not exist there
ls stickyfs

# Find the PID of the sticky process
pgrep a.out

# SIGSTOP it
kill -s SIGSTOP PID

# Observe the numbers stop scrolling down the screen
# Resume the process
kill -s SIGCONT PID

# Observe the numbers start scrolling again
# Kill the process with SIGKILL
kill -s SIGKILL PID

# Observe the numbers stop scroling, but the process does not fully exit, confirming that it is stuck in a kernel thread
# Unfreeze the stickyfs dir
sudo fsfreeze -u stickyfs

# Observe the process exits now
</code></pre>
<p>So it looks like SIGSTOP is usable here. Even though the stuck thread isn’t responding to the signals, the unstuck threads that could actually be dangerous are still affected by those signals.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 04:26:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3162</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>On the topic of a secure attention key, someone in 2016 posted a really nice overview of attack scenarios where a SAK is very useful: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/civis/threads/sak-sas-secure-attention-key-sequence-on-linux.1325235/#post-31739583" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">SAK/SAS - Secure attention key sequence on Linux | Ars OpenForum</a> Quoting the post:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s not about a machine we don’t trust; that’s a separate but valid concern. It’s about a computer that multiple people have access to, e.g. libraries, computer labs, workplaces. Many people may be allowed on that machine, but each having their own accounts and passwords.</p>
<p>Attack type number 1:<br>
Attacker logs into his account and starts up a full-screen program that looks and acts identical to the login screen. (Program designed to collect the username/password data and store it or send it somewhere, then shows a fictitious error screen or simply logs out or reboots or hangs so that someone forces a restart.)<br>
Victim finds an apparently unused workstation. Logs in. Game over.</p>
<p>Attack type number 2:<br>
Victim logs in, starts up some programs, opens some files, then locks the screen and goes for a coffee break.<br>
Attacker hard-resets the machine, logs in and runs a similar program that looks/behaves like the screenlocker instead.<br>
Victim returns and attempts to unlock the screen. Game over.</p>
<p>Attack type number 3:<br>
Victim forgets to lock screen on going to the john. (When you gotta go…)<br>
Attacker runs fake screenlocker on the Victim’s own acct.<br>
Victim returns and either forgot that he didn’t lock it or figures it timed out from inactivity. Unlocks screen. Game over. (program simply terminates itself putting him back at his desktop after having sent the password over the internet and deleting its tracks)<br>
Some compromise existed already, since Victim failed to lock, but this attack provides stealthy expansion of that gap, allowing future log on, not just a one time access, and also gives you any sudo privileges the account has.</p>
<p>Having a SAK that users are trained to ALWAYS enter before passwords eliminates the risk.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the features Windows has bound to the three finger salute is triggering the lock screen or login screen to function (the screen displays even before that, but the SAK signals it to prompt for the password), which conveniently solves all of these issues. To implement something like this on Linux, we could probably do something like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>The screen locker itself doesn’t accept a password, it simply listens for a privileged process to give it an “unlock the screen” signal and unlocks the screen upon receipt of that signal.</li>
<li>Pressing Ctrl+Alt+Del causes emerg-shutdown (which probably needs renamed at this point) to freeze all user accounts on the system, send the user to an unused TTY, and display a greetd+wlgreet window. The user can then log in with their user name and password.</li>
<li>The script that runs on login signals emerg-shutdown to unfreeze the system, then looks to see if the user is already logged in (and if so, on which TTY). If the user is already logged in, the script instructs emerg-shutdown to unlock that user’s TTY, then it switches to that user’s TTY and is done. If the user is not already logged in, a new login is created.</li>
</ul>
<p>This mitigates all three attack scenarios. As for how to implement this and the emergency session at the same time, we just need emerg-shutdown to be able to tell whether or not the active TTY is locked (this can be done most likely with the help of the custom screen locker). If the TTY is locked, the salute will trigger a login/unlock action like described above, otherwise it will trigger an emergency session like described earlier.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 03:31:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3161</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Had a conversation about how this could work with Patrick, this is my current set of ideas/plans after that conversation.</p>
<p>We have the <code>emerg-shutdown</code> background process now, which among other things monitors all keystrokes on the system by grabbing the /dev/input/event* devices on startup. This is done so that if the user presses a panic key combination (user configurable, the default is yet to be determined, see <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199" class="inline-onebox">Emergency key press shutdown sequence</a>), the system can be immediately and forcibly shut down, without any possibility of malicious interference or accidental overriding. That same mechanism could be used in theory to listen for any key combination though, allowing us to define keyboard shortcuts that talk to a privileged component of the system (similar to the Secure Attention Key in other operating systems). Another advantage of this is that it’s not possible for malware to access this interface unless it is running as root, because emulated input mechanisms allow communicating with the display server, not the kernel’s evdev driver. Injecting key events into the kernel’s evdev subsystem requires using uinput, which requires root privileges to access, thus unprivileged malware can’t send keystroke combinations in order to trigger whatever privileged actions are configured here.</p>
<p>Since shortcuts configured in emerg-shutdown require either root privileges or physical access to the machine to trigger, this makes it seem like the perfect place to implement a Ctrl+Alt+Delete handler. The question then becomes, what should this handler do?</p>
<p>There are two possible directions we could take this. One is the simple route - register the salute in emerg-shutdown, and send a DBus message to whatever user session is on an active TTY in response. Those messages would then instruct an agent running as the user to do something like start a task manager or lock the screen. This would be useful, but it would only be marginally better than just defining a keyboard shortcut in the user session. It wouldn’t allow the user to kill applications that are running as root or as a different user (something they may have a legitimate reason to do even in a user session), and it wouldn’t prevent anything “going wrong” in the user session (a malicious or runaway process, for instance) from being able to interfere with the salute’s functionality in some way.</p>
<p>The other, more complex route, would be to switch to an “emergency session” of sorts, moving the user to an unused TTY and launching a graphical session in that TTY where they can do things as root or another privileged user. This is far more powerful, <em>and</em> possibly far more secure if done right.</p>
<p>The more complex solution is unsafe under X11 because of the world-writable UNIX sockets created by X11, exposing attack surface that could result in exploitable escalation of privilege vulnerabilities. Under Wayland however, the display server’s socket is generally under /run/user/UID, which has strict permissions to prevent access by other users, so as long as the kernel’s permission subsystem holds up, this shouldn’t be an issue. We can thus run a separate Wayland server as a privileged user (such as <code>sysmaint</code>) alongside an unprivileged and untrusted user session, without as much fear of vulnerabilities. (If running a full Wayland server sounds like too much risk, we could also use a raw framebuffer. Qt supports rendering directly to a framebuffer, it’s very slow at least under a virtual machine, but it works. I think this is overkill though, and it will also make it hard to work with multiple programs at once, which would almost certainly be desirable.)</p>
<p>One danger of an emergency UI such as this is that it’s not impossible for a malicious application to prevent the user from escaping to the emergency session. The emergency session would simply run in a TTY (since that’s the only feature Linux has for this sort of thing), and it would be fairly trivial for malware running as a user in a graphical session to simply force the user back to the original TTY, using a console file descriptor. (One can switch the active TTY to any other TTY if they have write access to any one TTY. In other words, if the user is logged in graphically and thus /dev/tty7 is writable by them, malware running as that user can open /dev/tty7 and then switch the user to any desired TTY.) To prevent this, one solution would be to SIGSTOP potentially malicious processes, specifically those which run as a logged-in user. This cannot be done to every process in the system though, since:</p>
<ul>
<li>PID 1 cannot be SIGSTOP’d (I tried, the signal was silently ignored)</li>
<li>A SIGSTOP’d program can be SIGKILL’d without receiving a SIGCONT first</li>
<li>systemd’s watchdog mechanism can and probably will restart a service that is SIGSTOP’d as a result</li>
</ul>
<p>However, “freezing” all logged-in user accounts should still be feasible in theory. This would prevent any running malware from doing anything while the user is in the emergency session, thus it would be unable to force the user to a different TTY. Any malware on the system that wasn’t running as a logged-in user would have to be running as root or be able to elevate its privileges to that of a logged-in user in order to gain access to a console and thus change TTYs.</p>
<p>One thing that is still uncertain about SIGSTOP is how it behaves when dealing with stuck kernel threads. If a thread calls into the kernel and then gets stuck there (such as can happen when dealing with flaky I/O devices), it cannot be SIGKILL’d or SIGSTOP’d. What’s unclear is whether the process’s <em>other</em> threads can be SIGKILL’d or SIGSTOP’d in this situation. If the answer is “yes”, then using SIGSTOP should be an effective freezing mechanism, but if the answer is “no”, then malware may be able to circumvent a SIGSTOP by launching a thread that then does something to get stuck in the kernel. Getting a thread stuck in kernel mode is hard though (I believe it should be impossible without either buggy hardware, a buggy kernel, or root access, <s>and even with root access you’d have to do something convoluted like set up a VM with an NFS share, mount the NFS share on the host, kill the VM abruptly, and then attempt I/O on the mounted share</s> edit: just tried something like this, even this doesn’t result in a stuck kernel thread, <a href="https://chrisdown.name/2024/02/05/reliably-creating-d-state-processes-on-demand.html" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Creating controllable D state (uninterruptible sleep) processes</a> has better instructions for getting a process stuck in a kernel thread), so this might not be an issue.</p>
<p>Another difficulty is that we most likely are not going to go through a display manager., As a result, the “session” we will end up in will be rather limited and things that one might expect to work (like systemd user units, DBus, some xdg-related things, etc.) probably won’t work. Thus the functionality within the emergency session will need to be limited to cope with this. (This will also prevent us from simply switching to a sysmaint session when the salute is registered - the sysmaint session has features that depend on a full login session running. It most likely will not behave itself well if it doesn’t have all of the infrastructure usually set up by a display manager working right. We also can’t just switch to the sysmaint session because some of the features of the sysmaint session, like software updates, are not things that can be safely done when booted into a user session. Even if they work now, they won’t work once we implement Verified Boot.)</p>
<p>Obviously, some form of authorization will be needed in order to access the features of this emergency session. Otherwise any attacker with physical access to the system could use this to take the system over entirely. It shouldn’t be too difficult to implement an authorization prompt of some sort to make this work. Because of the need for authorization, the graphical session MUST NOT run as root, since then any arbitrary code execution vulnerability in a used graphical toolkit or Wayland compositor could allow an attacker with physical access to gain unauthorized root access. The sysmaint account would be ideal to use instead, since then if the user has set a password, they will have to provide it in order to run any privileged operations.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 02:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3160</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Emergency key press shutdown sequence</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Ctrl+*+Esc combos slightly scare me since Ctrl+Esc is the shortcut for bringing up the task manager under KDE, and I believe Ctrl+Shift+Esc does so on Windows.</p>
<p>Another possible shortcut is Ctrl+Alt+End, which is used by Windows Remote Desktop to send a Ctrl+Alt+Delete keypress to a remote PC. Using the End key would be rather fitting for this also, since an emergency shutdown will immediately end whatever you were doing on the computer.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:08:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3159</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure distro specific keyboard shortcuts</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It’s unlikely that additional DE spins will be added since every desktop comes with its own unique challenges, both for development and for support. That being said, there’s a good chance we will switch desktops from Xfce to LXQt when we port to Trixie (which we’re working on), since Xfce’s Wayland support is rather lacking, LXQt’s is more mature, and switching to Wayland is a goal for Kicksecure 18.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-distro-specific-keyboard-shortcuts/1147#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 23:27:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3158</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Non-Systemd - Systemd Discussion</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Things which are no longer required or highly unified, simplified thanks to systemd:</p>
<ul>
<li>any code related to daemonizing</li>
<li>daemon restart</li>
<li>signal handling</li>
<li>PID files and manual process tracking, service supervision (systemd notify)</li>
<li>seccomp call filtering</li>
<li>logging, log rotation</li>
<li>custom init scripts</li>
<li>socket activation</li>
<li>capabilities</li>
<li>child processes cleanup</li>
<li>in-exhaustive list</li>
</ul>
<p>Not easy to remember since thanks to systemd I didn’t have to worry much about all of that for years. Reading some application’s source code and recognizing they’re still manually handling daemonizing reminded me of this.</p>
<p>related wiki page:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Systemd">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1754476781" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Systemd" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:52AM - 06 August 2025">Kicksecure – 6 Aug 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Systemd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">systemd</a></h3>

  <p>systemd versus non-systemd / Miscellaneous / Find systemd dependency cycles.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/non-systemd-systemd-discussion/766#post_13</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 11:01:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3157</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Non-Systemd - Systemd Discussion</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Although not a direct security issue on its own, systemd is a bulky piece of software and has been <a href="https://without-systemd.org/wiki/index_php/Arguments_against_systemd/">heavily criticized</a> for numerous things.</p>
<p>For linux there are init available check <a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Comparison_of_init_systems#Init_system_comparison_table">here</a>.</p>
<p>For seL4 good news is that Genode OS has developed its own lightweight <a href="https://genode.org/documentation/genode-foundations/21.05/system_configuration/The_init_component.html">init component</a>.</p>
<p>Note: Though Genode init is not with (yet) rich features as systemd.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/non-systemd-systemd-discussion/766#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 19:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3154</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Is zsh the default shell globally for useradd?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="init38" data-post="1" data-topic="1200">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/c6cbf5/48.png" class="avatar"> init38:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>When I create new users will it default to setting the shell as zsh?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>No.</p>
<p>For that, Kicksecure would need to modify the <code>/etc/adduser.conf</code> configuration file.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="init38" data-post="1" data-topic="1200">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/c6cbf5/48.png" class="avatar"> init38:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Or do I have to manually edit passwd to set it?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="init38" data-post="1" data-topic="1200">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/c6cbf5/48.png" class="avatar"> init38:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Just curious as when I morphed a VM it would still default to sh when i created a new user.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Clarified in <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian#Distribution_Morphing_versus_ISO_-_Differences">Distribution Morphing versus ISO - Differences</a> just now:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li><strong>No user account settings changes:</strong> Any user account settings will remain unchanged.</li>
<li><strong>No user account shell changes:</strong> The user’s default <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Shell">shell</a> will remain the same.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/is-zsh-the-default-shell-globally-for-useradd/1200#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 07:35:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3153</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="init38" data-post="2" data-topic="1197">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/c6cbf5/48.png" class="avatar"> init38:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Please see my thread 1147 about this.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>These cannot be referenced by number. Difficult to find. I had to click on your profile and check all created forum threads.</p>
<p>This:<br>
<a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-distro-specific-keyboard-shortcuts/1147" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure distro specific keyboard shortcuts</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 07:27:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3152</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>related:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199" class="inline-onebox">Emergency key press shutdown sequence</a></li>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197" class="inline-onebox">Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_21</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 07:23:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3151</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>No Accessibility Support</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>People with special needs should have their own operating system, potentially even supervised by medical professionals, as each case may require specific tools depending on individual needs (vision, hearing, touch, speech …etc).</p>
<p>This should not be a concern for the project, as it does not target this field.</p>
<p>Not to mention the effort, bulk code, and other complexities involved. Therefore, it is not supported.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-accessibility-support/1201#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 06:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3150</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>What about other default shortcuts like <em>super key</em> for whisker menu for easy searching for applications like “windows task bar”. Many distros already set super key for application menu like Ubuntu and Mint.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:39:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3149</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Is zsh the default shell globally for useradd?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>When I create new users will it default to setting the shell as zsh?<br>
Or do I have to manually edit passwd to set it?</p>
<p>Just curious as when I morphed a VM it would still default to sh when i created a new user.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/is-zsh-the-default-shell-globally-for-useradd/1200#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3148</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>My idea was to use the existing emerg-shutdown framework (which monitors for a “panic” key combo already) to also act as the Ctrl+Alt+Delete handler. That would make it work anywhere in the system, and could also (if handled carefully) prevent malware running as a local user from being able to interfere with the key handler and associated features.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:36:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3147</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@init38]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Please see my thread 1147 about this.</p>
<p>My question is what route should be the go to?</p>
<p>Set a local shortcuts config for user and sysmaint? Downside would be these keyboard shortcuts would not populate if user uses sysmaint to create more users. Unless there is something specific to xfce4’s xconf for globally setting shortcuts it seems like the only route is dconf?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:23:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3146</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>No Rescue Mode</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The best and only thing hardware buyers can do is purchase devices that support user unlock/relock. Every purchase of a device that does not support unlock is a vote towards the end of general purpose computing access for mere morals.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>General-purpose computers are fun but insecure, a sad reality, but true. The wind does not blow as the ships desire, as they say.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Once general-purpose computers are no longer available, that’s the end of small Linux distributions such as this one.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>…Legal barriers.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>None of the following quotes seem to be a legal barrier.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>“Though the lawsuit was filed in California, NSO Group made its source code available to view only in Israel by an Israeli citizen, which the judge called “simply impracticable”, according to the ruling.”</p>
<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/feb/29/pegasus-surveillance-code-whatsapp-meta-lawsuit-nso-group" class="inline-onebox">Court orders maker of Pegasus spyware to hand over code to WhatsApp | WhatsApp | The Guardian</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>“NSO’s Pegasus code, and code for other surveillance products it sells, is seen as a closely and highly sought state secret. NSO is closely regulated by the Israeli ministry of defence, which must review and approve the sale of all licences to foreign governments.”</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>…these quotes do not imply that security researchers are prohibited from or scared to release malware artifacts such as disassembles due to fear of copyright laws. Specifically not in the case of Pegasus. Malware samples are shared and analyzed in public all the time.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It may not be impossible to secure that either.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah sadly i dont see how that can be secure.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This isn’t easy for sure. You’d probably need to be able to at least:</p>
<ul>
<li>understand/write for example the following documents:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/3mdeb/verified-boot/blob/master/measured_boot.md" class="inline-onebox">verified-boot/measured_boot.md at master · 3mdeb/verified-boot · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/3mdeb/verified-boot/blob/master/verified_boot_app_spec.md" class="inline-onebox">verified-boot/verified_boot_app_spec.md at master · 3mdeb/verified-boot · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/3mdeb/verified-boot/blob/master/verified_boot_main.md" class="inline-onebox">verified-boot/verified_boot_main.md at master · 3mdeb/verified-boot · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/3mdeb/verified-boot/blob/master/threat-model.md" class="inline-onebox">verified-boot/threat-model.md at master · 3mdeb/verified-boot · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>understand code flows</li>
<li>basic programming</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>How does one now they got an original iPhone from Apple or one that has been tampered with?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://checkcoverage.apple.com/">https://checkcoverage.apple.com/</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Might be some sort of remote attestation. Not easy and maybe even impossible to come up with a perfect implementation. Refer to the same wiki page <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a>.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/secure-enclave-sec59b0b31ff/web" class="inline-onebox">Secure Enclave - Apple Support</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That might be like Intel ME on steroids.</p>
<p>I may also not be the best idea to come up with more and more complex hardware designs. They’ll forget (or “forget”?) to disable some debugging feature. (<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/IOS" class="inline-onebox">Apple iOS - Malicious Backdoor or Debugging Feature? The Debate Over Operation Triangulation</a>) → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/About_Computer_(In)Security#Too_Much_Complexity">Too much complexity, etc.</a></p>
<p>As for end-user, desktop computers and notebooks, there does not seem to be any hardware vendors on Intel/AMD64 interested to provide such functionality. This might be due to lack of customer interest. The x86 market is shrinking.</p>
<p>On Intel/AMD64 we can be glad if we get at least <a href="https://github.com/openSIL/openSIL">OpenSIL</a>. That might be the next realistic step after <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901/5">Sovereign Boot</a>.</p>
<p>And if we’re really fortunate, maybe one day we’ll have <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Open-source_Hardware" class="inline-onebox">Open Source Hardware</a>. I’d prefer that any day about any proprietary co-processor.</p>
<p>The security co-processor design is to be considered in 10 to 20 years. That’s far away from anything realistic we’ll be working on anytime soon.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="18" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The question is: shall we have purely burned/fixed firmware where they are irreplaceable, non-upgradable which will be impossible to change by design (<a href="https://www.otomasyonavm.com/en/what-is-mask-rom">Mask ROM</a>, <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/memory/one-time-programmable-memory/">OTP</a>…), or upgradable with signed mechanism (more complexity, more attack surface to protect, but better usability).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Due to lack of hardware vendor interest… And due to no decent performance fully Open Source Hardware RISC-V being available yet… And due to Kicksecure not being a hardware development project… This is too far fetched for now.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171#post_19</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 11:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3145</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Emergency key press shutdown sequence</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-doesnt-trigger-a-shutdown/994" class="inline-onebox">Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</a> → this will be implemented soon: Removal of boot device will result in emergency shutdown. This will become available in Kicksecure 18 most likely.</p>
<p>As an additional feature, at the same time, we can provide an emergency key combination. Once pressed, a force shutdown sequence can be triggered.</p>
<p>We’re wondering about which key combination to use for that?</p>
<p><strong>Ctrl+Alt+Del</strong> (sometimes called the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Control-Alt-Delete">three-finger salute</a>”): May not be the most suitable. Different plans for this: <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197" class="inline-onebox">Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</a></p>
<p>Potential choices:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ctrl+Shift+Esc</strong></li>
<li><strong>Ctrl+Alt+Esc</strong></li>
<li><strong>Ctrl+Alt+Backspace</strong></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 10:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3144</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Unplugging external drive → shutdown: This feature has been implemented in packages security-misc, helper-scripts and user-sysmaint-split by <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@arraybolt3</a>. This feature will most likely become available in Kicksecure 18.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994#post_20</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 10:21:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3143</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><strong>Ctrl+Alt+Del</strong> (sometimes called the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Control-Alt-Delete">three-finger salute</a>”):</p>
<p>On Windows, the three-finger does something useful. Noways, shows a menu:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lock</li>
<li>Switch user</li>
<li>Sign out</li>
<li>Change a password</li>
<li>Task manager</li>
<li>Cancel</li>
</ul>
<p>On Qubes, simply activates the screen lock.</p>
<p>On Kicksecure, we could also provide similar options such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Task manager</li>
<li>Lock</li>
<li>Regular shutdown</li>
<li>Emergency shutdown</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 08:57:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3141</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>No Rescue Mode</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Not much point for me replying to an analogy.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That’s what the suggestion is saying: leaving the doors open/no doors is better than having closed doors to secure your home. But vendor means upstream, and upstream is the only entity to be trusted/responsible for the OS/hardware they provide anyway.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The best and only thing hardware buyers can do is purchase devices that support user unlock/relock. Every purchase of a device that does not support unlock is a vote towards the end of general purpose computing access for mere morals.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>General-purpose computers are fun but insecure, a sad reality, but true. The wind does not blow as the ships desire, as they say.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I couldn’t find any references for this.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/dec/20/whatsapp-pegasus-spyware-nso-group-hacking">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://static.guim.co.uk/images/favicon-32x32.ico" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/dec/20/whatsapp-pegasus-spyware-nso-group-hacking" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="01:38AM - 21 December 2024">the Guardian – 21 Dec 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/414;"><img src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/929f7ea80cf1654f1126abf6c53e5995a624bd9e/0_182_5472_3283/master/5472.jpg?width=1200&amp;height=630&amp;quality=85&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;precrop=40:21,offset-x50,offset-y0&amp;overlay-align=bottom%2Cleft&amp;overlay-width=100p&amp;overlay-base64=L2ltZy9zdGF0aWMvb3ZlcmxheXMvdGctZGVmYXVsdC5wbmc&amp;enable=upscale&amp;s=7a696b1d4ab26343b68d67282ec0349c" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="362"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/dec/20/whatsapp-pegasus-spyware-nso-group-hacking" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US judge finds Pegasus spyware maker liable over WhatsApp hack</a></h3>

  <p>WhatsApp celebrates victory as judge finds Israeli company NSO Group violated state and federal US hacking laws</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>“Though the lawsuit was filed in California, NSO Group made its source code available to view only in Israel by an Israeli citizen, which the judge called “simply impracticable”, according to the ruling.”</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/feb/29/pegasus-surveillance-code-whatsapp-meta-lawsuit-nso-group">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://static.guim.co.uk/images/favicon-32x32.ico" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/feb/29/pegasus-surveillance-code-whatsapp-meta-lawsuit-nso-group" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:53PM - 29 February 2024">the Guardian – 29 Feb 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/414;"><img src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/b54e794b6553cddd82c52adf03b6b325c3ddfcc5/0_117_3500_2101/master/3500.jpg?width=1200&amp;height=630&amp;quality=85&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;precrop=40:21,offset-x50,offset-y0&amp;overlay-align=bottom%2Cleft&amp;overlay-width=100p&amp;overlay-base64=L2ltZy9zdGF0aWMvb3ZlcmxheXMvdGctYWdlLTIwMjQucG5n&amp;enable=upscale&amp;s=4d6b133ab1aa0f97786849c4c3b635ae" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="362"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/feb/29/pegasus-surveillance-code-whatsapp-meta-lawsuit-nso-group" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Court orders maker of Pegasus spyware to hand over code to WhatsApp</a></h3>

  <p>Israeli company NSO Group is accused in lawsuit by Meta’s messaging app of spying on 1,400 users over a two-week period</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>“NSO’s Pegasus code, and code for other surveillance products it sells, is seen as a closely and highly sought state secret. NSO is closely regulated by the Israeli ministry of defence, which must review and approve the sale of all licences to foreign governments.”</p>
<p>…Legal barriers.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It may not be impossible to secure that either.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah sadly i dont see how that can be secure.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>They can require that devices must be unlocked on demand from select people and if they don’t comply, they’re threatened with detention. I don’t see how technology can solve that.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Nothing can be done to solve this. What we can do is ensure only the user can unlock it, nobody else (including the vendor/developer) should have this capability.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>How does one now they got an original iPhone from Apple or one that has been tampered with?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Similar to serial number verification or so:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://checkcoverage.apple.com/">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://apple.com/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="64" height="64">

      <a href="https://checkcoverage.apple.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">checkcoverage.apple.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://checkcoverage.apple.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Check Your Service and Support Coverage - Apple Support</a></h3>

  <p>Check your Apple warranty status. Enter a serial number to review your eligibility for support and extended coverage.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/secure-enclave-sec59b0b31ff/web">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://support.apple.com/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="64" height="64">

      <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/secure-enclave-sec59b0b31ff/web" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Apple Support</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/secure-enclave-sec59b0b31ff/web" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Secure Enclave</a></h3>

  <p>The Secure Enclave is a dedicated secure subsystem in the latest versions of iPhone, iPad, Mac, Apple TV, Apple Watch, Apple Vision Pro, and HomePod.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Note: Multiple layers of protection/tampering detection will be used.</p>
<p>The question is: shall we have purely burned/fixed firmware where they are irreplaceable, non-upgradable which will be impossible to change by design (<a href="https://www.otomasyonavm.com/en/what-is-mask-rom">Mask ROM</a>, <a href="https://semiengineering.com/knowledge_centers/memory/one-time-programmable-memory/">OTP</a>…), or upgradable with signed mechanism (more complexity, more attack surface to protect, but better usability).</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In any case, when someone receives a device, how can they be really sure they received a real device and not a fake device?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Bottom line to solve this, we need one complete ring in the chain of verified/signed software. Nothing will work unless process 123 is met. But yeah, a sealed circle means there is not much room to play with.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Depending on the availability of funding, one day we might formalize the threat model, discuss this with a firmware / hardware vendor and see what can be done.</p>
<p>Complex supply chain attacks: At this point, we have much lower hanging fruit to pick. That is, <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901">Verified Boot</a> on traditional Linux.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yep hopefully one day. The good thing is we now have this maturity of information to understand how future security will be shaped.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171#post_18</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 07:39:50 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3140</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Microsoft Windows ISO writer documentation (write Kicksecure ISO to USB) / balenaEtcher issues</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://consumerrights.wiki/Balena">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://consumerrights.wiki/images/favicon-96x96.png" class="site-icon" width="96" height="96">

      <a href="https://consumerrights.wiki/Balena" target="_blank" rel="noopener">consumerrights.wiki</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="500" height="500" src="https://consumerrights.wiki/images/6/6a/Balena.png" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar">

<h3><a href="https://consumerrights.wiki/Balena" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Balena - Consumer Rights Wiki</a></h3>



  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/microsoft-windows-iso-writer-documentation-write-kicksecure-iso-to-usb-balenaetcher-issues/434#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 09:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3139</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>No Rescue Mode</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes, people should be able to change the software on the same device that they purchased. They shouldn’t need to purchase another device specifically sold as unlocked.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If there is a secure way to do that, i think we gonna have happy world.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is what we’ll hopefully figure out here one day.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>vendor lock: Analysis of suspected infected device is hindered. <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/no_entry.png?v=12" title=":no_entry:" class="emoji" alt=":no_entry:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> (Not completely perfectly prevented. But it can be compared and one state - ease of analysis of rootkits - is better than the other - obfuscation.)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Its like something from reality, like having a door for your home, harder to see inside and harder to enter, but essential for keeping unwanted visitors out. However, very rarely but possible (some people never had it) weak spots like windows, broken walls, or poor door implementation could still let a thief sneak in. Outsiders also can’t easily tell if something’s wrong inside the house. Yet despite these risks, this protection remains absolutely necessary.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not much point for me replying to an analogy.</p>
<p>Why am I using analogies myself? I am using these in addition to technical explanations which are hard/impossible to understand for non-programmers but I am not using purely analogies.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>With vendor lock, you’re at the complete mercy of the vendor.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is the unavoidable big picture - the product user is under the product maker. It’s a reality everywhere, every day. The freedom just eases the forking if you want to do it your way.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The best and only thing hardware buyers can do is purchase devices that support user unlock/relock. Every purchase of a device that does not support unlock is a vote towards the end of general purpose computing access for mere morals.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>What we don’t have - according to my knowledge - at time of writing:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Legal limitation according to my investigation for this case.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I couldn’t find any references for this.</p>
<p>But I found a much more detailed report:</p><aside class="onebox pdf" data-onebox-src="https://info.lookout.com/rs/051-ESQ-475/images/lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://info.lookout.com/rs/051-ESQ-475/images/lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">info.lookout.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <a href="https://info.lookout.com/rs/051-ESQ-475/images/lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span class="pdf-onebox-logo"></span></a>

<h3><a href="https://info.lookout.com/rs/051-ESQ-475/images/lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lookout-pegasus-technical-analysis.pdf</a></h3>

  <p class="filesize">1835.51 KB</p>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Hence, wiki table replaced.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Such attacks are mitigated with full verified boot.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Full verified boot doesn’t protect you if the device is taken, a chip is decapped, malware firmware is installed, or if it can be applied to an SSD or USB ports changed with BadUSB ports or xyz (Check COTTONMOUTH or HOWLERMONKEY… <a href="https://www.eff.org/files/2014/01/06/20131230-appelbaum-nsa_ant_catalog.pdf">here</a>). This doesn’t contradict OS-BIOS verification.</p>
<p>So hardware must be a full circle - leaving xyz areas unchecked - then it can be easily taken, played with, and put back again. So only signed software must be interacting with each other.</p>
<p>Its like a chain of trust, or what so called <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/zero-trust-security-hardware-root">HRoT (Hardware root of trust)</a>.</p>
<p>Note: This probably will also require some software to be burned into the hardware that can’t be changed or removed. Future upgrade to the hardware would be needed to make such core changes, but this is normal anyway - not for the sake of more profits, but for improving security.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Indeed, Intel Boot Guard or an equivalent such as AMD Platform Secure Boot (PSB) or similar is required. A public key must be fused into Intel Guard or alike.</p>
<p>The processor will then verify the (EFI) BIOS.</p>
<p>So while user unlock/relock can be provided for the level of which operating system to boot, it cannot be provided securely against physical attacks for the firmware itself.</p>
<p>BYOB (bring your own bios)  - a system architecture where the device’s essential firmware is not stored in a fixed, soldered chip on the motherboard (as is typical in most modern computers), but instead resides on a removable storage medium like an SD card - might require more work to be secure from the physical attacks that you mentioned.</p>
<p>It may not be impossible to secure that either. But BYOB will probably not happen anytime soon (as no hardware vendor indicated interest) anyhow so there’s no need to develop a concept on how to secure that at this point.</p>
<p>So some things like the firmware can be firmware vendor controlled. However, freedom can be securely provided at the level of the operating system choice.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A) In a situation asked to provide the password (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_disclosure_law">key disclosure law</a>) under the threat of indefinite detention… Bad luck. It’s hard for technology to provide solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Authority of xyz country can access the OS of specific user/s, but they can’t implement anything widely on every device entering their country, for example.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>They can require that devices must be unlocked on demand from select people and if they don’t comply, they’re threatened with detention. I don’t see how technology can solve that.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Attack scenario: Unlock the bootloader, load a malware custom ROM that looks like Google, lock the bootloader, then send the device to the customer. How many users will notice the difference or reinstall the original OS as a security precaution?</p>
<p>Compare this to Apple - I think Apple is the only one taking pioneering, advanced steps to solve these issues (but sadly all in nonfree way).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Supply_Chain_Attacks">Supply Chain Attacks</a> (new wiki chapter created just now) are an issue indeed but in any case, vendor lock-in or no vendor lock-in.</p>
<p>How does one now they got an original iPhone from Apple or one that has been tampered with?</p>
<p>The problem with hardware is, it cannot be hashed. With software it’s possible to calculate as has an compare but with hardware this is impossible. See <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fw5FEuGRrLE">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fw5FEuGRrLE</a> on the topic of hashing (checksumming) hardware.</p>
<p>Since forbes (<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2017/03/23/wikileaks-cia-apple-mac-iphone-hacking/" class="inline-onebox">Fresh Wikileaks Dump Shows CIA Was Hacking iPhones A Year After Launch</a>) is linking to wikilleaks, I think I can too.</p>
<p>Quote <a href="https://wikileaks.org/vault7/document/NightSkies_v1_2_User_Guide/NightSkies_v1_2_User_Guide.pdf">https://wikileaks.org/vault7/document/NightSkies_v1_2_User_Guide/NightSkies_v1_2_User_Guide.pdf</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>(S) NightSkies (NS) version 1.2 is a beacon/loader/implant tool for the Apple iPhone 3G v2.1. The tool operates in the background providing upload, download and execution capability on the device. NS is installed via physical access to the device and will wait for user activity before beaconing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(S) Features:<br>
• Retrieves files from iPhone including Address Book, SMS, Call Logs (when available), etc.<br>
• Sends files and binaries to the iPhone such as future tools<br>
• Executes arbitrary commands on the iPhone<br>
• Grants full remote command and control<br>
• Masquerades as standard HTTP protocol for communications<br>
• Uses XXTEA block encryption to provide secure communications<br>
• Provides self-upgrade capability</p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="onebox stackexchange" data-onebox-src="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/154742/can-i-detect-a-firmware-toolkit-like-nightskies-on-my-iphone">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/154742/can-i-detect-a-firmware-toolkit-like-nightskies-on-my-iphone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">security.stackexchange.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
      <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/users/63721/tracy-cramer" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    <img alt="Tracy Cramer" src="https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/28421dffa7471c8852849161418fb842?s=256&amp;d=identicon&amp;r=PG" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="256" height="256">
  </a>

<h4>
  <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/154742/can-i-detect-a-firmware-toolkit-like-nightskies-on-my-iphone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Can I detect a firmware toolkit like NightSkies on my iPhone?</a>
</h4>

<div class="tags">
  <strong>tools, iphone, firmware</strong>
</div>

<div class="date">
  asked by
  
  <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/users/63721/tracy-cramer" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    Tracy Cramer
  </a>
  on <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/questions/154742/can-i-detect-a-firmware-toolkit-like-nightskies-on-my-iphone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">08:48PM - 23 Mar 17 UTC</a>
</div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<blockquote>
<p>The only real way to compare if a firmware image has been modified is to be able to take the firmware from the device, take a hash of it, and compare it to the hash of a known good copy.</p>
<p>The image taken from the device must be obtained in such a way that any malware on the device can’t tamper with the image being exported (i.e. obtain the image before the system boots). I’m not too familiar with iPhone forensic tools, so I couldn’t tell you the cost to do something like this.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So once a user receives a vendor locked device that has been compromised through a supply chain attack, they cannot even find out that the device has been compromised.</p>
<p>BYOB (bring your own BIOS) - where one can easily extract, checksum and/or replace the firmware by replacing the sd card sounds not so bad after all.</p>
<p>In any case, when someone receives a device, how can they be really sure they received a real device and not a fake device? Ok, it’s not so easy to copycat the latest, fastest device on the market. Maybe it’s just a thin client combined with a relay attack.</p>
<aside class="onebox pdf" data-onebox-src="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/woot17/woot17-paper-shwartz.pdf">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/woot17/woot17-paper-shwartz.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">usenix.org</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/woot17/woot17-paper-shwartz.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span class="pdf-onebox-logo"></span></a>

<h3><a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/woot17/woot17-paper-shwartz.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">woot17-paper-shwartz.pdf</a></h3>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2017/08/hacking_a_phone.html">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.schneier.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-favicon-1-32x32.png" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2017/08/hacking_a_phone.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="06:22AM - 28 August 2017">Schneier on Security – 28 Aug 17</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2017/08/hacking_a_phone.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hacking a Phone Through a Replacement Touchscreen - Schneier on Security</a></h3>

  <p>Researchers demonstrated a really clever hack: they hid malware in a replacement smart phone screen. The idea is that you would naively bring your smart phone in for repair, and the repair shop would install this malicious screen without your...</p>

  <p>
    <span class="label1">Est. reading time: 1 minute</span>
  </p>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Hardware wallets also have this issue. Is it a real hardware wallet, have malicious parts been added?</p>
<p><a href="https://support.ledger.com/article/4404389367057-zd" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://support.ledger.com/article/4404389367057-zd</a></p>
<p>Supply chain attacks, malicious parts are a hard one. Hardware implants, hardware replacements, and whatnot.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="16" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Attack scenario: Unlock the bootloader, load a malware custom ROM that looks like Google, lock the bootloader, then send the device to the customer.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We can refer to this as the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Forged Verified Boot Attack: Re-locks bootloader using attacker’s key to fake a secure boot state. Device appears secure but isn’t. A variant of phishing where the OS mimics a trusted UI (e.g., “Google Pixel” lookalike with backdoors).</li>
<li>Relocking Attack: synonym, same as above</li>
<li>Malicious Bootloader Re-lock Attack: synonym, same as above</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Solution?</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Tamper-Evident Verified Boot: Makes any modification to the boot chain detectable to the user. See:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://source.android.com/docs/security/features/verifiedboot/boot-flow" class="inline-onebox">Boot flow &nbsp;|&nbsp; Android Open Source Project</a></li>
<li><a href="https://source.android.com/docs/security/features/verifiedboot/device-state#user-settable-root-of-trust" class="inline-onebox">Device state &nbsp;|&nbsp; Android Open Source Project</a></li>
<li>User Notified of Changes: During boot, if the device detects enrollment of a non-stock key, it shows a distinct warning screen and reveals the public key fingerprint. This makes faked stock ROMs with re-locked bootloader keys highly detectable.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Remote_Attestation">Remote Attestation</a>: Potentially, in addition, but not as a primary defense.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Counter attacks to that solution:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Boot_User_Interface_Spoofing_Attack">Boot User Interface Spoofing Attack</a></li>
<li>fake device + <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Firmware_authentication.2C_avoiding_relay_attacks">relay attacks</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I think verified boot for the forseeable future will be primiarily useful against remote, software based attacks. Not against hardware implants, fake hardware.</p>
<p>Verified boot can:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<ol>
<li>Verified boot makes sure that the boot process has not been tampered with. (So if previously malware modified the system, it can be spotted and boot aborted before executing the malicious code.) And;</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<ol start="2">
<li>Detect unauthorized, unexpected write access by malware. Quote <a href="https://source.android.com/docs/security/features/verifiedboot/verified-boot" class="inline-onebox">Verify Boot &nbsp;|&nbsp; Android Open Source Project</a></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p>verification is a continuous process happening as data is loaded into memory</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>(related: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#When_the_verification_is_over.3F">When the verification is over?</a>)</p>
<p>Depending on the availability of funding, one day we might formalize the threat model, discuss this with a firmware / hardware vendor and see what can be done.</p>
<p>Complex supply chain attacks: At this point, we have much lower hanging fruit to pick. That is, <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a> on traditional Linux.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171#post_17</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 17:00:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3138</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>For clarification, the radiation hardening thing was a bit of a joke. “Radiation hardened” is a term used on Code Golf Stack Exchange for a program that still behaves as intended even if you delete any single arbitrary character from the program (or in some instances, multiple arbitrary characters). This can be fun to do for small projects but would be extraordinarily difficult (maybe even impossible) for anything beyond that, as can be demonstrated by the ridiculous lengths people need to go to in order to make even a small radiation-hardened program. I only brought it up because it was vaguely similar to making programs immune to random bit flips in RAM, which IMO is usually impractical and the wrong way to handle the problem anyway. Like I mentioned earlier, the solution to RowHammer isn’t to make bit-flip-resilient software, it’s to prevent the bits from flipping in the first place.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139?page=2#post_23</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 01:03:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3137</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="20" data-topic="1139">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Should Kicksecure <a href="https://codegolf.stackexchange.com/questions/57257/radiation-hardened-quine" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">implement radiation</a> hardening to have better security on airplanes and space vehicles and against radiation based attacks?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Like <code>CONFIG_EDAC</code> (Error Detection And Correction) and <code>CONFIG_RAS</code> (Reliability, Availability, Serviceability)?</p>
<p>rasdaemon is a userspace logger so would that even work with the configs already set or would they conflict?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>against radiation based attacks?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Like TEMPEST?</p>
<p>Most desktop environments as I recall, like Xfce are not using TEMPEST-resistant fonts by default.</p>
<p><a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/rc3-11444-etherify_-_bringing_the_ether_back_to_ethernet#t=513" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Defense against soft TEMPEST via Ethernet acting as an antenna</a></p>
<p>This research in this video briefly mentions that Tails has TEMPEST resistant or hardened fonts but I cant find the cited source in the video but I’m pretty sure its “monospaced fonts” or fonts that don’t have “Anti-aliasing” (Disable Anti-Aliasing for Fonts).</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139?page=2#post_22</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3136</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="20" data-topic="1139">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>to have better security on airplanes and space vehicles and against radiation based attacks?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It’s more of an OS+hardware thing, not just software… But yeah any vulnerability even if it’s only possible in a closed laboratory with internet speeds or hardware that only exist there then it should be reported to the developers. Quantum computers vs classical encryption is one example.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139?page=2#post_21</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 18:31:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3135</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>No Rescue Mode</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>vendor lock: Analysis of suspected infected device is hindered. <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/no_entry.png?v=12" title=":no_entry:" class="emoji" alt=":no_entry:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> (Not completely perfectly prevented. But it can be compared and one state - ease of analysis of rootkits - is better than the other - obfuscation.)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Its like something from reality, like having a door for your home, harder to see inside and harder to enter, but essential for keeping unwanted visitors out. However, very rarely but possible (some people never had it) weak spots like windows, broken walls, or poor door implementation could still let a thief sneak in. Outsiders also can’t easily tell if something’s wrong inside the house. Yet despite these risks, this protection remains absolutely necessary.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>What we don’t have - according to my knowledge - at time of writing:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Legal limitation according to my investigation for this case.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Such attacks are mitigated with full verified boot.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Full verified boot doesn’t protect you if the device is taken, a chip is decapped, malware firmware is installed, or if it can be applied to an SSD or USB ports changed with BadUSB ports or xyz (Check COTTONMOUTH or HOWLERMONKEY… <a href="https://www.eff.org/files/2014/01/06/20131230-appelbaum-nsa_ant_catalog.pdf">here</a>). This doesn’t contradict OS-BIOS verification.</p>
<p>So hardware must be a full circle - leaving xyz areas unchecked - then it can be easily taken, played with, and put back again. So only signed software must be interacting with each other.</p>
<p>Its like a chain of trust, or what so called <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/zero-trust-security-hardware-root">HRoT (Hardware root of trust)</a>.</p>
<p>Note: This probably will also require some software to be burned into the hardware that can’t be changed or removed. Future upgrade to the hardware would be needed to make such core changes, but this is normal anyway - not for the sake of more profits, but for improving security.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A) In a situation asked to provide the password (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_disclosure_law">key disclosure law</a>) under the threat of indefinite detention… Bad luck. It’s hard for technology to provide solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Authority of xyz country can access the OS of specific user/s, but they can’t implement anything widely on every device entering their country, for example.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If an adversary gets physical access to a computer (alike device) (such as phones), disappears with it and then comes back</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>What im saying is how to kill this attack.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>You didn’t answer my question:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>What’s the unfixable security issue(s) that can only be fixed by hard vendor lock to Google only with no user unlock/relock allowed?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I am sure, Google, GrapheneOS and others would be most interested the read your vulnerability report, if this was an indeed an issue.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Attack scenario: Unlock the bootloader, load a malware custom ROM that looks like Google, lock the bootloader, then send the device to the customer. How many users will notice the difference or reinstall the original OS as a security precaution?</p>
<p>Compare this to Apple - I think Apple is the only one taking pioneering, advanced steps to solve these issues (but sadly all in nonfree way).</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>With vendor lock, you’re at the complete mercy of the vendor.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is the unavoidable big picture - the product user is under the product maker. It’s a reality everywhere, every day. The freedom just eases the forking if you want to do it your way.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Accidentally push an automatic update that bricks the device forever.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I’m not sure how that’s possible without upstream making something go horribly wrong with the update. Its a very unlikely scenario to happen.</p>
<p>But having it on for system updates - I dont see it as a bad thing, as it will ensure the system gets updated on time. It can be optional but on by default, not a big deal.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planned_obsolescence">Planned obsolescence - Wikipedia</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Nobody should support this, because it’s done for profits sake. But on the other hand, you can’t have hardware/software remain secure and working forever, so sane obsolescence is an unavoidable/mandatory step.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If vendor lock-in is sufficient freedom for you if you cannot replace the software on devices that you purchased, then you’re not sharing the values of this project.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I’m a freedom maximalist, meaning I love to have everything as free software because it’s the user’s right to know what they’re using and securely verify the code is safe.</p>
<p>But the freedom must come with a secure environment:</p>
<p>So Step 1: Free the software - good, we have free software</p>
<p>Step 2: But it’s not functioning well (ugly). Okay, let’s have:</p>
<ul>
<li>Text editors helping, compiler hardenings…</li>
<li>Entire secure programming languages that avoid human mistakes</li>
</ul>
<p>Great, we’ve pretty much covered that in our time.</p>
<p>Step 3: Secure the code path until it reaches the user: We are here (and we sadly lag far behind when it comes to hardware).</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes, people should be able to change the software on the same device that they purchased. They shouldn’t need to purchase another device specifically sold as unlocked.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If there is a secure way to do that, i think we gonna have happy world.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171#post_16</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 18:01:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3134</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>No, that’s not what I meant. There’s no such obligation.</p>
<p>I am not going around telling all projects of some issue that applies to them. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/7556" class="inline-onebox">audit and protect from Qubes source code for malicious unicode - CVE-2021-42574 · Issue #7556 · QubesOS/qubes-issues · GitHub</a> or</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/onionshare/onionshare/issues/221" class="inline-onebox">sign all git commits · Issue #221 · onionshare/onionshare · GitHub</a></li>
<li>or similar.</li>
</ul>
<p>But anyone else can feel free to do this.</p>
<hr>
<p>What I was asking was…</p>
<p>Should Kicksecure <a href="https://codegolf.stackexchange.com/questions/57257/radiation-hardened-quine">implement radiation</a> hardening to have better security on airplanes and space vehicles and against radiation based attacks?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139#post_20</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 12:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3133</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="18" data-topic="1139">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Should also go report 100 of CVEs to implement <a href="https://codegolf.stackexchange.com/questions/57257/radiation-hardened-quine">radiation hardening</a> to have better security on airplanes and space vehicles and against radiation based attacks?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>You mean lets say a research institute found a vulnerability effecting 1000s of projects because they are using the same library or code issue…etc, the research institute if they can inform all of them this is a bad thing?</p>
<p>And if not by them, someone saw the study and informed other… this is good thing, im not sure hows that can be bad.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139#post_19</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 11:16:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3132</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="17" data-topic="1139">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="16" data-topic="1139">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>And now one could go to 1000s of other projects and report CVEs because they’re using a similar more rowhammer vulnerable coding style.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It should be if possible.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Should also go report 100 of CVEs to implement <a href="https://codegolf.stackexchange.com/questions/57257/radiation-hardened-quine">radiation hardening</a> to have better security on airplanes and space vehicles and against radiation based attacks?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139#post_18</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 09:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3131</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
