<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>Research into Wiping video RAM (VRAM) on shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>There are a lot of questions here; generally it’s better to have one forum post per question to keep things easy to track. (We use posts, especially development posts, to track individual things that need worked on, so keeping one topic per post makes us able to do that.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="1" data-topic="1404">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>When the system powers down, the kernel stops the CPUs and tells each driver to simply hand the device back to the firmware. The firmware may or may not clear the memory when power is removed. Complete loss of power guarantees erasure usually right?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It’s supposed to, and in practice it <strong>usually</strong> does. Unfortunately, it doesn’t <em>always</em> do so, 3mdeb did some research on how different RAM responds to power loss and some of it can maintain a substantial amount of data for alarmingly long. (One particular 4GB DDR4 DIMM from Kingston ended up retaining a tiny, but recognizable, amount of data for <em>two minutes</em> after power loss. Most other memory tested didn’t do that, but it’s dependent on the particular RAM you have.) See:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2024/2024-12-13-ram-data-decay-research/">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2024/2024-12-13-ram-data-decay-research/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blog.3mdeb.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2024/2024-12-13-ram-data-decay-research/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thoughts dereferenced from the scratchpad noise.  | Research of RAM data...</a></h3>



  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-01-24-ram-data-decay-research-part2/">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-01-24-ram-data-decay-research-part2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blog.3mdeb.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-01-24-ram-data-decay-research-part2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thoughts dereferenced from the scratchpad noise.  | Research of RAM data...</a></h3>



  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-02-20-conclusions-from-ram-data-remanence-tests/">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-02-20-conclusions-from-ram-data-remanence-tests/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blog.3mdeb.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://blog.3mdeb.com/2025/2025-02-20-conclusions-from-ram-data-remanence-tests/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thoughts dereferenced from the scratchpad noise.  | Conclusions from RAM data...</a></h3>



  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Many systems (all of them except for those with discrete GPUs) have video and system memory on the same RAM modules, so turning off the GPU first probably wouldn’t help much. What would help is the ability to wipe RAM when it’s no longer used, which we try to do via the kernel parameters <code>init_on_alloc=1</code> and <code>init_on_free=1</code> (both of which are set in <code>security-misc-shared</code>). It’s unclear if the Intel and AMD graphics subsystems actually obey these kernel parameters though; if the GPU reserves memory entirely for its own use, it might be out of the kernel’s control. Systems with discrete GPUs are even less likely to obey those settings.</p>
<p>We have a task made to look at wiping VRAM (<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/todo#wipe_video_RAM" class="inline-onebox">ToDo for Developers</a>), but it’s pretty low in the priority list.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/research-into-wiping-video-ram-vram-on-shutdown/1404#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 01:20:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3821</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>For how long would it be safe to use 17.4.4.6?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Banebere" data-post="1" data-topic="1406">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/b/7ba0ec/48.png" class="avatar"> Banebere:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The question goes for whonix 17 also, but to put it mildly 18 needs a bit of polishing,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Are there specific things that need polishing (beyond the one mentioned here)? From our standpoint Kicksecure 18 is stable, and while we are still polishing some things to make them more user-friendly, it’s very possible we’ll miss things if they aren’t pointed out. (Everyone’s use case is different, so we’re naturally more likely to notice issues that impact our workflows, and we don’t have telemetry to tell us what other people’s workflows are.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Banebere" data-post="1" data-topic="1406">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/b/7ba0ec/48.png" class="avatar"> Banebere:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>the main thing is that i need copy paste and with the wayland bug on virtualbox I aint getting that.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah, that is a problem. We’re somewhat at the mercy of Oracle here, once they fix it things should work, but until then we’re sort of stuck in a bind. (KVM is busted in a similar way, no working Wayland support in spice-vdagent.) Shared folders can be used as a workaround.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Banebere" data-post="1" data-topic="1406">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/b/7ba0ec/48.png" class="avatar"> Banebere:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So the question is for how long will the 17.4.4.6 versions of whonix and kick be safe to use?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Usually previous major versions of Kicksecure are considered end-of-life pretty shortly after new major version are released. Because of Qubes OS considerations, we’ll probably support version 17 for another couple of months or so, but I wouldn’t expect it to be much longer than that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/for-how-long-would-it-be-safe-to-use-17-4-4-6/1406#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 01:05:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3820</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Extrepo doesn&#39;t include Trixie</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Debian Salsa is Debian’s official Git forge, and it is a Gitlab instance. While I don’t know for certain if <em>that specific</em> extrepo repository is the official one upstream, I wouldn’t be surprised if it was, and extrepo is part of Debian. Our documentation recommends using it in some areas, so it would be good if it were kept up-to-date. I may be able to get the time to submit a fix upstream to re-enable the Trixie repo now that we have one.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/extrepo-doesnt-include-trixie/1396#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 01:01:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3819</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Switch LXQT compositor/labwc settings?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="zaliv" data-post="1" data-topic="1403">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/53a042/48.png" class="avatar"> zaliv:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>That said, given this is LXQT, is there a way to access the settings of labwc</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t think a GUI for this is pre-installed in Kicksecure. There is <a href="https://github.com/labwc/labwc-tweaks">labwc-tweaks</a>, but unfortunately that isn’t present in Debian Trixie (which Kicksecure 18 is based on), and it doesn’t have signed releases so we were reticent to package it ourselves. Currently the best way to tweak labwc settings is to read <a href="https://labwc.github.io/labwc-config.5.html">labwc’s documentation</a> and place your customizations in <code>~/.config/labwc/rc.xml</code> or another appropriate configuration file. (Note that we have layered configuration enabled in labwc, so you should only have to set the settings you want to <em>change</em>; anything that isn’t explicitly specified will fall back to system-wide configuration.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="zaliv" data-post="1" data-topic="1403">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/53a042/48.png" class="avatar"> zaliv:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>and/or change the compositor to Sway (for tiling)?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We don’t <em>explicitly</em> support switching to Sway, and because of how our Wayland session works it might be difficult to do so. <code>/usr/libexec/desktop-config-dist/start-lxqt-session</code> should give you a good starting point to work from, but keep in mind changes made to this file will be overwritten by upgrades of <code>desktop-config-dist</code> so modifying it directly is not recommended.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="zaliv" data-post="1" data-topic="1403">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/53a042/48.png" class="avatar"> zaliv:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I couldn’t see any GUI settings for this, but I was pretty sure they existed (granted it has been a while since I last used LXQT).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>They exist <em>under X11</em>. Unfortunately a lot of the GUI configuration tools in LXQt 2.1 are disabled when using Wayland, and some of the tools will likely remain that way permanently because LXQt doesn’t want to add compositor-specific code if possible. Tools like labwc-tweaks are supposed to fill in the gaps there, and we also have been creating some of our own tools (like <code>set-labwc-keymap</code> and <code>set-system-keymap</code>) to fill in more of the gaps.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="zaliv" data-post="1" data-topic="1403">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/53a042/48.png" class="avatar"> zaliv:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is there any way to change these safely?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Modifying user-specific configuration files like mentioned above is probably the best way forward.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/switch-lxqt-compositor-labwc-settings/1403#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3818</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Assuming it works at all, it will almost certainly work with the panic keyboard shortcut. Unsure if it will work with drive unplug, feel free to try it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_33</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:51:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3817</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="5" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is <code>rd.live.ram=</code> depreciated or changed? What branch is dracut sourced from? Is it from testing I’d assume right?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not that I’m aware of. Kicksecure doesn’t use it in our packages, and I doubt it would work on a fully installed system since it likely wants to copy a live image into RAM, not an installed partition. If you want to try using it with the ISO (or in other contexts), you’re welcome to; the 90dmsquash-live module in Kicksecure’s version of dracut seems to have the ability to parse <code>rd.live.ram</code>, so I assume it’s supported.</p>
<p>Kicksecure is using the same version of Dracut that’s in Debian Trixie. Right now that’s version 106-6 (so upstream version 106, Debian revision 6). We’ll probably stick with that for the duration of Kicksecure 18’s support.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="6" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Has Kicksecure fully transitioned to dracut as its initramfs generator?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We have indeed. We were using it as our primary initramfs generator in Kicksecure 17, but had initramfs-tools support as a fallback. In Kicksecure 18 we dropped the initramfs-tools support and are relying solely on Dracut.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="6" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is Kicksecure the first debian based distro that uses dracut?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not sure. We’ve been using it longer than Ubuntu, but not sure if we’re the first. It works for us and our users, that’s what we care about mainly.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 00:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3816</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>For how long would it be safe to use 17.4.4.6?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Banebere]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The question goes for whonix 17 also, but to put it mildly 18 needs a bit of polishing, the main thing is that i need copy paste and with the wayland bug on virtualbox I aint getting that. Also for some reason KVM slows down my machine to a craw.<br>
So the question is for how long will the 17.4.4.6 versions of whonix and kick be safe to use?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/for-how-long-would-it-be-safe-to-use-17-4-4-6/1406#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 08:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3815</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Research into Wiping video RAM (VRAM) on shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><code>cat /sys/class/drm/card*/device/power_state</code> returns D0 or D3cold indicating the power state</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/research-into-wiping-video-ram-vram-on-shutdown/1404#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 02:30:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3814</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Would <code>rd.live.ram=1</code> work with emerg-shutdown?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_32</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 02:20:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3813</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Extrepo doesn&#39;t include Trixie</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Is that even official I didn’t think it was on Gitlab?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/extrepo-doesnt-include-trixie/1396#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 02:15:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3812</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Research into Wiping video RAM (VRAM) on shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>While browsing the grub‑live wiki I discovered that neither grub‑live nor Tails clears VRAM when the system shuts down.</p>
<p>When the system powers down, the kernel stops the CPUs and tells each driver to simply hand the device back to the firmware. The firmware may or may not clear the memory when power is removed. Complete loss of power guarantees erasure usually right?</p>
<p>With the nohibernate flag now in play, could this interfere with reaching the deepest D3 cold power state? I’m no computer scientist, but my intuition says there shouldn’t be a direct link.<br>
Has anyone published research on this topic? Is a reliable feature even feasible for Kicksecure?</p>
<p>How could you turn the GPU off before the CPU?</p>
<p>Does an already normal linux shutdown put devices in D3 cold?</p>
<p>For context, I’ve been looking at kernel GPU parameters and both AMD and Radeon expose runtime power management flags that let the GPU request D3 Cold.</p>
<p>Building on a previous discussion about dracut and grub‑live, I’m wondering whether we can leverage <code>rd.driver.pre=</code> and <code>rd.driver.post=</code> to force the amdgpu module to load inside the initramfs before the real root mounts. Then keep that module loaded after the real root is mounted so it is still present when the dracut‑shutdown stage runs? I’d presume that it wouldn’t be as simple as just this alone. Something like the ram-wipe Dracut module?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/research-into-wiping-video-ram-vram-on-shutdown/1404#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 02:12:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3810</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Switch LXQT compositor/labwc settings?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@zaliv]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi, new Kicksecure user here. Before I continue, I want to say, thank you so much for this distro. This is amazing. This distro let me get what would have been weeks of work and plenty of holes from my knowledge gaps solved with a simple gui install. Between GrapheneOS and this, it’s amazing that we have tools that make some level of security <em>easy.</em></p>
<p>I’m fairly used to a traditional Linux desktop, where I have a window manager setup. Personally I would have loved if Kicksecure would provide a cli version to install on metal, but it seems the only option for that is morphing debian, which is not really what I want to do. I understand this is a low priority for most users, and obviously, the focus of this is security, not customization. That said, given this is LXQT, is there a way to access the settings of labwc and/or change the compositor to Sway (for tiling)? Some of my keyboard buttons (volume, most importantly)are not working, and I would like to add some keyboard shortcuts, but on Wayland, this needs to be done through the compositor, not LXQT. I couldn’t see any GUI settings for this, but I was pretty sure they existed (granted it has been a while since I last used LXQT). Have these been hidden for a security reason, or am I misremembering? Is there any way to change these safely?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/switch-lxqt-compositor-labwc-settings/1403#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 00:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3809</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Please post log output or a screenshot should that still be an issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It was an old install so no longer have logs…looking to flash a new ISO</p>
<p>Has Kicksecure fully transitioned to dracut as its initramfs generator? Is Kicksecure the first debian based distro that uses dracut? Looks like Fedora/RHEL has used it for awhile, which is not debian though.</p>
<p>After digging I see Ubuntu is switching to Dracut following 25.10 release.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 23:32:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3807</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Note that toram appears to be specific to live-tools and initramfs-tools. Kicksecure uses Dracut for initramfs management; the corresponding feature in Dracut appears to be rd.live.ram=1. I wouldn’t expect this to work with an installed Kicksecure system, but it might work on the ISO.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is <code>rd.live.ram=</code> depreciated or changed? What branch is dracut sourced from? Is it from testing I’d assume right?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 23:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3806</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you both for your replies</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 23:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3805</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/342">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/342" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/342" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Evaluate Blocking vendor‑specific USB Classes (e.g., FFh) in USBGuard?</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-12-15" data-time="16:13:44" data-timezone="UTC">04:13PM - 15 Dec 25 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/Gerry-Manders" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/225925156?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          Gerry-Manders
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">My ethernet usb adapter shows `with-interface ff:ff:00 with-connect-type "hotplu<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">g"`

&gt;Base Class FFh (Vendor Specific)
&gt;&gt; This base class is defined for vendors to use as they please. These class codes can be used in both Device and Interface Descriptors.

`ff:*:*` is the vendor‑specific class code (class 0xFF) with a vendor‑specific subclass (0xFF) and protocol 0x00. It is commonly used by USB‑Ethernet chips (e.g., ASIX AX88179, Realtek RTL8153) and other devices that provide their own *proprietary protocol* over USB.

https://www.asix.com.tw/en/product/USBEthernet/Super-Speed_USB_Ethernet/AX88179A

https://devicehunt.com/view/type/usb/vendor/0B95

https://forum.openwrt.org/t/usb-to-ethernet-adapter-asix-elec-corp-ax88x72a/164968/7

F****** proprietary should I be concerned now or what? Because the class is undefined by the USB‑IF, can it also be abused to hide unexpected functionality? 

With so much proprietary today is it only generic adapters that use this? Do you think its commonplace with name brand Ethernet adapters commonly found in box stores to also use vendor-specific aka proprietary?


Also both my mouse and keyboard I bought in person say HID? ( I bought in person not online)

Wired optical mouse (Walmart ONN brand) output: `with-interface 03:01:02 with-connect-type "hotplug"`

Wired keyboard output: `with-interface { 03:01:01 03:00:00 } with-connect-type "hotplug"`

The USB Ethernet Adapter I bought on Amazon so...kinda worried here

Does the driver listed with usbcore mean that it can secretly use HID or is that global dependency for the whole USB stack of all active USB devices?

```
user@host:~$ lsmod | grep ax88179
ax88179_178a           36864  0
usbnet                 57344  1 ax88179_178a
mii                    16384  2 usbnet,ax88179_178a
usbcore               348160  9 xhci_hcd,ehci_pci,usbnet,usbhid,usb_storage,ehci_hcd,xhci_pci,uas,ax88179_178a
```

Can udev be used to see which kernel driver was selected. Like If a device that should be a plain mouse or ethernet ends up bound to a generic driver that accepts vendor‑specific control transfers would that indicate a red flag?

---
## Key points
### Security surface
&gt; Vendor‑specific class FFh lets a device define its own protocol. An attacker could craft a malicious dongle that pretends to be a harmless peripheral (network card, storage, etc.) while actually executing hidden commands.


### Device compatibility
&gt; A portion of consumer‑grade USB‑Ethernet adapters (ASIX AX88179, Realtek RTL8153, etc.) use class FFh. \
How much that is undetermined and needs more research.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248?page=4#post_63</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 08:46:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3804</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Kvm install mullvad vpn</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Probably unspecific to Kicksecure, could be a proxy issue. This looks relevant:</p>
<aside class="onebox stackexchange" data-onebox-src="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/50840101/curl-35-error1408f10bssl-routinesssl3-get-recordwrong-version-number">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/50840101/curl-35-error1408f10bssl-routinesssl3-get-recordwrong-version-number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stackoverflow.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
      <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/users/9173068/bernhard-jaeger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    <img alt="Bernhard Jaeger" src="https://i.sstatic.net/S0Oau.jpg?s=256" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="256" height="256">
  </a>

<h4>
  <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/50840101/curl-35-error1408f10bssl-routinesssl3-get-recordwrong-version-number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">curl: (35) error:1408F10B:SSL routines:ssl3_get_record:wrong version number</a>
</h4>

<div class="tags">
  <strong>ssl, curl</strong>
</div>

<div class="date">
  asked by
  
  <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/users/9173068/bernhard-jaeger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    Bernhard Jaeger
  </a>
  on <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/50840101/curl-35-error1408f10bssl-routinesssl3-get-recordwrong-version-number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">02:44PM - 13 Jun 18 UTC</a>
</div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-kvm-install-mullvad-vpn/1399#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 22:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3801</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Kvm install mullvad vpn</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@whistleblow]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hey when I try to install Mullvadvpn and importing their pgp key I get the following error–-</p>
<p>“curl: (35) OpenSSL/3.0.17: error:0A00010B:SSL routines::wrong version number<br>
zsh: exit 35    sudo curl -fsSLo /usr/share/keyrings/mullvad-keyring.asc”</p>
<p>Whats the solution to this?</p>
<p>Thanks!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-kvm-install-mullvad-vpn/1399#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 22:21:41 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3800</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Extrepo doesn&#39;t include Trixie</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>In Debian’s extrepo-data, Kicksecure repo doesn’t include Trixie.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://salsa.debian.org/extrepo-team/extrepo-data/-/blob/master/repos/debian/kicksecure.yaml?ref_type=heads">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://salsa.debian.org/uploads/-/system/appearance/favicon/1/gitlabian_32.png" class="site-icon" alt="" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://salsa.debian.org/extrepo-team/extrepo-data/-/blob/master/repos/debian/kicksecure.yaml?ref_type=heads" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitLab</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="64" height="64" src="https://salsa.debian.org/assets/twitter_card-570ddb06edf56a2312253c5872489847a0f385112ddbcd71ccfa1570febab5d2.jpg" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" alt="">

<h3><a href="https://salsa.debian.org/extrepo-team/extrepo-data/-/blob/master/repos/debian/kicksecure.yaml?ref_type=heads" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">repos/debian/kicksecure.yaml · master · External repositories team /...</a></h3>

  <p>Debian Salsa Gitlab</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Can anyone help me issue a pull request to fix it or make an issue in the project? I don’t have an account on Salsa Gitlab.</p>
<p>Thank you</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/extrepo-doesnt-include-trixie/1396#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 16:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3797</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-18-released-major-release-upgrade/1375">Kicksecure 18 has been released and declared stable</a>. <code>emerg-shutdown</code> is provided and is enabled by default. Documentation:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/index.php?title=Emerg-shutdown&amp;stable=0">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765921209" class="site-icon" alt="" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/index.php?title=Emerg-shutdown&amp;stable=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:56AM - 17 December 2025">Kicksecure – 17 Dec 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/index.php?title=Emerg-shutdown&amp;stable=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">emerg-shutdown - Instantly Power Off the System</a></h3>

  <p>emerg-shutdown immediately and forcibly powers off the system if the boot drive is removed or a "panic" key combo is pressed. When used in combination with full disk encryption, it is a powerful tool to prevent data theft by physically present...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>In short, to trigger an emergency shutdown:</p>
<ul>
<li>Unplug the boot drive from the system (if using a USB boot drive), or</li>
<li>Press a “panic shortcut” on the keyboard. By default, the panic shortcut is <code>Ctrl + Alt + End</code>.</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_31</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 03:00:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3796</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>toram noswap nohibernate</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That’s how initramfs-tools calls it.</p>
<p>Kicksecure nowadays uses dracut as initrd generator. So that’s not applicable.</p>
<p>grub-live no longer supports initramfs-tools a this time (and doesn’t look as if we’re getting that back either).</p>
<p>You can look up what these options do in Debian <code>man</code> pages. → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First" class="inline-onebox">Utilize Search Engines, Documentation and AI</a></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Previously I installed grub-live on debian through the Kicksecure repo in the past out of curiosity it said I had swap enabled still which also confuses it me?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t remember such a bug. swap-file-creator always disabled itself once live mode was detected but maybe that message was confusing.</p>
<p>Please post log output or a screenshot should that still be an issue.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Whats different with “grub live” or makes it different from a custom entry that has <code>toram noswap nohibernate</code> chosen and passed after selecting it in the bootloader?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>There’s extensive documentation what grub-live actually does. Both, as user documentation and also a technical summary for developers.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765877425" class="site-icon" alt="" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="11:31AM - 16 December 2025">Kicksecure – 16 Dec 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/430;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/7e/Live-mode-promo.jpg?version=74f76110a32f37836677f4609a5c6551" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="690" height="431"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live" target="_blank" rel="noopener">grub-live - boot an existing Host OS or VM into Live Mode</a></h3>

  <p>Add a Live Mode entry to the grub boot menu on your existing Debian host platform. Stop persistent malware. Read-only mode. Make all writes go to non-persistent storage (RAM) instead of the hard disk.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p><code>nohibernate</code>: grub-live uses that too.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>rd.live.ram=1</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<ul>
<li><code>toram</code>: Is probably the same as <code>rd.live.ram=1</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>See also:<br>
<a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/load-kicksecure-into-ram/1370/2" class="inline-onebox">Load Kicksecure into RAM - #2 by Patrick</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:09:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3793</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>3D acceleration for Kicksecure VMs</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Creating this so I have something to reference for documentation on the wiki.</p>
<p>While attempting to update the glmark2 instructions for Kicksecure 18, I discovered that 3d acceleration under VirtualBox is a mess, at least when using VMSVGA graphics. So far:</p>
<ul>
<li>With 3d accel disabled, everything <em>seems</em> OK, glmark2-wayland runs without problems, but naturally it uses the CPU for everything.</li>
<li>With 3d accel enabled, glmark2-wayland still uses CPU rendering by default, because labwc is started with <code>WLR_RENDERER=pixman</code> set by default. One has to unset this environment variable before starting labwc to get 3d acceleration capabilities to be recognized. Technically this is a Kicksecure limitation that could be fixed.</li>
<li>If you are running with low memory (in my case 768 MB, I had left the VM with this amount of memory on accident), 3d accel is enabled, and glmark2-wayland is <strong>NOT</strong> using 3d accel (i.e. <code>WLR_RENDERER=pixman</code> is set), the VM will spontaneously hang or reboot during the glmark2-wayland test. This is because something (didn’t have the presence of mind to record what) in the kernel ends up doing the equivalent of a segfault, which results in a kernel oops, which results in a kernel panic, which results in an instant reboot..</li>
<li>If you attempt to run glmark2 (just plain glmark2, which will go through Xwayland) without using CPU rendering (<code>WLR_RENDERER=pixman</code>), the glmark2 window will briefly flash on-screen and then vanish.</li>
<li>If you attempt to run glmark2 (the X11 version) with GPU rendering (<code>WLR_RENDERER</code> unset when labwc is started), it will immediately crash <em>labwc itself</em> when launched.</li>
<li>If you attempt to run glmark2-wayland with GPU rendering (<code>WLR_RENDERER</code> unset when labwc is started), it will immediately error out:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">=======================================================
    glmark2 2023.01
=======================================================
    OpenGL Information
    GL_VENDOR:      VMware, Inc.
    GL_RENDERER:    SVGA3D; build: RELEASE;  LLVM;
    GL_VERSION:     4.1 (Compatibility Profile) Mesa 25.0.7-2
    Surface Config: buf=32 r=8 g=8 b=8 a=8 depth=24 stencil=0 samples=0
    Surface Size:   800x600 windowed
=======================================================
[build] use-vbo=false:[destroyed object]: error 7: importing the supplied dmabufs failed
 FPS: 1037 FrameTime: 0.965 ms
=======================================================
                                  glmark2 Score: 1036 
=======================================================
</code></pre>
<p>At this point I’m pretty sure 3d rendering in VirtualBox is just broken. It might work better if using VBoxSVGA graphics, but as I understand it, the 3d acceleration code for that graphics emulator is insecure and can be used for a VM escape.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/3d-acceleration-for-kicksecure-vms/1393#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 04:39:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3792</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Tengu" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/t/d26b3c/48.png" class="avatar"> Tengu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So my question is whats the difference between grub live and a custom grub entry with <code>toram noswap nohibernate</code> flags?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>grub-live mode mounts the root filesystem read-only, and uses one or more writable tmpfs filesystems (which exist purely in RAM) to store file changes. On the other hand, <code>toram</code> copies an ISO live filesystem into RAM entirely, so that you don’t need the boot media plugged in anymore for the system to remain running.</p>
<p>(Note that <code>toram</code> appears to be specific to live-tools and initramfs-tools. Kicksecure uses Dracut for initramfs management; the corresponding feature in Dracut appears to be <code>rd.live.ram=1</code>. I wouldn’t expect this to work with an installed Kicksecure system, but it might work on the ISO. Untested.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 01:37:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3791</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Grub Live vs toram?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Tengu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello Kicksecure,</p>
<p>Been a long time lurker since I started using whonix and really like debian and all that jazz.</p>
<p>So my question is whats the difference between grub live and a custom grub entry with <code>toram noswap nohibernate</code> flags?</p>
<p>Whats different with “grub live” or makes it different from a custom entry that has <code>toram noswap nohibernate</code> chosen and passed after selecting it in the bootloader?</p>
<p>Previously I installed grub-live on debian through the Kicksecure repo in the past out of curiosity it said I had swap enabled still which also confuses it me? That was like many months ago so I’m sure things have changed?</p>
<p>Is it some kind of compression swap like overlay like zram?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grub-live-vs-toram/1391#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 03:55:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3789</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It got blessed stable. See news.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 06:26:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3786</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@DoctorFreeman]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>No problem. And since there doesn’t seem to be a suitable category on Kicksecure forums for my text, I’ll assume that I should just come back later when my project has grown, unless otherwise instructed.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 04:50:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3785</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SpecialBook]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes, that should work, in particular you will want to follow the directions listed under “UEFI firmware fails to pick up Kicksecure boot entry”.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, it helped me. Plugged the SSD into another computer, followed these steps from the wiki via liveCD and grub kicksecure showed up.</p>
<p>Would love to upgrade to whonix 18 in the future once it is stable and there are more options for customization via GUI.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 20:36:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3783</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 18 for Qubes Released! Major Release Upgrade!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>(This forum post was previously a call for testers. No release critical bugs where found during the testing period. This forum post was therefore <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/transform-whonix-testers-wanted-forum-news-post-into-whonix-release-forum-news-post-ok/11405">transformed</a> into a stable release announcement. See edit history.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-18-for-qubes-released-major-release-upgrade/1377#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 15:57:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3782</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 18 Released! Major Release Upgrade!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>(This forum post was previously a call for testers. No release critical bugs where found during the testing period. This forum post was therefore <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/transform-whonix-testers-wanted-forum-news-post-into-whonix-release-forum-news-post-ok/11405">transformed</a> into a stable release announcement. See edit history.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-18-released-major-release-upgrade/1375#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 15:56:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3781</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you for the edit suggestion. Since the GitHub account and repository are new and not yet established, and to protect both security and the reputation of the Kicksecure wiki, I won’t include a link to it at this time.</p>
<p>Self-promotional link additions are problematic. If the project becomes established and the wider community requests its inclusion (based on independent usage/feedback), it can be reconsidered later.</p>
<p>Edit rejected.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 12:49:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3780</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I believe you’ve confused mutli-boot (in the sense of multiple operating systems on internal disks) with portable USB installations. The latter is explicitly supported for general use by end-users, see:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Ah i see, from my personal experience the moments that my partitions didnt show up were:</p>
<ul>
<li>UEFI vs Legacy: If you have UEFI settings + OS/UEFI installed and you used flash drive with legacy OS installed inside it, it wont be seen by the booting process.</li>
<li>BIOS settings: Some PCs wont detect automatically the flash drives inserted, so it needs to be done from the BIOS manually by making the flash/hard drive boot first, then reboot.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hope it can help.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 07:22:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3779</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Very cool, I can confirm I see the edit and the project looks neat! I’ll let <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/patrick">@Patrick</a> decide whether to accept the revision. (I have the ability to accept it, but my wiki powers were granted so I could do parts of my work on Kicksecure better and I’m not really a content moderator.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 01:28:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3778</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@DoctorFreeman]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks. For me the point of confusion was that even though I did click “Save Continue”, a new embedded window popped up and I closed it without actually saving. And submitting warned a loss of session data, as you said. I have saved and submitted again and it seems like it’s waiting for moderator’s approval now.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3777</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It looks like the wiki software didn’t accept your edit. I can’t find your edit anywhere in the pending queue or in the edit history.</p>
<p>Oftentimes when editing a page, I get shown a notice that the edit wasn’t accepted because of a loss of session data. I have to scroll to the bottom of the page and click “Save” again for it to work. Maybe try adding it again?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3776</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not sure if the moderators saw my wiki edit</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@DoctorFreeman]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I made wiki edit on the “Evil Maid Attack” page at the “Detection” section to describe a new anti evil maid tool I built called “Tripwire”, and added some more information to the other text. The editing process was pretty horrible. I can’t see my edit in my wiki account. Can a moderator confirm that they have seen the edit at least?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-sure-if-the-moderators-saw-my-wiki-edit/1387#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:17:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3775</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="4" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Also check:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group">
<blockquote>
<p>Its not only can cause a usability issue as <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Troubleshooting#Dual_Boot" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">mentioned here</a>, but its a <a href="https://forum.qubes-os.org/t/multibooting-qubes/18988" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">security issue</a> as well: One problem is that when you dual or multiboot, even if you are using encryption on your Qubes installation, /boot is still unprotected and could be maliciously modified by the other OS, possibly leading to Qubes itself being maliciously modified. The other problem is firmware security - for example the other system could infect the BIOS firmware, which might enable compromise or spying on the Qubes …</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>So what you want to do yourself is up to you but you need to figure things out yourself.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I believe you’ve confused mutli-boot (in the sense of multiple operating systems on internal disks) with portable USB installations. The latter is explicitly supported for general use by end-users, see:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/USB_Installation">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765445424" class="site-icon" alt="" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/USB_Installation" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc" title="04:38AM - 02 December 2025">Kicksecure – 2 Dec 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/03/Download-usb.jpg?version=fd433a55102b14d723f69090c7e6be4f" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/USB_Installation" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Installation of Kicksecure on a USB</a></h3>

  <p>Yes, Kicksecure can be installed on a USB. Here's how.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SpecialBook" data-post="3" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/7feea3/48.png" class="avatar"> SpecialBook:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>You can’t change many settings through the GUI.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is likely unfortunately a limitation of LXQt 2.1. We’ve tried to create tools to fill in the missing gaps, and will continue to do so as needed.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SpecialBook" data-post="3" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/7feea3/48.png" class="avatar"> SpecialBook:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I couldn’t figure out how to set the system to have two keyboard layouts at once and a way to switch between them.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is documented at:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Keyboard_Layout#Version_18">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765445424" class="site-icon" alt="" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Keyboard_Layout#Version_18" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc" title="03:05PM - 10 December 2025">Kicksecure – 10 Dec 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/419;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/e/ee/Keyboardlayout1282268640.jpg?version=ccdbe7fade73ea30979878ed4a600e0d" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="640" height="419"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Keyboard_Layout#Version_18" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Keyboard Layout</a></h3>

  <p>How to change the Keyboard Layout in Kicksecure.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>In short, boot into sysmaint mode and run <code>sudo set-system-keymap --interactive</code>, then follow the prompts. You will want to use something like <code>us,de</code> for your layout settings, and the option <code>grp:alt_shift_toggle</code> or similar to allow switching layouts by pressing a key combo (in this case, Alt+Shift).</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SpecialBook" data-post="3" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/7feea3/48.png" class="avatar"> SpecialBook:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If I boot into chroot and follow these steps, will it help to restore grub on the new computer?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, that should work, in particular you will want to follow the directions listed under “UEFI firmware fails to pick up Kicksecure boot entry”.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 19:45:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3773</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Multi-user - privleap issue - systemcheck / updatecheck</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Should be fixed for sure since a while already.</p>
<p>There’s now a <code>privleap</code> group.</p>
<pre><code>sudo adduser user2 privleap
</code></pre>
<p>So any additional user account can be added to that group and it should work as well as account <code>user</code>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/multi-user-privleap-issue-systemcheck-updatecheck/1046#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3772</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Sudoless Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Root#sudoless">The word <code>sudoless</code> is used by different people in many different ways.</a></p>
<p>Kicksecure 18 (and above) could be considered <code>sudoless</code> due to <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint">user-sysmaint-split</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/sudoless-kicksecure/139#post_16</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:37:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3771</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Creating new user will not be shown into boot menu</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The GRUB boot menu isn’t directly related which limited non-administrative account (not <code>sysmaint</code> account) will login.</p>
<p>By Kicksecue default, in user session, autologin is enabled for account <code>user</code>. This is probably causing confusion for multi-user use cases.</p>
<p>Additional confusion might be caused by calling a boot session “<code>user session</code>”, which does not refer to Linux login account user “<code>user</code>”.</p>
<p>By disabling autologin a lot confusion will be reduced. Because then the usual GUI or CLI login prompts can be used.</p>
<p>Related user documentation:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/User" class="inline-onebox">User Management</a> wiki page chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/User#Add_a_New_User">Add a New User</a>.
<ul>
<li>(And maybe related chapters such as <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/User#Allow_New_User_to_Login_to_Virtual_Console">Allow New User to Login to Virtual Console</a>.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Also <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Login" class="inline-onebox">Login Security</a> wiki page chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Login#Configuring_GUI_Autologin">Configuring GUI Autologin</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Multi-user - in this context - multiple humans sharing the same operating system on the same computer and using different user accounts for login is probably pretty unpopular for end-users. I think I might have seen some data if this in the past.</p>
<p>Maybe still somewhat popular in some corporate contexts.</p>
<p>So this currently isn’t tested much and isn’t a priority for Kicksecure at the time of writing. At the time when terminology was coined and the word “<code>user session</code>” introduced, perhaps there would have been a better wording that doesn’t confuse it with “account <code>user</code>”.</p>
<p>That is why a feature to choose which Linux user account to login with at GRUB boot will very most likely not be implemented. It would also technically be challanging and make our already demanding (on usability and development effort) GRUB boot menu even more demanding.</p>
<p>related:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/multi-user-privleap-issue-systemcheck-updatecheck/1046" class="inline-onebox">Multi-user - privleap issue - systemcheck / updatecheck</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/creating-new-user-will-not-be-shown-into-boot-menu/1385#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3770</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not Passing any Info from user to sysmaint (NetworkManager) (polkit)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Unfortunately, this is not easy to implement at all. It would require disabling polkit in user session. But this is a technical challange. There are many <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Polkit#Issues_when_disabling_Polkit">Issues when disabling Polkit</a>. References:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Strong_Linux_User_Account_Isolation#Polkit">Polkit</a> (developer documentation)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Polkit" class="inline-onebox">Polkit (formerly PolicyKit) / pkexec</a> (user documentation)</li>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/investigate-security-suid-impact-of-polkitd-and-policykit-libraries/1075" class="inline-onebox">Investigate security (SUID) impact of polkitd and policykit libraries</a> (development discussion)</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Future Kicksecure development roadmap:</p>
<ul>
<li>Polkit might no longer run by default in user session.</li>
<li>We might run polkit only in <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sysmaint">sysmaint</a> session by default.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-passing-any-info-from-user-to-sysmaint-networkmanager-polkit/1384#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:17:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3769</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SpecialBook" data-post="1" data-topic="1382">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/7feea3/48.png" class="avatar"> SpecialBook:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is there no other way?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765359024" class="site-icon" alt="" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="06:18PM - 26 June 2025">Kicksecure – 26 Jun 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/426;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/0a/Unsupported.jpg?version=4c03a6d49994df75ba2ec2ce26d99988" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="640" height="426"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Undocumented, Untested or Unsupported Features</a></h3>

  <p>This feature is either undocumented, untested, or unsupported. Options: Become a Contributor / Apply Self Support First Policy / Purchase Support.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Also check:</p>
<aside class="quote quote-modified" data-post="1" data-topic="1249">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar">
    <div class="quote-title__text-content">
      <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot-developers-only-discussion/1249">Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot [Developers-Only Discussion]</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/development/7"><span data-category-id="7" style="--category-badge-color: #25AAE2; --category-badge-text-color: #FFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category --style-square " title="Development of Kicksecure software and source code. Development Discussion Policy and First-Time Source Code Contributor Policy apply."><span class="badge-category__name">Development</span></span></a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    Its not only can cause a usability issue as <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Troubleshooting#Dual_Boot">mentioned here</a>, but its a <a href="https://forum.qubes-os.org/t/multibooting-qubes/18988">security issue</a> as well: 

One problem is that when you dual or multiboot, even if you are using encryption on your Qubes installation, /boot is still unprotected and could be maliciously modified by the other OS, possibly leading to Qubes itself being maliciously modified. 
The other problem is firmware security - for example the other system could infect the BIOS firmware, which might enable compromise or spying on the Qubes …
  </blockquote>
</aside>

<p>So what you want to do yourself is up to you but you need to figure things out yourself.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 09:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3768</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SpecialBook]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Yes, but unfortunately I understand that version 18 is for testers only. I tried it, but it seemed to me that many things still don’t work as they should. You can’t change many settings through the GUI.<br>
I couldn’t figure out how to set the system to have two keyboard layouts at once and a way to switch between them.</p>
<p>If I boot into chroot and follow these steps, will it help to restore grub on the new computer?</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Broken_Boot#Chroot_Boot_Recovery">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1765359024" class="site-icon" alt="" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Broken_Boot#Chroot_Boot_Recovery" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc" title="01:48PM - 18 May 2025">Kicksecure – 18 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/427;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/59/Broken_boot123.jpg?version=e2a6652ed121d41a5e51da884d4dae36" class="thumbnail" alt="" width="640" height="427"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Broken_Boot#Chroot_Boot_Recovery" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Broken Boot</a></h3>

  <p>System is no longer booting?</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 09:21:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3767</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Creating new user will not be shown into boot menu</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>When a new user created the expectation of the OS user to see this new user popped up automatically on the boot menu so he can use it similarly to user session which comes by default. Otherwise how he can even use the new user?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/creating-new-user-will-not-be-shown-into-boot-menu/1385#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3766</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Not Passing any Info from user to sysmaint (NetworkManager) (polkit)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The ability of passing information from user session to sysmaint session can be used maliciously.</p>
<p>Scenario in my head is that the NetworkManager if configured under user session the same info will be passed to sysmaint, what if the info passed will not be x.x.x.x IP but instead sudo 123?</p>
<p>So user/s sessions shall not pass information of their changes to sysmaint to avoid such scenario.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/not-passing-any-info-from-user-to-sysmaint-networkmanager-polkit/1384#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 09:04:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3765</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>IIRC, Kicksecure 17 had a problem where the fallback bootloader would only provide a GRUB prompt, but not actually boot the system. The real bootloader would boot the system, but that isn’t easily feasible to use in a portable system unless your system’s UEFI firmware has a good bootloader autodetection mechanism or offers a “Boot from File” option.</p>
<p>This seems to be fixed in Kicksecure 18. If you feel like trying a testing release, you might give that a shot and see if it works for you?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3764</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How do I keep up with updates on the wiki?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Good question. I guess there is no perfect way. If there is something very major, we post a news. → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Stay_Tuned" class="inline-onebox">Follow Kicksecure Developments</a></p>
<p>But often there are smaller updates. Perhaps these are posted on social medial. → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Official_Online_Profiles" class="inline-onebox">Official Kicksecure Online Profiles</a> But I guess that’s also not reliable to learn about all wiki changes.</p>
<p>Now, a way to see all wiki edits, is the following wiki URL, <code>Special:RecentChanges</code>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Special:RecentChanges">https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Special:RecentChanges</a></p>
<p>A free account is required to read it. (Reasons for that: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Wiki_History" class="inline-onebox">Wiki History</a>)</p>
<p>There’s also <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Offline_Documentation" class="inline-onebox">Browsing Kicksecure Documentation Offline</a>, specifically <a href="https://gitlab.com/kicksecure/kicksecure-wiki-backup" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure / Kicksecure Wiki Backup · GitLab</a> if you’re willing to use <code>git</code>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-do-i-keep-up-with-updates-on-the-wiki/1383#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 13:06:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3763</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How do I keep up with updates on the wiki?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SpecialBook]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>How do I get notified when new articles appear on the kicksecure wiki to keep up to date with current changes?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-do-i-keep-up-with-updates-on-the-wiki/1383#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 12:34:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3762</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Transfer kicksecure to another computer. can&#39;t see grub</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SpecialBook]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I installed kicksecure on a portable SSD along with linux mint, grub kicksecure boots by default and sees mint.<br>
Moved the SSD to a second computer and it does not see grub kicksecure, but sees grub mint. Why is this happening? Is there an easy way to fix this?<br>
sudo os-prober in mint does not find kicksecure.</p>
<p>Do I have to boot into a live iso system, mount the kicksecure partition there and in chroot mode do this command?<br>
efibootmgr -c -d /dev/sdX -p Y -L ‘Kicksecure’ -l ‘EFI\Kicksecure\shimx64.efi’</p>
<p>Is there no other way?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/transfer-kicksecure-to-another-computer-cant-see-grub/1382#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 12:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3761</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 18 Released! Major Release Upgrade!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@james369]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi, I already am running kicksecure 17 on a macbook 11,3 and it works fine.  I downloaded the testing iso, burnt to usb, held down option and selected the usb.  I tried every grub entry option and after I select it, it runs a line or  2 (something about dracut) and then the laptop just turns off.</p>
<p>I tried to edit the grub entries to add <code>nomodeset</code> but that also had the same result.   I re-downloaded the iso, tried a different usb and get the same result.</p>
<p>As a test I downloaded the xfce kicksecure, did exactly the same method of writing it to the same USB etc.. and it booted into the usb livemode with no errors. So it is surely something with this 18.0.7.5 iso.</p>
<p>I just noticed there is a 18.0.7.6 in the op, I will try that now.</p>
<p>Wonderful! It works a dream! ( whatever you changed from .5 to .6 worked.)<br>
Thanks to all, it looks great.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-18-released-major-release-upgrade/1375#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3760</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Qubes Template Development - Qubes Integration</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/6251">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/6251" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/QubesOS/updates-status</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/6251" target="_blank" rel="noopener">qubes-template-kicksecure-18 4.3.0-202512071252 (r4.3)</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-12-07" data-time="12:52:40" data-timezone="UTC">12:52PM - 07 Dec 25 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/fepitre-bot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/48861364?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          fepitre-bot
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          r4.3-testing
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">Template kicksecure-18 4.3.0-202512071252 for Qubes OS r4.3, see comments below <span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">for details and build status.

If you're release manager, you can issue GPG-inline signed command (depending on template):

* `Upload-template r4.3 kicksecure-18 4.3.0-202512071252 templates-itl` (available 5 days from now)
* `Upload-template r4.3 kicksecure-18 4.3.0-202512071252 templates-community` (available 5 days from now)

Above commands will work only if package in testing repository isn't superseded by newer version.

For more information on how to test this update, please take a look at https://www.qubes-os.org/doc/testing/#updates.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-qubes-template-development-qubes-integration/679?page=2#post_29</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 14:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3759</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
