<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="14" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Google dictates how apps must be built, packaged, and behave if they want to be distributed through the Play Store. Google can reject apps that don’t comply with sandboxing or violate permissions. Google Android developers have to use SDK and libraries dictated by Google.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right, and beyond that the Android operating system is designed in such a way where you fundamentally can’t just “do whatever you want”. The way in which the typical Linux desktop works, if someone needs root access and doesn’t want to prompt for it, they can just install a polkit configuration snippet or similar as part of the installation process, and get that access. With Android, not only can you not do that by policy, you can’t do that by design. Furthermore, we have to work with an already-existing app ecosystem with Kicksecure, whereas Android was free to make their own ecosystem from scratch. They don’t need to retain compatibility with anything if they don’t want to, whereas we do have to do that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_15</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 20:23:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2961</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="9" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Android can get away with it because Google can enforce rules about how Android apps are written and we can’t do that with Linux apps.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Could you elaborate a bit on that please?</p>
<p>I guess…</p>
<p>Google dictates how apps must be built, packaged, and behave if they want to be distributed through the Play Store. Google can reject apps that don’t comply with sandboxing or violate permissions. Google Android developers have to use SDK and libraries dictated by Google.</p>
<p>Why we cannot do that on general purpose Linux distributions?</p>
<ul>
<li>There is no central authority. Anyone can write and distribute a Linux application however they want. No organization (like Google on Android) can enforce mandatory sandboxing or privilege separation. More on organizational background: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Linux_User_Experience_versus_Commercial_Operating_Systems" class="inline-onebox">Linux User Experience versus Commercial Operating Systems</a></li>
<li>Most Linux applications weren’t designed with sandboxing in mind. → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/About_Computer_(In)Security#Security_Mindset_of_Open_Source_Software_Ecosystem">Security Mindset of Open Source Software Ecosystem</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_14</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 16:41:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2960</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Detailed overview of the issues with stable and rolling release distributions: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Stable_vs_Rolling_Distributions" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Stable vs Rolling Distributions - Security Analysis</a></p>
<p>Kicksecure’s current development strategy for the most part has been to harden Debian as much as is practically possible. This seems to have been working well for the most part, but there are some worries about the safety of some of the rather outdated software that Debian provides us. In particular:</p>
<ul>
<li>Critical, extremely complicated software like Firefox ESR and Thunderbird can sometimes get stuck with a known-vulnerable version in the latest version of Debian Stable for as long as a month.</li>
<li>Software that isn’t well-maintained may be left in a vulnerable state for long after the vulnerability is made public. (This happened with the zuluCrypt vulnerability discovered in Debian’s zuluCrypt packaging a couple weeks ago or so.)</li>
<li>Tangential to the above, bugs that aren’t considered to be that big of a deal may not be fixed in a stable release of Debian ever. This isn’t really a security issue necessarily, but it is a problem from a usability standpoint.</li>
</ul>
<p>These things would be more-or-less resolved if Kicksecure was a rolling-release distro, for instance by rebasing our code onto a rolling-release variant of Debian (if one were to exist - we sort of almost have one with Debian Testing, but it doesn’t quite serve the desired purpose perfectly). This however is not necessarily more secure:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rolling-release distros rolled out backdoored XZ code to end-users during the xz-utils attack. Thankfully (most of) those distros don’t seem to have been targeted by the backdoor at all, but in principle a backdoored upstream or similar supply chain attack can have a much worse impact when using a rolling release.</li>
<li>Rolling releases steadily introduce the latest bugs and vulnerabilities from upstream into the distro on a regular basis. (There isn’t really any way around this, this isn’t a criticism half so much of a statement of fact.) For software that isn’t so complex as to be riddled with unknown vulnerabilities like web browsers, this is a potentially increased danger.</li>
<li>Rolling releases can break a lot. An experienced user can go years or even over a decade without breaking a rolling release install beyond repair, but an inexperienced user can end up with a broken system within a few weeks if they accidentally do something like upgrade their system without checking what packages will be removed in the process. (I’d like to think I’m an experienced user, and I’ve nuked Debian Sid virtual machines multiple times doing this. Not fun.)</li>
</ul>
<p>It might be possible to combine the advantages of both stable and rolling releases, by keeping Kicksecure’s stable base, but offering “rolling” versions of specific packages like web browsers, email clients, (maybe?) media viewers, etc. Anything that has to handle highly complex untrusted data would be a good candidate for this sort of thing, especially software with a rapid-release cycle. We’re already moving in this direction to some decree with <a>Browser Choice</a>, which is in active development.</p>
<p>What are everyone’s thoughts on the above? Where could our docs use improvement? Are there ideas for how to get the best of both worlds (rolling and stable) other than just a stable base with specific rolling apps? What are some other apps we should probably think about making rolling or recommending that people install rolling versions of if they use those apps? Are there potential pitfalls we need to avoid with rolling apps? (On this last point, we probably should not do what KDE neon did to try to make the Qt and KDE stacks rolling on top of base Ubuntu - that way of doing things kept breaking things for people alarmingly frequently.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 01:30:18 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2959</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive doesn&#39;t trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Unfortunately, despite having developed this feature to the point where I would almost consider it ready to deploy, I have been unable to get it to work reliably on Kicksecure. It works just fine on plain Debian 12, but under Kicksecure it malfunctions in a very strange way that I have yet to figure out. I’ll most likely try to resume work on this for Trixie, in the hopes that things “just work” there.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-doesnt-trigger-a-shutdown/994#post_18</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 03:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2958</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>PureOS instead of Debian</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Vitaly]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Ok, Patrick, I agree with you. You’ve done a great job of choosing the right criteria, respect.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/pureos-instead-of-debian/1137#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 18:23:49 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2957</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>PureOS instead of Debian</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>That’s why there another criteria: <a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Operating_System#Community_Project_versus_Corporate_Project">Community Project versus Corporate Project</a></p>
<p>Added just now to the wiki:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: Debian and Fedora are just illustrative examples to describe the meaning of “Original Base Distributions” / “Tier 1 distributions only”.</p>
<p>This is only one criteria. Distributions must also pass other criteria listed on this wiki page.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is mostly theoretic anyhow. If you keep reading that page, you’ll find:<br>
<a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Operating_System#Requesting_a_Port_to_a_Different_Base_Operating_System">Requesting a Port to a Different Base Operating System</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/pureos-instead-of-debian/1137#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 12:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2955</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>PureOS instead of Debian</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Vitaly]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Tier 1 distributions only: original distributions such as Debian or Fedora - not forks of Debian or other base distributions.  This is because too many derivatives have come and gone over the years.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok, but Fedora is not a free distribution, it is monopolistically owned by Red Hat.<br>
This corporation recently, without consulting its user community, essentially took down the free CentOS.<br>
Furthermore, Fedora is essentially a permanent beta distribution with many bugs.<br>
There are so many bugs in Fedora that Linus, who was using it, once got very angry and cursed about it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/pureos-instead-of-debian/1137#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 12:54:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2954</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>PureOS instead of Debian</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Operating_System#Criteria_for_Choosing_a_Base_Distribution">Criteria for Choosing a Base Distribution</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Operating_System#Original_Base_Distributions_Only">Original Base Distributions Only</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.whonix.org/wiki/Dev/Operating_System#Community_Project_versus_Corporate_Project">Community Project versus Corporate Project</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Policy_On_Nonfreedom_Software">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1752485424" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Policy_On_Nonfreedom_Software" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:55AM - 08 June 2025">Kicksecure – 8 Jun 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="500" height="500" src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/8e/Shield123123213.png?version=562d948614d9c9998bd24cee9e0bcd07" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar">

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Policy_On_Nonfreedom_Software" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kicksecure ™ Policy On Non-Freedom Software</a></h3>

  <p>Permitted / Prohibited Discussions, Project Philosophy on Non-Freedom Software.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/nonfree">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1752485424" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/nonfree" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="09:33PM - 12 April 2025">Kicksecure – 12 Apr 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/nonfree" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Non-Freedom Firmware and Drivers</a></h3>

  <p>nonfree firmware</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/pureos-instead-of-debian/1137#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:35:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2953</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>PureOS instead of Debian</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Vitaly]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Dear developers,</p>
<p>Debian, of course, is a very good OS.<br>
But unfortunately, it and its core contain blobs and proprietary firmwares.</p>
<p>Why don’t you switch to PureOS instead of Debian to improve the security of Kicksecure?<br>
Project PureOS has an exceptionally clean kernel and no proprietary firmwares and drivers (and even an open BIOS).</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/pureos-instead-of-debian/1137#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 21:14:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2952</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Alright. Please implement <code>xz</code>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 04:48:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2949</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive doesn&#39;t trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve added panic key handling to the current emergency shutdown implementation. This will make it so that not only can you trigger an instant shutdown by removing a drive, but you can also do so by pressing a key combo. This is still only in my in-development security-misc and helper-scripts branches, but it’s coming along quite well. Thought I should give an update since it’s been a while since I worked on this <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=12" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-doesnt-trigger-a-shutdown/994#post_17</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 01:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2948</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Testing the settings from Fedora CoreOS:</p>
<ul>
<li>zstd with max compression:
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.01s user 0.03s system 0% cpu 18.719 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.02s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 17.553 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.03s system 0% cpu 17.478 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>29628K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We get a slightly (though only very slightly) larger file than <code>xz</code> would produce, and it takes about 7 seconds longer to produce it than <code>xz</code> or <code>gzip</code> would have taken. <code>xz</code> wins for both size and performance.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 16:02:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2947</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="7" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Keeping the default, uncompressed, also remains an option.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The default is gzip-compressed, not uncompressed. Dracut will indicate that it is using an automatically detected compression method (“pigz”, which is parallel gzip as I understand it) when the compression method is not set. So right now we’re using gzip compression in all instances.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="7" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>D) best boot compatibility for low RAM systems?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Systems with multiple tens of gigabytes of RAM can error out with “no available memory” if trying to boot with an initramfs that is too large. The issue is not “total amount of memory”, the issue is “total amount of contiguous memory that GRUB can see” (if I’m understanding correctly), and on some hardware, GRUB can’t find a very large contiguous block.</p>
<p>xz isn’t the fastest, but it’s faster than gzip, and much more efficient size-wise. I didn’t notice any impact on boot speed, and smaller size provides better compatibility, so that’s why I think xz strikes a good balance between all four points above. zstd sacrifices size (and therefore possibly compatibility) in favor of speed.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 14:07:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2946</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I was wondering what should be the priority here. These are the choices that I could identify:</p>
<ul>
<li>A) small size: optimize Kicksecure images for the smallest possible size?</li>
<li>B) fastest initrd creation time: The smallest amount of time spent on initrd creat during upgrades?</li>
<li>C) boot speed?</li>
<li>D) best boot compatibility for low RAM systems?</li>
</ul>
<p>The C) and D) seem more important than A) and B).</p>
<p>This probably means, for a brief moment during decompression, both the compressed image and the uncompressed (expanded) contents may reside in RAM at the same time. On systems with very limited memory, one might have a RAM usage spike and need enough RAM to hold both the compressed image and the fully decompressed contents simultaneously, at least during the extraction phase.</p>
<p>But I don’t know if that is a realistic consideration as user space might need more memory than this spike.</p>
<p>Keeping the default, uncompressed, also remains an option.</p>
<hr>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://cj.rs/blog/should-i-compress-my-initramfs/">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://cj.rs/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://cj.rs/blog/should-i-compress-my-initramfs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="06:47AM - 31 August 2022">Clément Joly – Open-Source, Rust &amp; SQLite – 31 Aug 22</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/219;"><img src="https://cj.rs/blog/should-i-compress-my-initramfs/trade-off.png" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="219"></div>

<h3><a href="https://cj.rs/blog/should-i-compress-my-initramfs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Should I Compress My Initramfs?</a></h3>

  <p>When decompressing is faster than reading from the disk.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/ytk6t3/blog_should_i_compress_my_initramfs/" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/ytk6t3/blog_should_i_compress_my_initramfs/</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Debian:<br>
Quote Debian bug report: <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=976054">initramfs-tools: [RFC] Compress initramfs file with zstd</a></p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>[742c8ee] Use zstd as default compression for initramfs (Closes: #<a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=976054">976054</a>)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>But we’re not getting this change because we’re using dracut instead of initramfs-tools.<br>
(<a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/replacing-initramfs-tools-with-dracut/4487" class="inline-onebox">replacing initramfs-tools with dracut - Development - Whonix Forum</a>)</p>
<p>related:</p><aside class="onebox discoursetopic" data-onebox-src="https://forums.whonix.org/t/replacing-initramfs-tools-with-dracut/4487/32">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/3/37fe81e592143b0c01c9656c44069b4bfdd3990e_2_32x32.ico" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/replacing-initramfs-tools-with-dracut/4487/32" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="06:06PM - 04 January 2024">Whonix Forum – 4 Jan 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/255;"><img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/original/2X/5/5ac973ff4302e69269667e09e67d850c0b628c7a.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="255"></div>

<div class="title-wrapper">
  <h3><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/replacing-initramfs-tools-with-dracut/4487/32" target="_blank" rel="noopener">replacing initramfs-tools with dracut</a></h3>
  <div class="topic-category">
      <span class="badge-wrapper bullet">
        <span class="badge-category-bg" style="background-color: #25AAE2;"></span>
        <span class="badge-category clear-badge">
          <span class="category-name">Development</span>
        </span>
      </span>
    <div class="topic-header-extra">
      <div class="list-tags">
        <div class="discourse-tags">
          <svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-tag svg-icon svg-string"><use href="#tag"></use></svg>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">milestone_whonix_17</span>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">status_closed_issue_implemented</span>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <p>Summary why Kicksecure was ported from initramfs-tools to dracut:  From the initrd generators I was aware of at the time, only dracut has an exitrd feature. Which means the system drops back into the initrd at shutdown time. It then (hopefully)...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>dracut allegedly according to the following configuration file uses zstd by default. I wonder why ours is uncompressed by default.</p>
<aside class="onebox githubblob" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/coreos/fedora-coreos-config/blob/stable/overlay.d/05core/usr/lib/dracut/dracut.conf.d/60-coreos-zstd.conf">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/coreos/fedora-coreos-config/blob/stable/overlay.d/05core/usr/lib/dracut/dracut.conf.d/60-coreos-zstd.conf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/coreos/fedora-coreos-config</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <h4><a href="https://github.com/coreos/fedora-coreos-config/blob/stable/overlay.d/05core/usr/lib/dracut/dracut.conf.d/60-coreos-zstd.conf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overlay.d/05core/usr/lib/dracut/dracut.conf.d/60-coreos-zstd.conf</a></h4>

<div class="git-blob-info">
  <a href="https://github.com/coreos/fedora-coreos-config/blob/stable/overlay.d/05core/usr/lib/dracut/dracut.conf.d/60-coreos-zstd.conf" rel="noopener"><code>stable</code></a>
</div>


      <pre><code class="lang-conf"># Compress initrd with zstd.  dracut defaults to -15, but we want the
# maximum reasonable compression, so override the command line to use
# dracut's defaults along with -19.
compress="zstd -19 -q -T0"
</code></pre>




  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 13:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2945</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I am not worried about xz. What happen to xz can happen to any project. After the xz backdoor has been spotted, there have been a lot eyes on xz. Therefore xz is now one of the projects that has received extensive code review.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 12:49:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2944</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Update errors after disabling user-sysmaint-split and vpn install</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Unrelated to user-sysmaint-split.</p>
<p>Highly unlikely related to user-sysmaint-split, which does not touch APT / sources list configurations / clock.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="farukar" data-post="1" data-topic="1134">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/f/898d66/48.png" class="avatar"> farukar:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>InRelease is not valid yet</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>See:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Operating_System_Software_and_Updates#InRelease_is_not_valid_yet_error">InRelease is not valid yet error</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/update-errors-after-disabling-user-sysmaint-split-and-vpn-install/1134#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 05:53:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2943</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="4" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It was done as change everything to zstd:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>OK, good to know.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="4" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Lol yeah thought about that from this perspective, but if we come to the linux kernel itself, these companies hands already there anyway (intel,nvidia…etc). So we go with the free software or not (and reliably secure) regardless the source from where, otherwise its a lost case.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Indeed, I made that comment mostly as a joke, thus the “:P”.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="4" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yeah guess who discovered xz backdoor? not a debian maintainer or so, but a microsoft engineer…</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The XZ backdoor never affected any stable release of Debian, because Debian doesn’t introduce new versions of software into older releases. So while the backdoor was not discovered by Debian, Debian did a very good job of defending the vast majority of their users from it even before it was known to be a thing.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="4" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So if there are no big issues with zstd + debian, i dont see it a bad choice imho.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I believe I pointed out a potential issue when mentioning overly large initramfs files causing boot failures on some machines. Is it a <em>big</em> issue? I guess that depends, but I know from experience that there are systems that, when faced with certain kernel drivers, will fail to boot with an initramfs compressed with a less efficient algorithm, and will succeed booting when that same initramfs is compressed with xz.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 23:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2942</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The initramfs use case is substantially different - size is<br>
more important than speed (to a point) because a too-big initramfs might<br>
fail to boot entirely.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It was done as change everything to zstd:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Fedora-43-Initrd-Zstd-Compress">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.phoronix.com/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="48" height="48">

      <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Fedora-43-Initrd-Zstd-Compress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">phoronix.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:554/185;"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2025&amp;image=initrd_zstd" class="thumbnail" width="554" height="185"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Fedora-43-Initrd-Zstd-Compress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fedora 43 Looks To Zstd-Compressed Initrd By Default For Space Savings &amp;...</a></h3>

  <p>A change proposal has been raised to compress the initrd by default using Zstd compression rather than XZ</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>(Arguably it’s in a good position to be backdoored by a<br>
nation-state too, but that depends on how much you trust Meta I guess :P)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Lol yeah thought about that from this perspective, but if we come to the linux kernel itself, these companies hands already there anyway (intel,nvidia…etc). So we go with the free software or not (and reliably secure) regardless the source from where, otherwise its a lost case.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1131">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Debian will be<br>
responsible for keeping it safe and maintained at that point</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah guess who discovered xz backdoor? not a debian maintainer or so, but a microsoft engineer…</p>
<p>So if there are no big issues with zstd + debian, i dont see it a bad choice imho.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 23:07:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2941</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It’s worth noting that Fedora switched to zstd specifically for RPM<br>
compression. The initramfs use case is substantially different - size is<br>
more important than speed (to a point) because a too-big initramfs might<br>
fail to boot entirely. This may become a real risk once we start using<br>
Dracut’s “sloppy hostonly” improvements, which include a lot more kernel<br>
modules and thus increase the size of the initramfs. The performance impact<br>
of zstd is benchmarked for initramfs compression above, and the impact is<br>
arguably negligible.</p>
<p>We shouldn’t let XZ’s reputation be tarnished after the xz-utils backdoor,<br>
in my opinion. The attack’s level of sophistication was high enough that I<br>
doubt most people would have handled things any better than the primary<br>
maintainer did, and after this experience I don’t believe he’ll make the<br>
same mistakes again. XZ’s source code is, to the best of our knowledge,<br>
clean currently, so I don’t believe the attack is a good reason to avoid it.</p>
<p>As for the Nebraska issue, that is a real problem. Zstd has the full force<br>
of Facebook backing it up, so it’s in a much better position to remain<br>
maintained. (Arguably it’s in a good position to be backdoored by a<br>
nation-state too, but that depends on how much you trust Meta I guess :P)<br>
That being said, as long as xz works reliably for initramfs compression<br>
when Debian 13 rolls around, I don’t see an issue - Debian will be<br>
responsible for keeping it safe and maintained at that point, and we can<br>
change our minds for a future release of Kicksecure. If we were using a<br>
rolling form of Debian, I’d probably pick zstd due to this concern, but<br>
since we’re using stable releases, I don’t see any substantial danger in<br>
using xz.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 18:10:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2940</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Fedora were using xz and done the comparison of xz VS zstd, the conclusion reached is that zstd overall will give better performance for the users:</p>
<p><a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Changes/Switch_RPMs_to_zstd_compression#Use_case:_Firefox_installation" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Changes/Switch_RPMs_to_zstd_compression#Use_case:_Firefox_installation</a></p>
<p>Another comparison by different project (not against xz but useful):</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://peazip.github.io/fast-compression-benchmark-brotli-zstandard.html#brotli_vs_zstd_compressor">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://peazip.github.io/fast-compression-benchmark-brotli-zstandard.html#brotli_vs_zstd_compressor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PeaZip file archiver utility, free RAR ZIP software</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://peazip.github.io/fast-compression-benchmark-brotli-zstandard.html#brotli_vs_zstd_compressor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fast compression: Brotli Zstandard comparative speed performances test</a></h3>

  <p>Fast compression benchmark. Comparison of Brotli, Zstandard formats performances, br vs zst compression and extraction speed, comparative test with 7Z LZMA2, RAR PPMd, ZIP Deflate algorithms.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Second issue of xz is the Nebraska issue (too much work for very important software for single or very few devs over long time):</p>
<aside class="onebox discoursetopic" data-onebox-src="https://discussion.fedoraproject.org/t/switch-to-zstd-from-xz/110789/16">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://us1.discourse-cdn.com/fedoraproject/optimized/2X/4/4a936c14d6cd5d29d6b7baf2511e406eeabed12c_2_32x32.png" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://discussion.fedoraproject.org/t/switch-to-zstd-from-xz/110789/16" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="04:00AM - 01 April 2024">Fedora Discussion – 1 Apr 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img src="https://us1.discourse-cdn.com/fedoraproject/original/2X/4/4701afb8ed62770e56cfd748606abe1c0d616b84.png" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="500" height="500">

<div class="title-wrapper">
  <h3><a href="https://discussion.fedoraproject.org/t/switch-to-zstd-from-xz/110789/16" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Switch to zstd from xz</a></h3>
  <div class="topic-category">
      <span class="badge-wrapper bullet">
        <span class="badge-category-bg" style="background-color: #51A2DA;"></span>
        <span class="badge-category clear-badge">
          <span class="category-name">Project Discussion</span>
        </span>
      </span>
    <div class="topic-header-extra">
      <div class="list-tags">
        <div class="discourse-tags">
          <svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-tag svg-icon svg-string"><use href="#tag"></use></svg>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">silverblue-team</span>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">workstation-wg</span>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <p>You won’t find much disagreement that zstd is a better algorithm, in most cases.  This is pretty well understood by this point.  Again though, it’s kind of beside the point.  Things that currently use XZ, cannot necessarily just switch out of the...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>The XZ maintainer experienced burnout and consequently scaled back some of the contribution reviews, which led to the XZ issue. GNOME discussed this issue as well:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/nautilus/-/issues/1936#note_2090670">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://gitlab.gnome.org/uploads/-/system/appearance/favicon/1/GnomeLogoVertical.svg.png" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/nautilus/-/issues/1936#note_2090670" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitLab</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="64" height="64" src="https://gitlab.gnome.org/uploads/-/system/project/avatar/1/bitmap.png" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar">

<h3><a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/nautilus/-/issues/1936#note_2090670" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Use zst compression instead of xz (#1936) · Issues · GNOME / Files · GitLab</a></h3>

  <p>Use cases ZStandard is a new file compression algorithm, the reference implementation of which, zstd, greatly outperforms every other compression method...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Bottom line is that zstd is the way to go.</p>
<p>Good thing that you reached to the conclusion second best choice.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 17:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2939</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Update errors after disabling user-sysmaint-split and vpn install</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@farukar]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>In order to hide the obvious use of TOR from my isp after install i disable the system split and install VPN.<br>
but after i try to upgrade nonroot it spits out the following errors:</p>
<p>E: Release file for tor+https://deb.debian.org/debian/dists/bookworm-updates/InRelease is not valid yet (invalid for another 3h 28min 51s). Updates for this repository will not be applied.<br>
E: Release file for tor+https://deb.debian.org/debian/dists/bookworm-backports/InRelease is not valid yet (invalid for another 3h 28min 51s). Updates for this repository will not be applied.<br>
E: Release file for tor+https://fasttrack.debian.net/debian-fasttrack/dists/bookworm-fasttrack/InRelease is not valid yet (invalid for another 6h 48min 3s). Updates for this repository will not be applied.<br>
E: Release file for tor+https://fasttrack.debian.net/debian-fasttrack/dists/bookworm-backports-staging/InRelease is not valid yet (invalid for another 6h 48min 2s). Updates for this repository will not be applied.<br>
zsh: exit 100   sudo apt update</p>
<p>when i do sudo apt update and upgrade it upgrades about 250mb of data witholding what i assume is the files that fail with the nonroot method</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/update-errors-after-disabling-user-sysmaint-split-and-vpn-install/1134#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:44:50 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2938</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to download onlder version of kicksecure?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Banebere" data-post="1" data-topic="1132">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/b/7ba0ec/48.png" class="avatar"> Banebere:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is there a way to download older versions of the software specifically the one before the system split.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>No.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Banebere" data-post="1" data-topic="1132">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/b/7ba0ec/48.png" class="avatar"> Banebere:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Also today i installed it in a new hard drive and the option to remove systemsplit is gone completely.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>1 topic = 1 forum topic please.<br>
If you wish to fix this, please open a new forum thread and post a screenshot.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-download-onlder-version-of-kicksecure/1132#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 11:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2936</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to download onlder version of kicksecure?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Banebere]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Is there a way to download older versions of the software specifically the one before the system split.</p>
<p>While i think its a great feature it is causing me too much pain in the ass.<br>
Also today i installed it in a new hard drive and the option to remove systemsplit is gone completely.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-download-onlder-version-of-kicksecure/1132#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 11:34:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2935</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Dracut compression research</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Patrick asked me to look into the compression options offered by Dracut for initramfs compression. This is the results of that research, written here since the results are a bit lengthy and require the ability to post images for sharing the charts I made.</p>
<p><strong>tl;dr: I think we should use xz compression. It’s acceptably fast, it compresses way better, and there doesn’t seem to be any compelling reason to avoid it.</strong></p>
<p>The initramfs has to be decompressed by the kernel on boot, so I only researched compression algorithms supported by the kernel in Debian Bookworm. (Trixie supports the exact same compression algorithms, so this research should apply to Trixie as well, assuming the compression utilities perform similarly in Trixie to how they perform in Bookworm, which I find likely given the age of these utilities.)</p>
<p>Bookworm’s kernel and Dracut both support the following compression algorithms:</p>
<ul>
<li>gzip (this is what we’re using now)</li>
<li>lz4</li>
<li>lzma</li>
<li>lzo</li>
<li>xz</li>
<li>zstd</li>
<li>cat (uncompressed, taken into consideration to provide a best-case scenario for time and a worst-case scenario for size)</li>
</ul>
<p>Dracut also supports bzip2, but Bookworm’s and Trixie’s kernels both did not appear to support that.</p>
<p>To determine which algorithm was most likely desirable, I benchmarked them against each other. The following testing methodology was used:</p>
<ul>
<li>Create a file, <code>/etc/dracut.conf.d/99-compress.conf</code> to set the compression algorithm in.</li>
<li>For each compression algorithm, change <code>99-compress.conf</code> to specify the desired algorithm, then run <code>time sudo dracut --force</code> three times.</li>
<li>Record the output of <code>time</code> after each dracut invocation.</li>
<li>Record the size of the output initramfs after each dracut invocation.</li>
</ul>
<p>In all instances, the file size of the output initramfs was identical (to within a kilobyte at least) across all three runs of Dracut when using a single compression algorithm, so I only recorded file size once per algorithm. All tests were run in a KVM/QEMU virtual machine with 4 virtual CPUs, 4 GB RAM, and all host CPU features passed through to the guest (<code>-cpu host</code>). The host system has an i9-14900HX processor. The raw results of the benchmarks are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>gzip
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.06s user 0.10s system 1% cpu 12.240 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 10.907 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 10.912 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>39724K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lz4
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.02s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 7.476 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.02s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 7.408 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 7.541 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>48064K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lzma
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.09s user 0.07s system 0% cpu 46.595 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 45.677 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.02s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 45.339 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>26292K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>lzop
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.09s user 0.08s system 0% cpu 38.810 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.02s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 37.862 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 37.837 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>44880K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>xz
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.09s user 0.08s system 1% cpu 11.655 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.01s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 10.542 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.02s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 10.571 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>28288K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>zstd
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.10s user 0.07s system 1% cpu 8.676 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.08s user 0.09s system 2% cpu 7.680 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.01s system 0% cpu 7.404 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>33248K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>cat (no compression, baseline)
<ul>
<li>run 1: <code>0.09s user 0.08s system 3% cpu 5.279 total</code></li>
<li>run 2: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 4.189 total</code></li>
<li>run 3: <code>0.01s user 0.02s system 0% cpu 4.252 total</code></li>
<li>file size: <code>136088K</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I did not benchmark boot speed with each of the different algorithms used, although I did verify that the virtual machine booted with an initramfs made with each algorithm. The boot speed seemed pretty much the same to me with each algorithm, and would have been difficult to measure in an objective, reliable fashion. I will note, I may have noticed a very slight speedup during boot with the zstd algorithm.</p>
<p>The following two graphs are provided to visualize the data above (created using LibreOffice):</p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/e92324d818d85c5e818003116c0999d6539ad7a6.png" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/e92324d818d85c5e818003116c0999d6539ad7a6" title="initramfs-gen-speed"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/e92324d818d85c5e818003116c0999d6539ad7a6.png" alt="initramfs-gen-speed" data-base62-sha1="xgqxRhWowoHkhwQKDySGIr6PCzI" width="605" height="340"></a></div><p></p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/2bd2414d9be6f209da5f48a7de40331332b64632.png" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/2bd2414d9be6f209da5f48a7de40331332b64632" title="initramfs-gen-efficiency"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/2bd2414d9be6f209da5f48a7de40331332b64632.png" alt="initramfs-gen-efficiency" data-base62-sha1="6fF02CNFpWuQxjjDkTxl0imYZz4" width="605" height="340"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Takeaways from the above data:</p>
<ul>
<li>From a size standpoint, lzma performed the best, lz4 performed the worst.</li>
<li>From a speed standpoint, zstd and lz4 are about tied for best speed, while lzma is the worst for speed.</li>
<li>lzo/lzop is certainly a bad choice - it approaches lzma in slowness while also making a file larger than gzip and almost as large as lz4. It’s the worst of all worlds combined.</li>
<li>xz is probably the most compelling as far as a balance between good speed and good compression - it’s almost as good as lzma as far as size, while being just a hair faster than gzip.</li>
<li>zstd is a bit of an improvement over gzip in size, while also being very very fast.</li>
</ul>
<p>I am of the opinion that xz is the best choice here based on this data, as our existing compression speed has been acceptable and shaving off 2-3 seconds per initramfs generation doesn’t seem that compelling except perhaps when doing ARM builds of Kicksecure on x86_64 hardware.</p>
<p>It is worth noting, people who know much more about compression tools under the hood than I do have complaints about design flaws in xz, which are documented <a href="https://www.nongnu.org/lzip/xz_inadequate.html" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">here</a>. I do not believe the issues mentioned in this article are of concern for the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>The article primarily relates to xz’s suitability for long-term archival. Kernel initramfs files aren’t really something where “long-term archival” is a concern.</li>
<li>Most of the article focuses on xz’s lack of resiliency in the face of partial archive corruption. But we don’t care about this at all, we assume the initramfs is bit-for-bit identical to when it was created, and indeed in the future we will likely be signing the initramfs as part of Verified Boot (which will mandate that the initramfs be bit-for-bit idential to when it was created).</li>
<li>Other parts of the article focus on compatibility issues with different versions of xz. This also is not a concern - as long as dracut produces an initramfs that the Linux kernel can read and boot with, things are compatible enough for us.</li>
<li>The rest of the article appears to focus on various design decisions in xz that could have been made better. None of that is relevant for us though, since whatever feature set Dracut is using in xz is good enough to give it a very acceptable compression speed while also providing the second-smallest file size of any of the compression algorithms documented here. Even if xz could be better than it is, right now it’s better than everything else except maybe zstd if you really care about speed.</li>
</ul>
<p>Someone else I saw did <a href="https://linuxreviews.org/Comparison_of_Compression_Algorithms" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">similar compression performance benchmarking</a> and concluded that <code>zstd</code> was the best general-purpose algorithm, though the data they present shows that parallel xz actually performed better than zstd’s best compression in both compression size and speed. One concerning thing this article does point out though is that xz can use a lot of RAM. For this reason, I tried generating a dracut initramfs using xz compression in a Kicksecure-CLI VirtualBox VM with only 512 MB RAM. Memory consumption during the initramfs generation rose to a maximum of 318M according to htop, and went down to 263M once the initramfs was generated, meaning that dracut and whatever tools it ran (including xz) used about 55M of memory during the generation process. Only about 1.97M of swap ended up used. This is much more than both gzip and zstd (which both only require about 5M of memory), but seems acceptable to me. 55M is not that much, especially given that <code>fwupd</code> is just sitting there eating 97M while doing basically nothing.</p>
<p>As a final note, I checked <a href="http://cve.org" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">cve.org</a> to see if security vulnerabilities were found in either the xz or zstd compressors in the Linux kernel. I found no vulnerabilities for either algorithm (using the search terms “linuz kernel xz” and “linux kernel zstd”).</p>
<p>In conclusion, I believe xz is the best compression method for us to use with dracut, due to its slightly better performance and much better compression compared to our current default, gzip. zstd is my second choice, and may be what we want to use if we have problems with xz’s speed or memory consumption.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/dracut-compression-research/1131#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:48:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2934</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Verified Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sCohCVvcp7E">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sCohCVvcp7E</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 11:26:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2928</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Verified Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.dasharo.com/projects/sovereign-boot-wizard/" class="inline-onebox">Sovereign Boot Provisioning Wizard - Dasharo Universe</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot/901#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 11:26:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2927</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure ISO Download Broken?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You mean formatted as a code box with copy button?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-iso-download-broken/1072#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 10:42:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2926</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Since Android is going for a virtualization based approach for some apps and since that’s more secure we might need to do the same.</p>
<p>Perhaps if running on a host operating system, we’ll use per application virtualization.</p>
<p>In case of nested virtualization (if we run already inside a VM), we’ll investigate that more. Provide a user configurable setting in that case perhaps. Or fallback to another solution (run without virtualization) because we’ll suggest to use multiple VMs.</p>
<p>We’ll need a separate ticket to investigate the security impact of nested virtualization. We’ll weigh it against running applications inside a VM without nesting.</p>
<p>That is, if even possible, such as slow performance making this infeasible.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_13</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 10:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2925</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="desi_fubu" data-post="9" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/d/da6949/48.png" class="avatar"> desi_fubu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yeah I like the idea of sysmaint and hope to see it progress, might want to look at adding an option in sysmaint panel next for setting a GRUB password.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That’s there already <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=12" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> If you click “Manage Passwords” on the system maintenance panel, a popup will appear that allows you to change your user password, bootloader password, or disk passphrase. (It looks like <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/System_Maintenance_Panel" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">System Maintenance Panel</a> doesn’t have that documented yet, that should probably be fixed.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:02:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2922</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Opening Firefox to look things up while booted into sysmaint mode could be a fatal move.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>You’re right, it could be fatal move since its the account with most privileges so to speak.<br>
Agreed its better to look up on another device or look up via user (then save file).</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>You may note that the sysmaint session has no “launch browser” button and no Start Menu - that’s specifically because we’re <em>trying</em> to keep people from launching Firefox in sysmaint mode if at all possible</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah and avoid general purpose use, and honestly this is what I did before sysmaint as I would only have one dedicated user for sudo privlages and only login to that user do install or update software of fix system wide issues etc.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>we try to make it harder to shoot yourself in the foot that way.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Really do appreciate this more then you know thanks.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most users who have a less strict threat model can probably afford to remove user-sysmaint-split.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yeah I like the idea of sysmaint and hope to see it progress, might want to look at adding an option in sysmaint panel next for setting a GRUB password.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2921</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>One possible argument in favor of the VM-based approach is that we could run “unsafe” apps in sysmaint sessions safely. We went to a great deal of effort to prevent people from launching Firefox in a sysmaint session because of the dangers it poses, but launching a virtual machine sandbox with Firefox in it would be much safer than standard or sandboxed Firefox. The inability to safely use a web browser in a sysmaint session <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/7">is causing some frustration</a>, and while we did see that coming and decided it was worth it, being able to remove that frustration would be nice.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:17:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2920</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure ISO Download Broken?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Like its formatted down below on the writing to USB section the terminal drop down.</p><aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/ISO#Terminal">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1751535025" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/ISO#Terminal" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc" title="12:46AM - 25 May 2025">Kicksecure – 25 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/ISO#Terminal" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Kicksecure Live ISO (via USB) and Installation</a></h3>

  <p>Kicksecure Installation Guide. This guide will help you download the ISO image, create your bootable media, and install Kicksecure on your computer.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-iso-download-broken/1072#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:16:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2919</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>USERMAINT? You mean sysmaint? Please edit.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes I meant SYSMAINT however I don’t see the edit button available here.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:13:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2918</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="desi_fubu" data-post="5" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/d/da6949/48.png" class="avatar"> desi_fubu:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yeah but since sysmaint is the only user that has sudo privileges its gonna be little annoying if a user is trying fix things and they need to look them up. Another example is looking how to install something lets say to install a .deb for software found online or build something from source online.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Well… you have a point, and you’re kind of proving my point at the same time. Opening Firefox to look things up while booted into sysmaint mode could be a fatal move. You may note that the sysmaint session has no “launch browser” button and no Start Menu - that’s specifically because we’re <em>trying</em> to keep people from launching Firefox in sysmaint mode if at all possible. This <em>does</em> make it harder to look things up, but there’s not any safe way to allow looking things up while in sysmaint mode. (What you could do instead is look up how to do things while in user mode, create plain text files with notes about what you intend to do in sysmaint mode, then reboot into sysmaint mode and do those things. You can access the files saved in your user account by running <code>sudo -i</code>, then <code>cd /home/user</code>.)</p>
<p>Obviously this is going to be severely annoying for a significant number of use cases. And as a developer, I freely admit to using sysmaint mode for things it isn’t designed to be used for (mostly building packages from a VM shared folder). My threat model is such that I can do that safely, but since we’re trying to cater to much stricter threat models, we try to make it harder to shoot yourself in the foot that way. Most users who have a less strict threat model can probably afford to remove user-sysmaint-split. (The only reason I don’t is because I have to develop the sysmaint session itself, so having it around is essential.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2917</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Enterprise Laptop style WiFi Switch causes Permanent freeze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="8" data-topic="1105">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>then move the cursor immediately after the <code>ro</code> kernel parameter.<br>
Then just press and hold the delete key until the rest of the line is erased (though don’t erase parameters you want to keep).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah I will try that here, and yeah it only appears to be Kicksecure specific.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enterprise-laptop-style-wifi-switch-causes-permanent-freeze/1105#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:12:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2916</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks. This drop in file could also be placeholder used to configure other apps in Kicksecure that rely on org</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2915</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Enterprise Laptop style WiFi Switch causes Permanent freeze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>If a Debian 12 live ISO doesn’t trigger it, then it’s very likely Kicksecure’s fault. Now the question is, what part of Kicksecure?</p>
<p>As a first step, can you try booting without any of the hardening kernel command line options passed? To do this, boot the laptop, then press the <kbd>E</kbd> key on the boot menu rather than Enter. Move your cursor to the line that starts with the word <code>linux</code>, then move the cursor immediately after the <code>ro</code> kernel parameter. (Note that if you have an encrypted installation, you’ll probably have a kernel parameter with the word <code>luks</code> somewhere in there, make sure to NOT delete that one.) Then just press and hold the delete key until the rest of the line is erased (though don’t erase parameters you want to keep). Once that’s done, press Ctrl+X to boot. This change will only apply to this boot, it isn’t persistent.</p>
<p>Once you’ve booted in that configuration, try the WiFi switch again. If it works, then we’ve narrowed it down to a kernel parameter, and we can start narrowing down which one.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enterprise-laptop-style-wifi-switch-causes-permanent-freeze/1105#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:05:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2914</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Yeah I just checked and the toggle system tray on Debian 12 Live Xfce is separate from the plugin. If you already have the plugin it will add a second power selector like in the case of Debian 12 Live Xfce (not kickscure).</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2913</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>it’s possible the OS isn’t detecting your system’s battery.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>On same system booted into Debian 12 Live Xfce the power manager plugin is there on the panel</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The sysmaint session is intentionally designed to be a bit annoying to use as a general-purpose session because using it as a general-purpose session is a security hazard.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah but since sysmaint is the only user that has sudo privileges its gonna be little annoying if a user is trying fix things and they need to look them up. Another example is looking how to install something lets say to install a .deb for software found online or build something from source online.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>It may be possible to pull in a good power manager applet from the Debian repos</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah as long as it doesn’t increase attack surface.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="3" data-topic="1108">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>f the permissions limitations in a user session and the functionality limitations in a sysmaint session are too limiting for your use case, you can revert back to “unrestricted admin mode” by booting into the <code>REMOVE user-sysmaint-split | enable unrestricted admin mode</code> boot option. This will get rid of the sysmaint session and bring back <code>sudo</code> access in normal user sessions. See <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Unrestricted Admin Mode</a> for details.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah I that I like sysmaint-split I just got confused for a second.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 23:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2912</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Enterprise Laptop style WiFi Switch causes Permanent freeze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="1105">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>you can try to install a newer kernel</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Do you think that is what it is or do you think its something related to pci firmware that manages the switch? I’m pretty sure its all managed by the same network controller.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enterprise-laptop-style-wifi-switch-causes-permanent-freeze/1105#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 22:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2911</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Enterprise Laptop style WiFi Switch causes Permanent freeze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>On Debian 12 Live Xfce the hardware WiFi switch works and doesn’t freeze. Same for Tails 6.17 the hardware WiFi switch works and no system freezes. Here are some outputs of commands across all three live systems bellow as I’m trying to narrow it down.</p>
<p>Debian 12.11.0 Live Xfce:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">user@debian:~$ lsusb |grep wireless
Bus 001 Device 007: ID 8087:07dc Intel Corp. Bluetooth wireless interface
user@debian:~$ lspci |grep Network
02:00.0 Network controller: Intel Corporation Wireless 7260 (rev 73)
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">user@debian:~$ sudo dmesg | grep -i "wifi"
[   17.347003] Intel(R) Wireless WiFi driver for Linux
[   17.347109] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: enabling device (0000 -&gt; 0002)
[   17.540002] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: firmware: direct-loading firmware iwlwifi-7260-17.ucode
[   17.540296] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: loaded firmware version 17.3216344376.0 7260-17.ucode op_mode iwlmvm
[   17.976223] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: Detected Intel(R) Dual Band Wireless AC 7260, REV=0x144
[   17.982616] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: reporting RF_KILL (radio disabled)
[   17.982637] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: RF_KILL bit toggled to disable radio.
[   18.013307] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: base HW address: 00:50:93:fb:8a:d2, OTP minor version: 0x0
[   18.061377] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0 wlp2s0: renamed from wlan0
[   70.945980] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: RF_KILL bit toggled to enable radio.
[   70.945985] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: reporting RF_KILL (radio enabled)
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">user@debian:~$ sudo dmesg | grep -i iwlwifi
[   17.366954] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: enabling device (0000 -&gt; 0002)
[   17.548906] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: firmware: direct-loading firmware iwlwifi-7260-17.ucode
[   17.549152] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: loaded firmware version 17.3216344376.0 7260-17.ucode op_mode iwlmvm
[   18.130315] iwlwifi 0000:02:00.0: Detected Intel(R) Dual Band Wireless AC 7260, REV=0x144
</code></pre>
<p>Kicksecure kernel version:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">[sysmaint ~]% sudo uname -r                      
6.1.0-34-amd64
[sysmaint ~]%
</code></pre>
<p>Debian 12.11.0 Live Xfce kernel version:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">user@debian:~$ uname -r
6.1.0-35-amd64
user@debian:~$ 
</code></pre>
<p>Tails 6.17 kernel version:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">amnesia@amnesia:~$ uname -r
6.1.0-37-amd64
amnesia@amnesia:~$
</code></pre> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enterprise-laptop-style-wifi-switch-causes-permanent-freeze/1105#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 22:40:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2910</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We can’t really not consider VirtualBox - it’s the primary supported platform for Kicksecure and Whonix, and the automated installer will install VirtualBox and a Kicksecure appliance by default.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>These were periodic time choices, meaning in 2013~ there wasnt much of choices for new project growing up, coming 2025 this is can be considered from the past.</p>
<p>Switching to VM per app, this idea can even merge whonix into kicksecure, how? because what is whonix doing is taking OS in VM connecting it through another VM, what can be done on VM per App is that X app in VM can use Y anonymization app/s in VM or even GW in VM.</p>
<p>To have these genius futuristic ideas coming to true without having virtualbox on the other hand = Be it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 22:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2908</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>My first thought looking at this is that user account isolation sounds neat but will probably be difficult to implement. Lots of file ownership changes would be required in order to allow the user to get files into and out of applications. AppArmor doesn’t have a sandboxing feature like SELinux appears to, though it does allow enforcing MAC. Seccomp is unsafe, Android can get away with it because Google can enforce rules about how Android apps are written and we can’t do that with Linux apps. It also sounds like Android is using some sort of chroot variant possibly (or some fancy feature of SELinux) to limit host file visibility, which would further complicate things.</p>
<p>I guess it would be better than nothing though. I’m not sure if it would be easier to implement than using a containerization engine, maybe it would be.</p>
<p>(I don’t like sandboxing approaches in general especially without seccomp, since any LPE vuln in the kernel will allow a sandbox escape, and there have been many LPE vulns in the kernel as I understand it. Virtualization would make that much, much harder.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 15:54:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2907</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Would “do it similar to how Android is doing it” be an option?</p>
<ul>
<li>Separate Linux user account name.</li>
<li>Separate folder.</li>
<li>Mandatory access control.</li>
<li>Secomp (optional, as feasible).</li>
</ul>
<p>Though, Android might be starting to use Android Virtualization Framework (AVF) for some apps.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 13:16:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2906</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>We can’t really not consider VirtualBox - it’s the primary supported platform for Kicksecure and Whonix, and the automated installer will install VirtualBox and a Kicksecure appliance by default. It’s <em>the</em> Kicksecure platform. This is probably part of why the restrictions are a dealbreaker because of nested virtualization concerns (it will technically work but it will be painfully slow in many circumstances).</p>
<p>Containers using the same system kernel won’t be a problem if the same OS is being used both on the host and in the container, which we can do. The security concerns of containerization are still there, but if we use a mature containerization platform like Incus rather than trying to roll our own (which is what I think we were doing with sandbox-app-launcher in the past), that might not be so bad.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 18:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2905</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>virtualized apps and VirtualBox at the same time is a real issue</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I dont see the need to use virtualbox if we have KVM support. Virtualbox on gnu/linux is bad idea even more on debian.</p>
<p>So i see that this can be avoided by not having virtualbox consideration.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe it would be possible to allow the applications containers to function as either containers or VMs</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I think better to avoid the possibility to downgrade the model and allow application/s to use containers instead of being virtualized, because containers using the same system kernel will lead to bad results IMO.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 18:21:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2904</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Vm-app-manager#Limitations" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Limitations</a> seem a deal-breaker.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah… containerization is so flimsy from what I’ve seen though that it seems like a dealbreaker to me. The limitations in nested virtualization scenarios aren’t really that bad since the user is already using virtual machines, they can use multiple VMs for isolation.</p>
<p>Being unable to use virtualized apps and VirtualBox at the same time is a real issue, and one that is very hard to avoid. Maybe it would be possible to allow the applications containers to function as either containers or VMs, so that one could use containerization when necessary, and virtualization when possible.</p>
<p>Incus considers container escape to be a security vulnerability: <a href="https://github.com/lxc/incus/security" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Security Overview · lxc/incus · GitHub</a> It’s an LXD fork (developed by the original LXD developers), and might be more workable (maybe even more secure?) than bwrap. I believe it’s present in Debian Trixie.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2903</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1120" data-full="true">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Created a wiki page with some ideas: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Vm-app-manager">vm-app-manager - Virtualization-powered application sandbox</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Check spectrum design:</p>
<p><a href="https://spectrum-os.org/design.html" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://spectrum-os.org/design.html</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 11:10:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2899</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>InRelease is not valid yet (invalid for another 4h 25min 51s)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Fix clock on the host operating system by manually setting it.</p>
<p>Then set the hardware clock based on the software clock.</p>
<pre><code>sudo hwclock --systohc
</code></pre>
<p>That should help having a correct time after reboot.</p>
<p>If that does not work, it could be unspecific to Kicksecure and be hardware issue. Often a broken BIOS battery.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/inrelease-is-not-valid-yet-invalid-for-another-4h-25min-51s/1113#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2898</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Separate (some) user applications from the operating system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Flatpak is also messy for other reasons. Unfortunately, not high quality packaging with the same standards and quality control as Debian. See:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Install_Software#Flatpak">Flatpak</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Some potential overlap:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sandbox-app-launcher">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1751448625" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sandbox-app-launcher" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="05:43PM - 22 November 2024">Kicksecure – 22 Nov 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/360;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/6/60/Sandboxing123123.png?version=3cfd8ad0add8394094af458025316228" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="360"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sandbox-app-launcher" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sandbox-app-launcher - Sandboxed Application Launcher</a></h3>

  <p>sandbox-app-launcher is an application launcher that starts each app inside its own restrictive sandbox. It runs each app as its own user, in a bubblewrap sandbox and confined by AppArmor.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox discoursetopic" data-onebox-src="https://forums.whonix.org/t/system-wide-sandboxing-framework-sandbox-app-launcher/9008">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/3/37fe81e592143b0c01c9656c44069b4bfdd3990e_2_32x32.ico" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/system-wide-sandboxing-framework-sandbox-app-launcher/9008" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="09:45PM - 26 February 2020">Whonix Forum – 26 Feb 20</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/255;"><img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/original/2X/5/5ac973ff4302e69269667e09e67d850c0b628c7a.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="255"></div>

<div class="title-wrapper">
  <h3><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/system-wide-sandboxing-framework-sandbox-app-launcher/9008" target="_blank" rel="noopener">System-wide sandboxing framework - sandbox-app-launcher</a></h3>
  <div class="topic-category">
      <span class="badge-wrapper bullet">
        <span class="badge-category-bg" style="background-color: #25AAE2;"></span>
        <span class="badge-category clear-badge">
          <span class="category-name">Development</span>
        </span>
      </span>
    <div class="topic-header-extra">
      <div class="list-tags">
        <div class="discourse-tags">
          <svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-tag svg-icon svg-string"><use href="#tag"></use></svg>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">status_open_issue_todo</span>
            <span class="discourse-tag simple">component_security</span>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <p>We’re currently working on a full system apparmor policy to confine all userspace processes but this has 2 issues:    It doesn’t use more restrictive profiles for user applications. A PDF viewer shouldn’t have the same profile as init.    It can’t...</p>

  <p>
    <span class="label1">Reading time: 84 mins 🕑</span>
      <span class="label2">Likes: 349 ❤</span>
  </p>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Perhaps sandbox-app-launcher is promising?</p>
<p>It wouldn’t fully separate core system packages from user applications. Debian packaging maintainer scripts would still be trusted. During package installation, malicious or vulnerable Debian packaging maintainer could compromise the system. There are no history precedents in <a href="http://packages.debian.org">packages.debian.org</a> as far I am aware, but still something worth mitigating.</p>
<p>Perhaps sandbox-app-launcher, if worthwhile, could install packages inside a per-application system chroot?</p>
<hr>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1120">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>vm-app-manager - Virtualization-powered application sandbox</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Vm-app-manager#Limitations">Limitations</a> seem a deal-breaker.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/separate-some-user-applications-from-the-operating-system/1120#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:44:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-2897</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
