<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You’ll have to give more specific steps for how to reproduce this. I’ve just attempted to reproduce the issue using Debian 12 + KDE Plasma, on a UEFI-based virt-manager machine. The exact steps taken are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Create a new virtual machine, specify that a Debian 12.7.0 netinst ISO should be used</li>
<li>Set RAM to 4 GB, disk space to 20 GB</li>
<li>Check “Customize configuration before installing” on the final screen of the VM creation wizard</li>
<li>Set firmware to UEFI (specifically <code>OVMF_CODE_4M.fd</code>)</li>
<li>Begin installation</li>
<li>Configure as follows:
<ul>
<li>Full Name: <code>User</code></li>
<li>Username: <code>user</code></li>
<li>Disk configuration:
<ul>
<li>Partition 1: EFI System Partition, 300 MB</li>
<li>Partition 2: ext4 mounted at <code>/</code>, use all remaining disk space</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Desktop environment: KDE Plasma</li>
<li>Timezone and locale settings set appropriately</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Once installation is complete, reboot</li>
<li>Carefully follow instructions at <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Install Kicksecure inside Debian</a> to morph the distribution into Kicksecure, some notes as to how I followed the instructions:
<ul>
<li>When given the option of using extrepo or manual configuration for initially adding the Kicksecure repository, I chose manual configuration.</li>
<li>Signing key was downloaded using TLS.</li>
<li>“Clearnet Rep.” settings were used for manually configuring the Kicksecure repo.</li>
<li>The Kicksecure metapackage I installed was <code>kicksecure-cli-host</code>, to avoid pulling in XFCE</li>
<li>Before following post-installation steps, I rebooted, tested login via SDDM with both Plasma X11 and Plasma Wayland sessions, confirmed it worked, and confirmed <code>security-misc</code> was installed using <code>dpkg-query -s security-misc</code> (it came back as <code>install ok installed</code>)</li>
<li>In the post-installation steps, I used <code>sudo rm /etc/apt/sources.list</code> rather than <code>sudo mv /etc/apt/sources.list ~/</code> for getting rid of the original sources.list file, it contained nothing important</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With this setup, Kicksecure is installed, <code>security-misc</code> is installed, and SDDM login works just fine, both with Wayland and X11 options. <s>I did not test sleep since this is a virtual machine and getting a virt-manager VM out of sleep can be <em>really hard</em>, but I would expect it to work.</s> EDIT: Just tested sleep too, works without issues, even with <code>security-misc</code> installed.</p>
<p>Some things about your configuration that you may want to double-check that may be the source of some of the issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>Did you install <code>kicksecure-cli-host</code> or <code>kicksecure-xfce-host</code>? Doing the latter on a machine with another desktop environment already will end up installing XFCE on the machine, which could conflict with your existing desktop environment in interesting ways.</li>
<li>Is your user account named <code>user</code>? There are some subsystems in Kicksecure that only allow an account named <code>user</code> to take certain actions. It’s possible (though unlikely) that the inability to take those actions with another account could be causing the issue.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve not yet tested with the Cinnamon desktop, or with Debian derivatives such as Sparky or Mint.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_13</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 23:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1698</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think I like the idea, especially in combination with disabling “easy” recovery mode and the Dracut recovery console. I think the only thing I’d really like to add to all of the above is that we document how to make the Dracut recovery console available again. I’ve used it for multiple debugging sessions that would have been rendered impossible or close to impossible without it. Let’s go with requiring the password on every boot since that provides substantial benefits over just locking out the configuration options.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="8" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>GRUB bootloader password to prevent all boot menu entries could be considered more secure than BIOS power-on password, because it’s not a “hardware magic feature” but instead a software feature implemented in Freedom Software, GRUB.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We should be careful with calling it more secure IMO - the bootloader password may be harder to bypass, but the BIOS password is necessary to complicate attacks that involve booting from an external USB drive. They both have their pros and cons, and ideally should be used together.</p>
<p>Also, we should consider how whatever tooling we make for setting this password interacts with FDE. A user with high security requirements might use BIOS password, bootloader password, FDE passphrase, and a user account password, preferably all different. Most users with moderate security requirements will get away with just FDE though, and those with lower requirements can use a BIOS + bootloader password and avoid the overhead and potential data loss risk of FDE. Do we want our tool to tell the user “You’re using FDE, you probably don’t need a bootloader password”? If so, should we make some brief in-tool documentation that explains the threat models each configuration might be used to defend against?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 23:16:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1697</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>System freezes on startup after entering login and password</p>
<p>polkit-agent-helper-1[4010]: pam_exec(polkit-1:auth): usr/libexec/security-misc/pam_faillock_not_if_x failed: exit code 1<br>
pam_wheel(polkit-1:auth): Ignoring access request ‘user’ for ‘user’</p>
<p>sddm [1940] authentication information: "usr/libexec/security-misc/pam-info: WARNING: 1 failed login attempt<br>
sddm [1940] authentication information: “Login will be blocked after 50 attempts”<br>
sddm-helper-[4089]: pam_exec(sddm:auth): usr/libexec/security-misc/pam_faillocl_not_if_x failed: exit code 1<br>
sddm[1940]: Existing authentication ongoing, aborting</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 13:22:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1696</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>kernel: Low-power S0 idle used by default for system suspend<br>
kernel: nvme 0000:04:00.0: platform quirk: setting simple suspend<br>
kded5[2685]: kscreen.kded: PowerDevil SuspendSession action not available!<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[4816]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)<br>
kernel: printk: Suspending console(s) (use no_console_suspend to debug)<br>
kernel:  amdgpu_device_suspend+0x53/0x150 [amdgpu]<br>
kernel:  pci_pm_suspend+0x78/0x170<br>
kernel:  __device_suspend+0xf1/0x470<br>
kernel:  async_suspend+0x1a/0x80<br>
kernel: queueing ieee80211 work while going to suspend<br>
kernel: amd_pmc AMDI0009:00: Last suspend didn’t reach deepest state<br>
kernel: PM: suspend exit<br>
systemd[1]: systemd-suspend.service: Deactivated successfully.<br>
systemd[1]: Finished systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Reached target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Stopped target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[8743]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)<br>
kernel: printk: Suspending console(s) (use no_console_suspend to debug)<br>
kernel:  amdgpu_device_suspend+0x53/0x150 [amdgpu]<br>
kernel:  pci_pm_suspend+0x78/0x170<br>
kernel:  __device_suspend+0xf1/0x470<br>
kernel:  async_suspend+0x1a/0x80<br>
kernel: amd_pmc AMDI0009:00: Last suspend didn’t reach deepest state<br>
kernel: PM: suspend exit<br>
systemd[1]: systemd-suspend.service: Deactivated successfully.<br>
systemd[1]: Finished systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Reached target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Stopped target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[11869]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)</p>
<p>my friend’s journal. he has the most interesting situation in debian kde plasma - system does not want to go into sleep mode, desktop reboots only. then system started sleep mode and hung. He said he didnot notice any other errors in journal. but sleep mode error goes away immediately if you delete security-misc and reboot</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 13:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1694</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>There are many different options.</p>
<ul>
<li>F) BIOS power-on password</li>
<li>G) BIOS administrator password</li>
</ul>
<p>These can be different passwords. Administrator password can usually clear/change power-on password and is also allowed to boot.</p>
<p>In this discussion, I was revering to <code>F) BIOS power-on password</code>, a password that is required for every boot.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If the BIOS password prevents booting the machine too, then yes, it does do all of that already.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This was my assumption.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But in that situation a bootloader password isn’t all that useful, except as defense-in-depth against a relatively unskilled adversary. (Granted, most adversaries most of our users encounter will be relatively unskilled, and I can definitely imagine someone who can figure out a BIOS password reset via an article from the Internet but who can’t figure out how to get past a bootloader password.)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right. The the protection provided by the BIOS power-on password isn’t that great. It’s a “hardware magic feature”. Some BIOS can be reset with:</p>
<ul>
<li>recovery code provided by websites, and</li>
<li>removal of CMOS battery,</li>
<li>motherboard BIOS reset jumper.</li>
</ul>
<p>There might be some BIOS resistant to that, designed to not easily being reset, but that is dependent on the hardware producer and may be dependent on the BIOS settings.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The bootloader password is still valuable though, even against a non-technical attacker, if the passwords are being used to prevent bootup entirely.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>GRUB bootloader password to prevent all boot menu entries could be considered more secure than BIOS power-on password, because it’s not a “hardware magic feature” but instead a software feature implemented in Freedom Software, GRUB.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Obviously at this point an attacker with slightly more skill would insert a live USB into the victim machine and boot from that, but there are plenty of attackers who lack that skill, especially in domestic abuse situations, so this still seems valuable to me, even if the benefits are limited at best.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 11:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1692</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think I see where I’m misunderstanding - I’m thinking of using BIOS and bootloader passwords specifically for preventing access to advanced configuration settings, i.e. the system can be <em>booted</em> without either password, but dropping to a GRUB shell or booting from an external drive using the BIOS should require one of the system passwords. In this context the passwords are only useful for preventing unauthorized root access and denying the ability to tamper with the system’s storage without removing the internal drive. Thus ability to gain root access on an unencrypted system has been the threat I’ve been considering most strongly. I think you’re thinking about these passwords being used to prevent even bootup, such that the system is essentially bricked unless you possess both BIOS and bootloader passwords. This way the passwords are used not just to prevent unauthorized root, but as a form of authentication to even use the system. We should decide on which one we’re discussing so that we’re both talking about the same thing.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Doesn’t a BIOS password alone already prevent all of that and requires taking out the drive or some other physical attack?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If the BIOS password only prevents getting into BIOS options, no, it does not. One simply has to drop to a GRUB console (trivially doable on many EFI systems by repeatedly pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> during bootup) and they can then boot any arbitrary OS by hand, including one provided on an external USB drive. Similarly, if you have a bootloader password but not BIOS password, you can trivially bypass it by booting from an external drive using the BIOS’s boot functionality. Only password-protecting both seriously complicates attacks that involve booting from an external drive.</p>
<p>If the BIOS password prevents booting the machine too, then yes, it does do all of that already. But in that situation a bootloader password isn’t all that useful, except as defense-in-depth against a relatively unskilled adversary. (Granted, most adversaries most of our users encounter will be relatively unskilled, and I can definitely imagine someone who can figure out a BIOS password reset via an article from the Internet but who can’t figure out how to get past a bootloader password.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Then surely the question will come up “in which cases it does not suffice?” The answer is most likely, in complex cases which are not applicable to the reader, because if these were applicable, the question would not come up. One case that can be constructed is some sort of corporate setup.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I think this is applicable to everyday users too though, whether you’re requiring passwords for bootup or for config access. Depending on the difficulty of opening a device, being forced to take the drive out of the machine to modify it is a very significant hurdle that an attacker may not have the opportunity to carry out (i.e. someone who gains physical access to a machine but only for a very short period of time, and who has to leave the machine more-or-less intact once their attack is complete, this is basically the classic evil maid scenario). Some machines even have soldered internal storage, especially cheap, lightweight devices like “HP Stream” and “onn.” machines - this makes this class of attack nearly impossible without access to advanced, expensive equipment for desoldering the storage chips and resoldering them onto something that allows reading and writing them.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A BIOS password alone will stop most non-technical attackers. More technical attackers who steal the hard drive would be stopped by FDE. That’s why BIOS password + FDE always seemed to be as the most important passwords.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The bootloader password is still valuable though, even against a non-technical attacker, if the passwords are being used to prevent bootup entirely. Many machines have a manufacturer-provided backdoor for resetting BIOS passwords, and tools for exploiting these backdoors are publicly available on the open Internet (<a href="https://bios-pw.org/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://bios-pw.org/</a> is a good example). For machines such as this, a non-technical attacker can probably bypass the BIOS password easily enough, but then they have the bootloader password to contend with. Obviously at this point an attacker with slightly more skill would insert a live USB into the victim machine and boot from that, but there are plenty of attackers who lack that skill, especially in domestic abuse situations, so this still seems valuable to me, even if the benefits are limited at best.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But a reboot will go through BIOS or are you referring to kexec? (I don’t know if GRUB can be load somehow using kexec.)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I meant a reboot that goes through BIOS. Assuming the system is not password-protected, you can easily gain a root shell on Kicksecure without the root or user passwords by following <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Recovery_Mode" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Recovery - Kicksecure</a>. An FDE password prevents this though.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In conclusion, the bootloader password seems to only make sense in niche cases.</p>
<ul>
<li>BIOS password bypass included in the threat model</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>corporate (alike) situations</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not necessarily.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>adversary taking out the hard drive and attempting to boot it in a different computer (circumventing BIOS password) (but then FDE would be much more important)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess sorta, though any attacker with the skill needed to move a drive between laptops probably also has the skill needed to boot a live USB to bypass the bootloader password. FDE would be much more important here, agreed.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1691</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Right. So similar to <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723/6" class="inline-onebox">Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password - #6 by Patrick</a> there could be a corporate setup use case.</p>
<p>A malicious employee could manage to corrupt some system files to then get a dracut recovery shell.</p>
<p>Or the complex VM related attack you’ve described.</p>
<p>We could set <code>rd.shell=0 rd.emergency=halt</code> in security-misc. (And then undo the setting in debug-misc, if not already the case.)</p>
<p>But we would only set it for <code>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</code> (default boot entry) or <code>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX</code> (all boot entries, including recovery boot entry)?</p>
<p>The kernel parameters <code>rd.shell=0 rd.emergency=halt</code> can be modified or unset from GRUB boot menu. But those who worry about that, can either set a BIOS password and/or a bootloader password, depending on their threat model.</p>
<p>Setting it for default (non-recovery) boot menu entries might makes sense. Because those who want to protect Linux recovery mode boot entries, need to set a GRUB root password anyhow.</p>
<p>Another related solution: <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/remove-linux-recovery-mode-boot-option-from-default-grub-boot-menu/727" class="inline-onebox">Remove Linux recovery mode boot option from default GRUB boot menu</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:13:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1690</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Remove Linux recovery mode boot option from default GRUB boot menu</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The default GRUB menu entry currently:</p>
<ul>
<li>sets: <code>loglevel=0 quiet</code></li>
</ul>
<p>The recovery mode GRUB menu entry</p>
<ul>
<li>does not set: <code>loglevel=0 quiet</code></li>
<li>sets <code>single</code></li>
</ul>
<p>That is not a massive difference.</p>
<p>Reasons for simplification:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724" class="inline-onebox">Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</a> (we could disable dracut recovery console at the same time)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/boot_modes" class="inline-onebox">Role-Based Boot Modes (user versus admin) for Enhanced Security</a> (the more options, the more confusing and recovery mode might not be very important)</li>
</ul>
<p>Instead, for debugging, single user mode, dracut rescue shell we could instead document how to accomplish that on the <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery" class="inline-onebox">Recovery - Kicksecure</a> wiki page using <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub#Kernel_Boot_Parameter_Change">Kernel Boot Parameter Change</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/remove-linux-recovery-mode-boot-option-from-default-grub-boot-menu/727#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1689</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>If these should be fixed, please report a bug.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:40:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1688</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>It might help to clarify under what situations a bootloader password provides a meaningful level of additional security.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>I am documenting that here: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Bootloader_Password">Bootloader Password</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>From my standpoint, you have to have at least a bootloader password, a root password, and a BIOS password for it to be useful at all (the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on, the bootloader password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting and entering recovery mode, and the BIOS password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting into an OS on an external drive).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doesn’t a BIOS password alone already prevent all of that and requires taking out the drive or some other physical attack?</p>
<p>Well, one could add the assumption that the adversary has a BIOS password bypass. Then the bootloader password might help. This might be an unrealistic assumption.</p>
<p>I think a BIOS password + FDE pre boot authentication password is sufficient “in most cases”.</p>
<p>Then surely the question will come up “in which cases it does not suffice?” The answer is most likely, in complex cases which are not applicable to the reader, because if these were applicable, the question would not come up. One case that can be constructed is some sort of corporate setup.</p>
<p>For example, an employee is given a BIOS password for booting from the internal hard drive, but not from other devices. Furthermore, the employee is allowed to boot using the standard/default option but prevented from booting the recovery boot option, because that password would be retained for system administrators only.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>(the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That reminds me of, quote <a href="https://xkcd.com/1200/" class="inline-onebox">xkcd: Authorization</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>If someone steals my laptop while I’m logged in, they can read my email, take my money, and impersonate me to my friends, but at least they can’t install drivers without my permission.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But more seriously…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>(the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess it depends on the threat model. Physical attacks while powered on are always a very high risk situation.</p>
<p>I however was thinking of BIOS password, bootloader password, FDE password, Linux user password, Linux root/sudo password in terms physical attacks while the machine is powered off.</p>
<p>A BIOS password alone will stop most non-technical attackers. More technical attackers who steal the hard drive would be stopped by FDE. That’s why BIOS password + FDE always seemed to be as the most important passwords.</p>
<p>If a physical attacker gets to run (passwordless) sudo, as mentioned in the xkcd, I might not mind much, as most sensitive data is accessible already when logged in as user (not root).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the bootloader password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But a reboot will go through BIOS or are you referring to kexec? (I don’t know if GRUB can be load somehow using kexec.)</p>
<p>Good, you could say not having a sudo password will allow a physical attacker to run kexec. But is that even still neeed? → xkcd</p>
<p>In that threat model that I am considering here now, physical attacks while powered are excluded. [1]</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If you have passwordless sudo, you can just <code>sudo -i</code> and then remove the bootloader password or change bootloader config as you see fit. Granted, FDE would protect against that.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right. I would exclude that form that threat model anyhow due to xkcd.</p>
<hr>
<p>In conclusion, the bootloader password seems to only make sense in niche cases.</p>
<ul>
<li>BIOS password bypass included in the threat model</li>
<li>corporate (alike) situations</li>
<li>adversary taking out the hard drive and attempting to boot it in a different computer (circumventing BIOS password) (but then FDE would be much more important)</li>
</ul>
<p>Please correct me if I am wrong. Happy to present the full threat model analysis in the wiki.</p>
<hr>
<p>[1] For physical attacks while powered on:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Screen_Lock">Screen Lock</a> (weak)</li>
<li><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/panic-button-panic-shutdown-buskill-the-usb-kill-cord-for-your-laptop/13755" class="inline-onebox">panic button / panic shutdown / BusKill - The USB kill cord for your laptop - Development - Whonix Forum</a> (ticket)</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1687</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I have not seen these problems in xfce. Only in Cinnamon and Kde Plasma. These problems are related to security-misc - removing package fixes these problems.<br>
I just shared observations for those who want to install a other desktop or another OS with Kicksecure</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:25:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1686</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="7" data-topic="46">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>These errors are in Debian,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If these error are happening on Debian without Kicksecure being involved, please report bugs against Debian.</p>
<p>If these error are happening on Kicksecure, please report bugs as per <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs" class="inline-onebox">Bug Reports, Software Development, and Feature Requests</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 13:53:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1685</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>There is a hang of LightDM and SDDM in Cinnamon and KDE Plasma after latest update security-misc - LightDM endlessly requires password, SDDM freezes after entering password. Use autologin! These errors are only at system startup - locking screen and changing user do not cause these errors then after desktop boots.<br>
And sleep mode hangs up on those desktops – use screen lock instead of sleep!<br>
These errors are in Debian, LMDE, MX and Sparky</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 08:12:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1684</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="724">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Not to be confused:</p>
<ul>
<li>A) dracut recovery shell [This topic]</li>
<li>B) Linux recovery mode (Single-User Mode) [somewhat related, but not the same]</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right, that’s what I thought. Then yeah, I think this change would make sense.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="724">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If protecting all GRUB bootloader boot menu entries, is there still a point in disabling dracut recovery shell?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess it depends. Theoretically an attacker could try to gain a root shell on a system by fooling some privileged component of the system into damaging boot files, then reboot and have a root shell. That would let them turn a data corruption vulnerability into a privilege escalation one. Blocking the Dracut recovery shell prevents that - the attacker can use the data corruption vuln to render the system unbootable, but can’t use that to then gain root access. If the system under attack was a physical system, this wouldn’t be that important to defend against since the user is probably using FDE which would prevent this sort of attack too, but if the system under attack if an unencrypted VM hosted on a server, then this would be a reasonable attack to fear and I can see this being a good mitigation for it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 23:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1683</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It might help to clarify under what situations a bootloader password provides a meaningful level of additional security. From my standpoint, you have to have at least a bootloader password, a root password, and a BIOS password for it to be useful at all (the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on, the bootloader password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting and entering recovery mode, and the BIOS password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting into an OS on an external drive). At that point you have to take the drive out of the victim computer in order to attack it easily.</p>
<p>With FDE, the bootloader password is only able to help prevent an attacker from easily modifying the contents of the disk blindly, and it still needs to be combined with a BIOS password to do that effectively.</p>
<p>I don’t see a whole lot of value in enabling a bootup password. That should be FDE’s job. On systems with soldered storage, a bootup password might complicate attacks, but FDE can do the same thing with all systems, even if those systems use non-soldered storage like a SATA or NVMe drive. I do see value in pairing a BIOS password with a bootloader password that prevents config modifications or boot menu access though, since the attacker now at least has to remove the storage drive from the victim system in order to tamper with the disk contents. The memory issue you bring up is helpful, but as long as the bootloader and admin passwords are the same, that should help avoid memory problems.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Having a bootloader password makes little sense if the user account isn’t password-protected and passwordless sudo is available.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t see the strong connection between those.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If you have passwordless sudo, you can just <code>sudo -i</code> and then remove the bootloader password or change bootloader config as you see fit. Granted, FDE would protect against that.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Bootloader password + FDE + user auto login might make sense?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If paired with a BIOS password, I think so.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>it probably makes sense for the bootloader and admin user passwords to be the same.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In theory nice, but when changing 1 password (such as the Linux user account admin password), coudln’t the GRUB bootloader (root) password get desync? That could be confusing.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah, that’s a decent point. If our app was the canonical “how to change your password” app in Kicksecure, that would help prevent that problem, but then there’s probably a feature in XFCE that will change only just the user password, and of course <code>passwd</code> exists. Not sure how to deal with that…</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 23:46:18 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1682</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Not to be confused:</p>
<ul>
<li>A) dracut recovery shell [This topic]</li>
<li>B) Linux recovery mode (Single-User Mode) [somewhat related, but not the same]</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>This topic overlaps very much with <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723" class="inline-onebox">Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</a>.</p>
<p>If protecting all GRUB bootloader boot menu entries, is there still a point in disabling dracut recovery shell?</p>
<p>Specifically, since there is a Linux recovery mode boot menu entry anyhow.</p>
<p>A theoretic argument could be made “if an attacker can bypass GRUB passwords”, but these minor <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks" class="inline-onebox">Protection against Physical Attacks</a> measures help against weak adversaries. An advanced adversary that could in theory bypass the bootloader password, would probably bother with neither GRUB passwords, dracut recovery shell nor Linux recovery mode but instead use <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Malicious_Hardware_Modifications">Malicious Hardware Modifications</a>, <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Side_Channel_Attacks">Side Channel Attacks</a> or similar.</p>
<p>related:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Recovery_Mode">Recovery Mode</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Root#Recovery_Mode">Root Login using Recovery Mode</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Root#Passwordless_Recovery_Mode_Security_Discussion">Passwordless Recovery Mode Security Discussion</a></li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 09:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1680</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732267825" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:13PM - 22 October 2024">Kicksecure – 22 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/436;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/1/1a/Usesearchengine.jpg?version=5e9554ee776455694f21fc054f14be65" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="436"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Utilize Search Engines, Documentation and AI</a></h3>

  <p>Avoid basic questions. Effective use of search engines and AI (Artificial Intelligence). Utilizing extensive Kicksecure documentation.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote" data-post="1" data-topic="46">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/h/8491ac/48.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46">Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/support/6"><span data-category-id="6" style="--category-badge-color: #0088CC; --category-badge-text-color: #FFFFFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="User support for the Kicksecure operating system."><span class="badge-category__name">Support</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    Hi! 
Anyone tried to install Kicksecure on top of Linux Mint Debian Edition? 
The recently released version of LMDE 5 is based on Debian 11 Bullseye. 
Is there a chance it will work properly?
  </blockquote>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 09:04:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1678</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Should the GRUB bootloader, if unavailable:</p>
<ul>
<li>A) prevent all boots?; or</li>
<li>B) prevent only editing GRUB configuration (kernel parameters) and some boot menu entries such as recovery mode?</li>
<li>C) the user should decide that (either by manually setting that up and/or using our maybe yet to be invented tool)?</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So perhaps the tool that does this should set user and bootloader passwords?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Just for everyone else reading (as you probably know that)… As per Linux / GRUB default - unspecific to Kicksecure - technically there are many different passwords available… At least…</p>
<ul>
<li>A) Linux user account <code>user</code> password</li>
<li>B) Linux user account <code>admin</code> password</li>
<li>C) Linux user account <code>root</code> password</li>
<li>D) GRUB bootloader <code>user</code> password</li>
<li>E) GRUB bootloader <code>root</code> password</li>
</ul>
<p>These are all independent, stored in different “places”.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>it probably makes sense for the bootloader and admin user passwords to be the same.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In theory nice, but when changing 1 password (such as the Linux user account admin password), coudln’t the GRUB bootloader (root) password get desync? That could be confusing.</p>
<p>In theory, always asking for a bootloader password might make most sense. This lowers the chance that the user will forget the password when needed. (If never asked for GRUB user password but then 1 year later being asked for GRUB root password could be an issue.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 08:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1677</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Having a bootloader password makes little sense if the user account isn’t password-protected and passwordless sudo is available.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t see the strong connection between those.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Having a bootloader password makes little sense if the user account isn’t password-protected and passwordless sudo is available.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Bootloader password + FDE + user auto login might make sense?</p>
<p>Because the bootloader password is a minor <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks" class="inline-onebox">Protection against Physical Attacks</a>.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>do we want this to be separate from the user password?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess an argument could be made why it should be different but then “100” different passwords is bad usability. Those who insist on different passwords for everything should be able to set them. But if we provide a tool to easily set up a GRUB password, using the same password as user <code>user</code> or <code>admin</code> (?) might make sense.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Lastly, for most users, it probably makes sense for the bootloader and admin user passwords to be the same.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right, probably best if same by default.</p>
<p>The difference is only something we should document.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 07:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1676</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It may be worth asking, do we want this to be separate from the user password? Having a bootloader password makes little sense if the user account isn’t password-protected and passwordless sudo is available. Similarly, for unencrypted systems, having a user password isn’t very helpful if the bootloader has no password set. Lastly, for most users, it probably makes sense for the bootloader and admin user passwords to be the same. So perhaps the tool that does this should set user and bootloader passwords?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 19:31:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1674</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>We should make sure this doesn’t break Recovery Mode, that’s the only thing wrong I can think of with that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 19:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1673</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>After <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723" class="inline-onebox">Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</a> has been implemented…</p>
<p>Should disable dracut recovery console?</p>
<p>Should set kernel parameters:</p>
<pre><code>rd.shell=0 rd.emergency=halt
</code></pre>
<p>As per <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/554853/how-can-i-secure-the-dracut-shell" class="inline-onebox">fedora - How can I secure the dracut shell? - Server Fault</a>?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 16:49:48 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1672</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It does not help too much. Documented already. But for completeness sake, first step might be documenting how to configure a <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Bootloader_Password">Bootloader Password</a>.</p>
<p>Second step might be development of a tool which simplifies adding a bootloader password.</p>
<p>There is <code>grub2-setpassword</code> but unavailable in Debian.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual/grub/html_node/Authentication-and-authorisation.html">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual/grub/html_node/Authentication-and-authorisation.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gnu.org</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual/grub/html_node/Authentication-and-authorisation.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GNU GRUB Manual 2.12: Authentication and authorisation</a></h3>

  <p>GNU GRUB Manual 2.12: Authentication and authorisation</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 16:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1671</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@LMDE]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>HI all,<br>
I realise morphing Linux Mint Debian edition to Kicksecure is unsupported, but I’m interested in learning from the experience of anyone who has done this. One thing I’m wondering is how updates will work after morphing. Will I continue to get updates from Linux Mint? Are there any big problems you’ve encountered?<br>
Thanks</p>
<p>Edit:<br>
Hi Patrick,<br>
Thanks for replying. Yes, I’m aware of those links/options. That’s why I specifically stated I know it’s unsupported. I was hoping for some feedback and discussion from other users, not support from the team.</p>
<p>If such discussions are not allowed here, can you direct me to somewhere they are allowed?</p>
<p>I’ve searched and there are very few discussions of Kicksecure + Linux Mint elsewhere on the web. I’m not surprised as it’s increasingly difficult to ask questions anywhere these days.</p>
<p>I’ve asked a similar question on the Linux Mint forums and they also closed the topic, saying it wasnt relevant to Mint and I should ask the question on Kicksecure forums. The rules for posting on Reddit forums are labyrinthine and arbitrary at the same time.</p>
<p>So, if such a discussion can’t be allowed here either, where are Kicksecure users supposed to learn from each other? Please consider reopening this topic or else consider adding a forum section where users are able to discuss things among themselves without expecting involvement from the Kicksecure team. This would be another valuable learning resource.<br>
Regards</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 16:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1670</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure installation: Cannot set timezone. link creation failed, target /usr/share/timezone; link name: /etc/localtime</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubpullrequest" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/pull/2400">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/pull/2400" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/calamares/calamares</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row" data-github-private-repo="false">



    <div class="github-icon-container" title="Pull Request">
      <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 12 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M11 11.28V5c-.03-.78-.34-1.47-.94-2.06C9.46 2.35 8.78 2.03 8 2H7V0L4 3l3 3V4h1c.27.02.48.11.69.31.21.2.3.42.31.69v6.28A1.993 1.993 0 0 0 10 15a1.993 1.993 0 0 0 1-3.72zm-1 2.92c-.66 0-1.2-.55-1.2-1.2 0-.65.55-1.2 1.2-1.2.65 0 1.2.55 1.2 1.2 0 .65-.55 1.2-1.2 1.2zM4 3c0-1.11-.89-2-2-2a1.993 1.993 0 0 0-1 3.72v6.56A1.993 1.993 0 0 0 2 15a1.993 1.993 0 0 0 1-3.72V4.72c.59-.34 1-.98 1-1.72zm-.8 10c0 .66-.55 1.2-1.2 1.2-.65 0-1.2-.55-1.2-1.2 0-.65.55-1.2 1.2-1.2.65 0 1.2.55 1.2 1.2zM2 4.2C1.34 4.2.8 3.65.8 3c0-.65.55-1.2 1.2-1.2.65 0 1.2.55 1.2 1.2 0 .65-.55 1.2-1.2 1.2z"></path></svg>
    </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">



      <h4>
        <a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/pull/2400" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Allow restricting the filesystem's usable in manual partitioning (wip)</a>
      </h4>

    <div class="branches">
      <code>calamares:calamares</code> ← <code>ArrayBolt3:arraybolt3/restrict-fs</code>
    </div>

      <div class="github-info">
        <div class="date">
          opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2024-11-21" data-time="08:23:07" data-timezone="UTC">08:23AM - 21 Nov 24 UTC</span>
        </div>

        <div class="user">
          <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
            <img alt="ArrayBolt3" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/104878738?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
            ArrayBolt3
          </a>
        </div>

        <div class="lines" title="1 commits changed 14 files with 424 additions and 18 deletions">
          <a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/pull/2400/files" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
            <span class="added">+424</span>
            <span class="removed">-18</span>
          </a>
        </div>
      </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">This is my first attempt at implementing https://github.com/calamares/calamares/<span class="show-more-container"><a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/pull/2400" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">issues/2397. I tried to follow the existing conventions when it came to how configuration was fetched, making a new class for the map of restricted filesystems for mountpoints and handling default configuration values in much the same way as other parts of the code handled them. I don't like the way I had to plumb PartitionCoreModule and Config objects into areas of the code that didn't used to use them, but it was the only way I could see to do the job and still be consistent.

There are some major shortcomings still left in the code:

* &lt;s&gt;For mountpoint-specific filesystem whitelists, I'm not taking into account that un-mountable filesystems should always be allowed, even though I document that this is taken into account. This **must** be fixed before this can be merged.&lt;/s&gt; Resolved.
* &lt;s&gt;It doesn't take into account the case when mountpoint `/a` can be filesystem X, mountpoint `/a/b` cannot be filesystem X, and the user chooses to only make a partition for mountpoint `/a` and leave `/a/b` on the same filesystem as `/a`. In that instance the user could set `/a` to be filesystem X, and thus `/a/b` would also be filesystem X, despite that being prohibited.&lt;/s&gt; Resolved, the UX isn't awesome but it does work.
* &lt;s&gt;No testing has been done yet, at all. I don't even know if Calamares will launch with this.&lt;/s&gt; Did some testing, it's working decent so far.

I'm not sure if this is the right approach to this, or if I should be approaching the problem in a fundamentally different way. I'm happy to scrap the patch and try again if this isn't the right way to do this.

EDIT: The code is mostly working now. It still needs a good test plan written and thoroughly tested before it's merge-ready, but it seems to work right, and is ready for review.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-installation-cannot-set-timezone-link-creation-failed-target-usr-share-timezone-link-name-etc-localtime/652#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 09:18:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1668</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Great resoning!</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="674">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I personally would rather leave it out of the exceptions for servers</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Alright, let’s do it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 09:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1667</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="674">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Therefore, someone who installs it, will actually need it.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not necessarily:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">[user ~]% apt-cache rdepends spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper
spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper
Reverse Depends:
  libspice-client-glib-2.0-8
[user ~]% apt-cache rdepends libspice-client-glib-2.0-8
libspice-client-glib-2.0-8
Reverse Depends:
  virt-viewer
  spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper
  vinagre
  spice-client-gtk
  gir1.2-spiceclientglib-2.0
  libspice-client-gtk-3.0-5
  libspice-client-glib-2.0-dev
  gnome-boxes
</code></pre>
<p>So in theory, a user who wants to run VMs on the server might end up installing virt-viewer, gnome-boxes, or similar, and end up pulling in the SPICE client library, which then in turn pulls in this obscure SUID executable for dealing with one portion of USB passthrough. For users who actually need USB passthrough, this is fine, but for other users, it could potentially be an issue.</p>
<p>This is really hypothetical though. Why would someone install gnome-boxes (a desktop application) on a server? If they want to run VMs on a server, they’d install libvirt on it, and then connect to libvirt using software like virt-manager from a client machine. So meh. I personally would rather leave it out of the exceptions for servers, but it’s not something I’m set on. If you’re happier with it shared, I’m fine with that.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 01:16:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1666</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I no longer know how important that exception for <code>spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> is at all. Cannot find how it ended up getting added.</p>
<p><code>spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> isn’t installed by default in Kicksecure (or Whonix). Not even inside VMs.</p>
<p>Therefore, someone who installs it, will actually need it.</p>
<p>The issue is also that the threat model of permission hardener isn’t well enough defined.</p>
<p><code>spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> isn’t installed by default and doesn’t install itself using <code>apt install spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> by accident either. If malware was able to run <code>apt install spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code>, then there would already be a root compromise and permission hardener couldn’t help anymore either.</p>
<p>From that perspective, that exception can stay shared for simplicity?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="674">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Finally. the binary is setuid. Obscure-but-insecure things are where a lot of vulnerabilities are found, like the recent CUPS RCE.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>That’s why permission hardener disables many historically used SUIDs that are nowadays no longer popular (at least not by Kicksecure (or Whonix) users).</p>
<p>Some examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>write SUID, wall SUID</li>
<li>passwd SUID (using it with sudo instead, multi-users desktops are not popular where this is required)</li>
<li>su (using sudo instead, maybe <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/replace-sudo-with-doas/17482" class="inline-onebox">Replace sudo with doas - Development - Whonix Forum</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>These are well suitable for permission hardener, since these are installed by default and hard (infeasible? / impossible?) to not have installed by default.</p>
<p>This is the main motivation for permission hardener. To disable SUIDs where it’s not strictly required for most users, yet having these binaries around is “mandatory”.</p>
<p>However, for packages such as <code>spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> maybe, the SUID functionality might be specifically wanted by the user?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 13:49:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1665</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hmm, I see a lot of your points here. I think the only one I disagree with is the SPICE whitelist point - the <code>spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper</code> being granted an exception from permission-hardener here is apparently only used when a host is passing through USB devices to a guest. (See <a href="https://packages.debian.org/sid/misc/spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Debian -- Details of package spice-client-glib-usb-acl-helper in sid</a>) I don’t foresee this happening frequently (if ever) on a server. In theory, an attacker could use USB passthrough to compromise a confidential VM should they gain access to the host (use USB-over-IP to connect a malicious USB device to a compromised server remotely, then pass it through to the target VM and exploit a driver within the VM to gain a foothold there). Finally. the binary is setuid. Obscure-but-insecure things are where a lot of vulnerabilities are found, like the recent CUPS RCE.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 01:14:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1664</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>After morphing, I can not start distrobox</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>sudo permission-hardener disable /usr/bin/crun*</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wildcards (“<code>*</code>”) are unsupported.</p>
<p>But anyhow.</p>
<p>I did <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/git#Search_the_Source_Code">Search the Source Code</a> and there is no mention of <code>crun</code>. So not a permission-hardener issue in this case.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="3" data-topic="688">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Error: crun: open executable: Operation not permitted: OCI permission denied</em></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I found this error message on search engines.</p>
<p>Dunno.</p>
<p>Consider this unsupported.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1731922224" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:07AM - 12 October 2024">Kicksecure – 12 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/426;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/0a/Unsupported.jpg?version=4c03a6d49994df75ba2ec2ce26d99988" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="426"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Undocumented, Untested or Unsupported Features</a></h3>

  <p>This feature is either undocumented, untested, or unsupported. Options: Become a Contributor / Apply Self Support First Policy / Purchase Support.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>As per:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1731922224" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:21AM - 25 October 2024">Kicksecure – 25 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:666/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/c/c6/Self-support.jpg?version=ff7bb4e369079801406f79a2ab8db191" class="thumbnail" width="666" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Definition of the Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/after-morphing-i-can-not-start-distrobox/688#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 16:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1663</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>After morphing, I can not start distrobox</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It helped. But now I have a new problem<br>
<em>Error: crun: open executable: Operation not permitted: OCI permission denied</em><br>
and this command does not work <em>sudo permission-hardener disable /usr/bin/crun</em></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/after-morphing-i-can-not-start-distrobox/688#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 14:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1662</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>This is now part of <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian" class="inline-onebox">Install Kicksecure inside Debian</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>8.</strong> Install console related packages.</p>
<p>This might also result in removal of <code>plymouth</code>, which is good, because it is <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unsupported">unsupported</a>. <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian#cite_note-8">[8]</a></p>
<p>sudo apt install console-data console-common kbd keyboard-configuration</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(related wiki template for wiki editors: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Template:Prerequisites" class="inline-onebox">Template:Prerequisites - Kicksecure</a>)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 14:23:18 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1661</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="3" data-topic="641">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><code>plymouth</code> <code>Conflicts:</code> <code>console-common</code>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I just wanted you to write about this problem on site in morphing section before <em>command sudo apt install --no-install-recommends kicksecure-xfce-host</em>. many see “error: plymouth Conflicts: console-common” and stop there. my friends had it. I have not yet met morphing without this conflict</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 07:26:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1660</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>After morphing, I can not start distrobox</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SUID_Disabler_and_Permission_Hardener" class="inline-onebox">SUID Disabler and Permission Hardener</a> could be the issue.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="1" data-topic="688">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>/usr/bin/newuidmap</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SUID_Disabler_and_Permission_Hardener#Re-enable_Specific_SUID_Binaries">Re-enable Specific SUID Binaries</a></p>
<pre><code>sudo permission-hardener disable /usr/bin/newuidmap
</code></pre> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/after-morphing-i-can-not-start-distrobox/688#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 20:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1659</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/partying_face.png?v=12" title=":partying_face:" class="emoji only-emoji" alt=":partying_face:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/white_check_mark.png?v=12" title=":white_check_mark:" class="emoji only-emoji" alt=":white_check_mark:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 19:42:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1658</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Kicksecure works well in LMDE, MX Linux and Sparky Linux. BUT security-misc conflicts with SDDM at system startup (SDDM may hang) - autologin solves this problem. This problem does not occur at logout and screen lock. I use kicksecure in KDE Plasma on Debian, MX and LMDE - I have not noticed any problems or errors for over a month</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 07:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1657</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Kicksecure works great without plymouth. I advise everyone to remove it. This conflict appears in classic Debian, in MX Linux, in Mint LMDE and Sparky Linux  - both in those installed via USB on host and in VM</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 07:48:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1656</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>After morphing, I can not start distrobox</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>After morphing, I can not start distrobox<br>
distrobox enter my-ubuntu<br>
WARN[0000] “/” is not a shared mount, this could cause issues or missing mounts with rootless containers<br>
ERRO[0000] running <code>/usr/bin/newuidmap 2660 0 1000 1 1 100000 65536</code>:<br>
Error: cannot set up namespace using “/usr/bin/newuidmap”: fork/exec /usr/bin/newuidmap: permission denied<br>
I couldnt change this error. Could you try to reproduce and write a solution to problem? Thanks</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/after-morphing-i-can-not-start-distrobox/688#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 18:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1623</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to stop writing my ISO&#39;s as Rock Ridge/Joliet</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So you must be an extremely valuable target.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>To expand on that…</p>
<p>Extremely valuable target either due to monetary richness or other factors of power such as public influence. Normal people are not being attacked with such extremely sophisticated malware.</p>
<p>So if this is a priority issue for your to resolve, if affordable, this is the best time ever to hire a professional IT support company, malware researcher. (No specific recommendations are being made.)</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I am certain, that in many places, you would get accused of trolling. But then again, <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First#Artificial_Intelligence">Artificial Intelligence</a> can help.</p>
<p>I’ve just posted your public forum post into the AI and added:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some commentators are accusing the user of trolling. What can be done to not get perceived as trolling?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is the result:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://chatgpt.com/share/673787b9-77b8-8000-9686-018bf86b8212">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://cdn.oaistatic.com/assets/favicon-32x32-p4ktpm1x.webp" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/673787b9-77b8-8000-9686-018bf86b8212" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chatgpt.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/388;"><img src="https://cdn.oaistatic.com/assets/chatgpt-share-og-u7j5uyao.webp" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/673787b9-77b8-8000-9686-018bf86b8212" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ChatGPT</a></h3>

  <p>A conversational AI system that listens, learns, and challenges</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>The technological points ChatGPT is making aren’t that great but the general advice on how to draft these kind of inquiries are helpful.</p>
<p>For communication in free, public support places (such as this forum), I suggest to report 1 very specific issue at a time only. See also:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs#Reporting_Guidelines">Reporting Guidelines</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs#Sample_Bug_Report">Sample Bug Report</a></li>
</ul>
<p>For example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Steps to reproduce the behavior	:</p>
<pre><code>man gnustep
</code></pre>
<p>Expected result:</p>
<p>My an page should have same content as on <a href="https://manpages.debian.org/bookworm/gnustep-common/GNUstep.7.en.html" class="inline-onebox">GNUstep(7) — gnustep-common — Debian bookworm — Debian Manpages</a>.</p>
<p>Actual result:</p>
<p>…</p>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-stop-writing-my-isos-as-rock-ridge-joliet/687#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 17:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1622</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to stop writing my ISO&#39;s as Rock Ridge/Joliet</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You might want to take a look at <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Malware_and_Firmware_Trojans#Valid_Compromise_Indicators_versus_Invalid_Compromise_Indicators" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Malware, Computer Viruses, Firmware Trojans and Antivirus Scanners</a>, malware as a general rule does not make itself obvious because that runs entirely against the point of making malware in the first place.</p>
<p>Where did you get that xorriso command from?</p>
<p>Bluetooth is intentionally enabled in Kicksecure, there are features that make it safer baked into the distro.</p>
<p>overlayfs is intentionally provided in Kicksecure, it is even used in the “live mode” feature.</p>
<p>FUSE is intentionally provided in Kicksecure, it’s necessary to run AppImages and the like and should be present on pretty much all distros.</p>
<p>NTFS-3g lets you access NTFS drives, which is another thing many distros enable and which is useful for many users.</p>
<p>You haven’t indicated what you think the manpages should look like, so I’m not sure what’s unusual there.</p>
<p>I think you understand what I’m getting at. So far none of what you’ve shown indicates compromise for sure. That’s not to say you definitely aren’t compromised (you can’t prove a negative), but there isn’t sufficient evidence of it here. If you are a high-profile target (most people aren’t), whoever’s targeting you probably isn’t foolish enough to make themselves this obvious. If you aren’t a high-profile target, it’s very unlikely that someone would rationally pour this much effort into attacking you.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-stop-writing-my-isos-as-rock-ridge-joliet/687#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 17:38:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1621</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to stop writing my ISO&#39;s as Rock Ridge/Joliet</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>This gets called anytime I download an ISO</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>xorriso -as mkisofs -R -r -J -joliet-long -l -cache-inodes -iso-level 3 --grub2-boot-info --grub2-mbr /usr/lib/grub/i386-pc/boot_hybrid.img -efi-boot-part --efi-boot-image -v -A “application_id” -p “preparer” -publisher “publisher” -V “cdlabel” --modification-date=20240XXXXXXXX -no-emul-boot -boot-load-size 4 -boot-info-table -b boot/grub/grub_eltorito -eltorito-alt-boot -e boot/grub/efi.img -no-emul-boot -isohybrid-gpt-basdat -isohybrid-apm-hfsplus -o /home/user/derivative-binary/17.2.3.7/Kicksecure-Xfce-17.2.3.7.iso /home/user/derivative-binary/Kicksecure-Xfce_iso-tmp</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Where, how do you see that this command gets executed anytime you download an ISO?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So, what I’m trying to get at as is, has anyone dealt with this before?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I highly doubt it.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is this a known thing that others are getting attacked with in the wild,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I highly doubt that too.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>the boot loader they force me to boot from contains a kernel for Windows, Mac, and Linux</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Sounds like the most sophisticated malware ever.</p>
<p>Even Stuxnet, Flame, Duqu, Operation Triangulation aren’t multi operating system capable.</p>
<p>Such highly sophisticated malware would usually attempt to stay stealth. The user wouldn’t notice it. This is elaborated in wiki chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Malware#Valid_Compromise_Indicators_versus_Invalid_Compromise_Indicators">Valid Compromise Indicators versus Invalid Compromise Indicators</a>.</p>
<p>This is because the development effort to create such malware is so expensive, that it’s not supposed to be detected. How expensive? My first guess is far excess in access of $ 100 K USD and several months or years of development work.</p>
<p>So you must be an extremely valuable target.</p>
<p>However, this case is a strange combination, because…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="z24" data-post="1" data-topic="687">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/z/ce7236/48.png" class="avatar"> z24:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>the man pages and python documentation are not standard, almost all of the binaries serve an alternate purpose than their name would lead you to believe, for example I can run ‘gpic FILENAME &gt; OUTPUT.txt’ and deobfuscate data hidden inside of files. There is a man page for GNUstep (if I recall correctly) that’s as long as novel and it goes into detail about how to write code in order to cause a buffer overflow in the kernel.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is impossible to happen by accident as a side-effect of the malware. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XZ_Utils_backdoor" class="inline-onebox">XZ Utils backdoor - Wikipedia</a> had side effects such as high CPU usage and longer SSH login times, but nothing even remotely similar to what you’re describing.</p>
<p>This can only happen if source code was specifically written to purposefully change the system behavior. Someone must have written that novel or at least copied it into the source code of malware or installed it later post system compromise.</p>
<p>So what would be happening here is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zersetzung" class="inline-onebox">Zersetzung - Wikipedia</a>. Because these effects are intentional and no malware developer can be as stupid as replacing a man page with a novel by mistake. This can only be intentional.</p>
<p>The Kicksecure project does not offer system / malware audits. For reasons why that is so, see wiki chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Malware#Malware_Audits">Malware Audits</a>.</p>
<p>I had an interesting chat with ChatGPT about this topic, which might be useful for inspiration on what you can do next.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://chatgpt.com/share/67378590-66a4-8000-b30d-b55247e40177">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://cdn.oaistatic.com/assets/favicon-32x32-p4ktpm1x.webp" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/67378590-66a4-8000-b30d-b55247e40177" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chatgpt.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/388;"><img src="https://cdn.oaistatic.com/assets/chatgpt-share-og-u7j5uyao.webp" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/67378590-66a4-8000-b30d-b55247e40177" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ChatGPT</a></h3>

  <p>A conversational AI system that listens, learns, and challenges</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-stop-writing-my-isos-as-rock-ridge-joliet/687#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 17:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1620</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How to stop writing my ISO&#39;s as Rock Ridge/Joliet</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@z24]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Edit: I may have included too much additional information, I tried to provide enough data so others that have experienced this or may experience it in the future are able to locate this thread through search engines and hopefully get a resolution the issue.</p>
<p>This gets called anytime I download an ISO and I can’t figure out how to make it stop. Its able to replace the freshly downloaded ISO with the Rock Ridge version instantaneously before I could even run a dd command or launch disk image writer to get the fresh ISO written to disk before it is modified.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>xorriso -as mkisofs -R -r -J -joliet-long -l -cache-inodes -iso-level 3 --grub2-boot-info --grub2-mbr /usr/lib/grub/i386-pc/boot_hybrid.img -efi-boot-part --efi-boot-image -v -A “application_id” -p “preparer” -publisher “publisher” -V “cdlabel” --modification-date=20240XXXXXXXX -no-emul-boot -boot-load-size 4 -boot-info-table -b boot/grub/grub_eltorito -eltorito-alt-boot -e boot/grub/efi.img -no-emul-boot -isohybrid-gpt-basdat -isohybrid-apm-hfsplus -o /home/user/derivative-binary/17.2.3.7/Kicksecure-Xfce-17.2.3.7.iso /home/user/derivative-binary/Kicksecure-Xfce_iso-tmp</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t think I’m on the real Kicksecure anymore. A lot of things that shouldn’t be enabled by default are enabled like the bluetooth.service, overlayfs, fuse, and ntfs3g are also enabled. My xdg-user-dirs is normally /home/user/.config I think, it has been changed to point to /usr/bin/share/, that way I load flatpaks from the wrong directory just like the flatpak escape 0day did.</p>
<p>The doocumentation (man pages for example) aren’t even the same and my grub menu shows that lines have been removed, there is a new line added that is a if fi statement to insert two more kernel modules named lzopio and xen (I think that’s the name of them, very close if not). It seems like the lower deck of the overlayfs  is hooking into upper deck with some malicious binaries and shared objects, deleting anything hooked into the upper deck causes a crash, the lower deck is all lib32 software running on a squashfs.img and its dependencies get mangled in with my own, I have to download SSH libs for apps that don’t require networking to function or other random packages that should not be dependencies. I also have to delete the boot order using efitbootmgr and modify my grub entry in order to actually boot into the system at the lower deck. Even figuring out how to boot into the lower deck of the system doesn’t solve the problem though unfortunately.</p>
<p>It’s not as simple as reformatting my USB drive and secure erasing my SSD then using a fresh ISO, it’s like the data doesn’t really get wiped from the USB even though it appears that way to software like gparted and gnome-disks reading the disk image. I have wiped it then brought it over to a remote location, away from my potentially infected machine and it still manages to write that same ISO with the overlayfs and Rock Ridge ISO.</p>
<p>So, what I’m trying to get at as is, has anyone dealt with this before? What can I do aside from considering my devices trashed? I’m strongly considering dumping this data publicly out of frustration but something doesn’t feel right about doing that, somebody certainly put a lot of time and effort into devoping and writing documentation for this system.</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the man pages and python documentation are not standard, almost all of the binaries serve an alternate purpose than their name would lead you to believe, for example I can run ‘gpic FILENAME &gt; OUTPUT.txt’ and deobfuscate data hidden inside of files. There is a man page for GNUstep (if I recall correctly) that’s as long as novel and it goes into detail about how to write code in order to cause a buffer overflow in the kernel. So sharing something like that publicly seems to me like I would be destroying the hard work of someone or some group of individuals who have put a lot of time into it. As much I hate what they did to me, I’m also in awe of their work and complexity of the system at the same time.</p>
<p>Is this a known thing that others are getting attacked with in the wild, is it more likely a targeted attack and not wide spread? Locally it seems to spread like a worm via usb and through the network, the boot loader they force me to boot from contains a kernel for Windows, Mac, and Linux (version 5.1, unsupported and out of date), so even switching operating systems does not solve the problem. I hope someone can provide a solution that doesn’t involve throwing my machine into the dump.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-to-stop-writing-my-isos-as-rock-ridge-joliet/687#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 14:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1619</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Enable and use zRAM instead for swap</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubcommit" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator/commit/528694be791b126da112cbf71276a1dacd9273f6">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator/commit/528694be791b126da112cbf71276a1dacd9273f6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Commit">
    <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M10.86 7c-.45-1.72-2-3-3.86-3-1.86 0-3.41 1.28-3.86 3H0v2h3.14c.45 1.72 2 3 3.86 3 1.86 0 3.41-1.28 3.86-3H14V7h-3.14zM7 10.2c-1.22 0-2.2-.98-2.2-2.2 0-1.22.98-2.2 2.2-2.2 1.22 0 2.2.98 2.2 2.2 0 1.22-.98 2.2-2.2 2.2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator/commit/528694be791b126da112cbf71276a1dacd9273f6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no longer consider hibernation by default</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        committed <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2024-11-15" data-time="11:16:30" data-timezone="UTC">11:16AM - 15 Nov 24 UTC</span>
      </div>

      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/adrelanos" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="adrelanos" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/1985040?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          adrelanos
        </a>
      </div>

      <div class="lines" title="changed 1 files with 4 additions and 1 deletions">
        <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator/commit/528694be791b126da112cbf71276a1dacd9273f6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <span class="added">+4</span>
          <span class="removed">-1</span>
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">to have a smaller default swap file by default

and because hibernation is not y<span class="show-more-container"><a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/swap-file-creator/commit/528694be791b126da112cbf71276a1dacd9273f6" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">et compatible with Secure Boot

https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enable-and-use-zram-instead-for-swap/654/8</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/enable-and-use-zram-instead-for-swap/654#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 11:18:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1617</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>KickSecure SMB setup</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SlowMoe" data-post="1" data-topic="684">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/slowmoe/48/104_2.png" class="avatar"> SlowMoe:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Now I have a GLinet Flint 2 router</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>GLinet runs on modified version on OpenWRT.<br>
I suggest you flash it with stock OpenWRT cause I personally dont trust GLinet’s firmware.</p>
<p>Also ask on the OpenWRT forum about this “SMB”.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-smb-setup/684#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 21:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1616</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Randomized hostname protocol</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Crawfish" data-post="7" data-topic="565">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/c/3e96dc/48.png" class="avatar"> Crawfish:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Using a Different MAC for SSH</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>SSH doesn’t send the devices MAC Address at most it might send the hostname but good info about using network namespaces that might be useful for something in Kicksecure.</p>
<p>As far as I understand the issue related to</p>
<blockquote>
<p>MAC randomization breaks root server and VirtualBox DHCP / IPv6PrivacyExtensions might be problematic</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I believe they are referring to Installing Kicksecure as the OS on VPS server.<br>
In this case I think Kicksecure should just NOT randomize Ethernet MAC addresses by commenting it out. Reason being most servers are wired in especially VPS, if you look at any server rack they aren’t going to be using wireless as that would create too much cross talk and you wouldn’t get optimized speeds.</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">#ethernet.cloned-mac-address=stable
</code></pre>
<p>Also like <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/crawfish">@Crawfish</a> said</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Crawfish" data-post="7" data-topic="565">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/c/3e96dc/48.png" class="avatar"> Crawfish:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><code>connection.stable-id=${CONNECTION}/${BOOT}</code></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This has to be set if you don’t want Network Manager to leak or revert back to permaddr cause Network Manger will.</p>
<p>Alternatively you could also set it to set a new mac everytime you reconnect in a session instead.</p>
<p><code>connection.stable-id=${CONNECTION}/${RANDOM}</code></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/randomized-hostname-protocol/565#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 21:28:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1615</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>KickSecure SMB setup</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Try <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs#Generic_Bug_Reproduction">Generic Bug Reproduction</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-smb-setup/684#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 20:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1614</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>ISO - Development</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1087470">live-build: Binary stage runs apt commands, breaking certain image build workflows</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/iso-development/371#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 20:57:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1613</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>No worries.</p>
<p>Fixed by git revert.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 20:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1612</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Splitting security-misc into shared, desktop, and server packages</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="674">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>[!] │ │ │ ├── panic-on-oops.service (shared) (useful on desktop and server, systemd config looks invalid with a conflict between WantedBy and After)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Fixed.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It turns out I was wrong here - the config <em>looked</em> invalid but actually was not. I had mistakenly thought that <code>WantedBy</code> required the wanted service to start before the wanting service. This was false, the <code>systemd.unit</code> manpage states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note that requirement dependencies do not influence the order in which services are started or stopped. This has to be configured independently with the <code>After=</code> or <code>Before=</code> options. If unit <code>foo.service</code> pulls in unit <code>bar.service</code> as configured with <code>Wants=</code> and no ordering is configured with <code>After=</code> or <code>Before=</code> , then both units will be started simultaneously and without any delay between them if <code>foo.service</code> is activated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So having a unit be both <code>WantedBy=multi-user.target</code> and <code>After=multi-user.target</code> is actually valid. Furthermore, removing the <code>After=multi-user.target</code> line has resulted in an error message on boot:</p>
<pre><code>[ SKIP ] Ordering cycle found, skipping panic-on-oops.service
</code></pre>
<p>Adding back <code>After=multi-user.target</code> to <code>/usr/lib/systemd/system/panic-on-oops.service</code> resolves the issue.</p>
<p>Sorry about the mix-up here.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/splitting-security-misc-into-shared-desktop-and-server-packages/674#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 03:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1611</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>KickSecure SMB setup</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SlowMoe]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think Kicksecure may have some security settings that prevent it from setting up. ty. Im going to check that</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-smb-setup/684#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 21:11:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1610</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
