<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Kicksecure does not use systemd-resolved by default - maybe this is reason for the problems?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 18:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1748</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How does Kicksecure compare to Silverblue?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Silverblue/secureblue does not have a live-mode - it is seriously inferior to Kicksecure. I think many people like kicksecure for its live mode.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-does-kicksecure-compare-to-silverblue/745#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 16:42:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1747</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>GrapheneOS Attacks Kicksecure! What should the response be?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I am not sure the author of that tweet is seeking a productive conversation. This is what I get from the [Whonix X account](<a href="https://x.com/Whonix" class="inline-onebox">x.com</a> account):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why can’t you reply to this?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This author has blocked you, so you can’t perform this action</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Got it</p>
</blockquote>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080" title="x_blocked"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080_2_690x370.jpeg" alt="x_blocked" data-base62-sha1="y9w3PK10EURbaH35PlPdLhDKXeg" width="690" height="370" srcset="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080_2_690x370.jpeg, https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080_2_1035x555.jpeg 1.5x, https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/ef5d5305ed38be00c0e2de71a62d0aa63df20080.jpeg 2x" data-dominant-color="D9DADB"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Generally, I am also not sure Twitter / X is a suitable place for a productive conversation.</p>
<p>If I had to guess, I would say that this is in retaliation for:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Mobile_Operating_System_Comparison" class="inline-onebox">Mobile Operating System Comparison</a> chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Mobile_Operating_System_Comparison#GrapheneOS">GrapheneOS</a>, which is factual, backed with sources/references, but unwelcome criticism. (Discussion here: <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/overview-of-mobile-projects-that-focus-on-either-and-or-security-privacy-anonymity-source-available-freedom-software/4557/48" class="inline-onebox">Overview of Mobile Projects - That focus on either/and/or security, privacy, anonymity, source-available, Freedom Software. - #48 by TommyTran732 - News - Whonix Forum</a>) And maybe,</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot - Kicksecure</a> chapters, <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Rooted_Security_versus_Non-Rooted_Security">Rooted Security versus Non-Rooted Security</a> and <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Ideological_Considerations">Ideological Considerations</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>That tweet might have been in context of <a href="https://privsec.dev/posts/linux/choosing-your-desktop-linux-distribution/" class="inline-onebox">Choosing Your Desktop Linux Distribution | PrivSec - A practical approach to Privacy and Security</a> because another commenter has posted it in that thread (<a href="https://xcancel.com/iAnonymous3000/status/1861464122405110098#m">https://xcancel.com/iAnonymous3000/status/1861464122405110098#m</a>) and then the author referring to “encrypted swap”.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Kicksecure/Whonix doesn’t do any significant hardening</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I can imagine how one could come to such a mistaken conclusion, if not having reviewed:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/#security">Kicksecure homepage, security</a>,</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/About" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure - A Security Hardened Linux Distribution</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Strong_Linux_User_Account_Isolation" class="inline-onebox">Strong Linux User Account Isolation</a>,</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc" class="inline-onebox">GitHub - Kicksecure/security-misc: Kernel Hardening; Protect Linux User Accounts against Brute Force Attacks; Improve Entropy Collection; Strong Linux User Account Separation; Enhances Misc Security Settings - https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Security-misc</a></li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>They sabotaged security efforts</p>
</blockquote>
<p>They’re entitled to their opinion but I would suggest when critizing others, making grandiose accusations, it should always be backed up with actual evidence.</p>
<p>Better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>They sabotaged security efforts [1]</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>[1] exact link/reference + exact quotation</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Otherwise, one first need to ask for clarification what this is even about.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>and the efforts to do that were stalled and then rolled back when the person responsible for most of it left the project.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If this is about <a href="https://github.com/madaidan" class="inline-onebox">madaidan · GitHub</a>, then it can be seen that madaidan’s github activity completely ceased in 2022, not only related to Kicksecure/Whonix.</p>
<p>Related: <a href="https://github.com/madaidans-insecurities/madaidans-insecurities.github.io/issues/77" class="inline-onebox">Is this project still maintained? · Issue #77 · madaidans-insecurities/madaidans-insecurities.github.io · GitHub</a></p>
<p>So this can hardly be blamed on Kicksecure/Whonix.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="qtzvytqr77x4t5cq" data-post="1" data-topic="739">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/q/a4c791/48.png" class="avatar"> qtzvytqr77x4t5cq:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Secureblue is doing useful work.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>And I am glad to see, that secureblue was inspired by Kicksecure, forked some of Kicksecure’s configuration files. For example, documented here, quote <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/secureblue" class="inline-onebox">Comparison of secureblue with Kicksecure and Development Notes</a></p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>secureblue <code>/etc/sysctl.d/hardening.conf</code> file as of commit <a href="https://github.com/secureblue/secureblue/blob/a6b58f042b0e9e9036a6d68a5b202eed96a1a892/files/system/etc/sysctl.d/hardening.conf">a6b58f042b0e9e9036a6d68a5b202eed96a1a892</a><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/https://github.com/secureblue/secureblue/blob/a6b58f042b0e9e9036a6d68a5b202eed96a1a892/files/system/etc/sysctl.d/hardening.conf"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/73/Internet_Archive_logo.png" alt="archive.org" width="13" height="15"></a> was inspired by, more or less copied and pasted from Kicksecure as can be seen from the following comment found in that file.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">## Prevent kernel info leaks in console during boot. ## https://phabricator.whonix.org/T950 kernel.printk = 3 3 3 3
</code></pre>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>Can be discussed here:</p><aside class="quote" data-post="2" data-topic="745">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-does-kicksecure-compare-to-silverblue/745/2">How does Kicksecure compare to Silverblue?</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/support/6"><span data-category-id="6" style="--category-badge-color: #0088CC; --category-badge-text-color: #FFFFFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="User support for the Kicksecure operating system."><span class="badge-category__name">Support</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    Created just now to answer this:
  </blockquote>
</aside>

<p>So I hope this would extend to, “Kicksecure is doing useful work”.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grapheneos-attacks-kicksecure-what-should-the-response-be/739#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 14:48:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1746</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How does Kicksecure compare to Silverblue?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Created just now to answer this:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/secureblue">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732959025" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/secureblue" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:13PM - 30 November 2024">Kicksecure – 30 Nov 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/secureblue" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Comparison of secureblue with Kicksecure and Development Notes</a></h3>

  <p>Comparison of some of Secureblue and Kicksecure security enhancements, hardening techniques, and unique development features. Explore detailed differences, overlapping features, and future improvement notes for both security-focused operating...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-does-kicksecure-compare-to-silverblue/745#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 14:17:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1745</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>How does Kicksecure compare to Silverblue?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@extraextra]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>How does Kicksecure compare to Silverblue?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-does-kicksecure-compare-to-silverblue/745#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 09:50:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1743</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>GrapheneOS Attacks Kicksecure! What should the response be?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@privacy]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Kicksecure is awful. Has a horrible choice of base OS for security and they don’t do valuable work to improve it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Who is they?</p>
<p>You mean not very many people are contributing enough or working on Kicksecure is what that translates to?<br>
The claim that Kicksecure “doesn’t do valuable work to improve it” overlooks the contributions made by the project in terms of privacy and security enhancements. Kicksecure integrates various security features and tools that are designed to protect user anonymity and data, which can be valuable in the context of its intended use.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>They sabotaged security efforts and are spreading misinformation about allocator hardening and other topics they don’t understand.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The understanding I have is it breaking Xorg and both Whonix/Kicksecure use Xfce. Again who is they who is sabotaging security efforts, do they mean more like little to no people working on it compared to GrapheneOS?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Secureblue is doing useful work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok, some of those things look like they could be ported or looked at on Kicksecure/Whonix but take in mind this Secureblue is a Fedora project.</p>
<p>Kicksecure strives to be hardened Debian or rather what Debian out of the box should be. If you have ever manually hardened your Debian installs you understand how valuable Kicksecure or rather the repository is.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone making an equivalent out of Fedora Silverblue or Arch would obsolete it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again the focus on the base system is Debian.<br>
This is not a Fedora based distro or Arch.</p>
<p>Silverblue uses two things for containerization Podman and Flatpak, but primarily uses Podman for containerization. Podman may be something for Kicksecure/Whonix to look into, but in regards to Flatpak I’m someone who will always avoid it because I think Flatpak is utter trash.</p>
<p>Silverblue and Android both use SELinux. SELinux is more complex then AppArmor but might be better but requires lots of configuration and policy management. Take in mind another Privacy/Security distro Tails doesn’t use SELinux but rather AppArmor instead.</p>
<p>Also as stated by Daniel Micay:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>AppArmor is extremely limited in what it can do compared to SELinux. Ubuntu integrated of App Armor and the Fedora and RHEL integration of SELinux barely does anything though. That’s not particularly serious SELinux integration and barely does anything for a desktop setup at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="qtzvytqr77x4t5cq" data-post="1" data-topic="739">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/q/a4c791/48.png" class="avatar"> qtzvytqr77x4t5cq:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Presumably, you all disagree with Daniel Micay / GrapheneOS. What is the rebuttal here?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Well I will say this Daniel Micay always has always acted like everyone is out to get him.<br>
Unlike Daniel Micay, the main dev that maintains Whonix/Kicksecure <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/patrick">@Patrick</a> is the one holding up the project isn’t attacking others and acting like everyone is out to get them.<br>
It’s important to recognize the challenges that come with being the primary maintainer of a project. Burnout can be a real issue for those who are responsible for testing and developing software, and this can impact the pace of progress. Patrick’s ability to navigate these challenges while fostering a positive environment speaks to his character and dedication to the project. I have never felt anything other then a  toxic or rather elitist feeling then when I have talked to those in the GrapheneOS space, I don’t feel that reflects their developers, but rather their community. I don’t get that feeling in the Kicksecure/Whonix community.</p>
<p>The only thing I guess I could agree with him on is his/her’s tweet is mention of Wayland and I think a top priority of Kicksecure/Whonix would be swiching to Wayland and a different Desktop Environment instead of Xfce. As it currently stands Xfce doesn’t have Wayland support. I don’t know how Hardened Malloc works with Wayland but once the switch then it could be ported. Whonix workstation and Kicksecure could be better but this involves research/testing and you know like more people contributing, which Daniel fails to mention.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grapheneos-attacks-kicksecure-what-should-the-response-be/739#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 08:38:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1742</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>All apps work - telegram, whatsapp, signal, browser (except tor without tor). As soon as you uninstall kicksecure and pure vpn instantly connects to servers. That’s why I am asking which kicksecure package can affect internet? You can install tor in kicksecure, then disable tor network: network.dns.disabled ⇒ false extensions.torlauncher.start_tor ⇒ false network.proxy.socks ⇒ _ and this browser won’t work, but it work in default debian-ubuntu. If you can launch this browser, it will launch a pure vpn. I knew for sure that security-misk, tirdad, sdwdate packages were definitely not related to this problem</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 07:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1740</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="3" data-topic="742">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>you should know which package in kicksecure is responsible for internet or dns management. i thought it was kicksecure-network-conf package but no - it’s not even installed</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Please keep in mind that Kicksecure is a large project, and I am an external contributor to it. I know many parts of it quite well, but other parts I’m not as familiar with. I don’t necessarily know exactly where every other contributor before me has put everything <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=12" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="linuxer" data-post="3" data-topic="742">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/b5e925/48.png" class="avatar"> linuxer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>yes without vpn everything works except tor browser without tor network - my girlfriend has 2 tor browsers, one is like a mallvad. in this browser there is no internet - “check dns settings” (internet works without kicksecure)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I should have been more clear - I’m trying to find out if DNS is working for other apps or not. It sounds like it probably is, but just so we can be completely sure, can you share the output of <code>dig kicksecure.com</code>?</p>
<p>Finally, other users of PureVPN have noticed “connection timed out” errors that didn’t have anything to do with DNS. See <a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=230486" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">[SOLVED] PureVPN with OpenVPN timeout / Networking, Server, and Protection / Arch Linux Forums</a>, maybe that has some info that would be useful?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 01:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1738</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>namesrever 127.0.0.53<br>
yes without vpn everything works except tor browser without tor network - my girlfriend has 2 tor browsers, one is like a mallvad. in this browser there is no internet - “check dns settings” (internet works without kicksecure)<br>
Package: systemd-resolved<br>
Status: install ok installed<br>
pure-vpn log says that connection timed out</p>
<p>you should know which package in kicksecure is responsible for internet or dns management. i thought it was kicksecure-network-conf package but no - it’s not even installed</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 17:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1737</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>To begin with, I’d recommend running <code>sudo apt install --no-install-recommends kicksecure-cli-host</code> to put back at least most of the packages you’ve tried removing. Without knowing what you removed, it’s hard to know whether you’ve potentially weakened the system’s security or not.</p>
<p>Next, the DNS stuff. Right now I’m not totally sure that DNS is actually the problem, and if it is, it’s unclear what’s wrong with it, so I need to ask you for some more information.</p>
<ul>
<li>Can you share the contents of your <code>/etc/resolv.conf</code> file? This file indicates what DNS server the system is using. I <em>do</em> need to see the IP addresses in this file, since they tell me what DNS servers the system is configured to use. Unless your network is very badly misconfigured, or you’re hosting your own public DNS server in your house, those IP addresses won’t be usable to locate or identify you, and thus should be safe to share publicly. You can look up any IP addresses you see to make extra sure.</li>
<li>Is the computer able to connect to websites without a VPN?</li>
<li>What is the output of <code>dpkg-query -s systemd-resolved</code>?</li>
<li>Does “pure-vpn” have logs you can share that could help us understand what’s wrong a little bit better?</li>
</ul>
<p>I have an idea for a fix, but let’s start with that and see where things go from there.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 15:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1736</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>GrapheneOS Attacks Kicksecure! What should the response be?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>As far as I can tell, this has no bearing on Kicksecure whatsoever.</p>
<p>External community drama is not a distro problem, it’s that simple. People are entitled to their own opinions about software applications, and are welcome to share those opinions with others. I do it, my friends do it, you’ve probably done it, and I have no issue with someone at GrapheneOS doing it too. (I say “someone” because I don’t know who has control over the official GrapheneOS Twitter account.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grapheneos-attacks-kicksecure-what-should-the-response-be/739#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 15:34:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1735</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>After morphing, I can not start distrobox</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>yes you are right. second problem is not related to kicksecure. sorry</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/after-morphing-i-can-not-start-distrobox/688#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 09:25:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1734</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>VPN does not work after installing Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@linuxer]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>hi. my girlfriend installed morphing kicksecure on debian xfce and her pure-vpn stopped working - can’t connect to server. it looks like these are problems due to dns changes. how to return default dns settings or what package to delete so that kicksecure doesn’t interfere with dns? i tried to delete several packages, but to no avail. only timeshift solves problem - a return to default debian. i use nordvpn and mullvad - there is no such problem.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/vpn-does-not-work-after-installing-kicksecure/742#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 09:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1733</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>GrapheneOS Attacks Kicksecure! What should the response be?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@extraextra]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Use an exclamation mark as if this is a big deal? So you just made a new account here to start a mud fight?</p>
<p><a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/patrick">@Patrick</a>: Don’t waste your time with Daniel Micay. He’s got some issues. Starting fights with everyone as reported numerous times.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=Dx7CZ-2Bajg" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://youtube.com/watch?v=Dx7CZ-2Bajg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=4To-F6W1NT0" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://youtube.com/watch?v=4To-F6W1NT0</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bromite/bromite/issues/2141" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Please remove all code from Vanadium and GrapheneOS project members · Issue #2141 · bromite/bromite · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/PrivacyGuides/comments/13spm4d/daniel_micay_steps_down_as_lead_developer_of/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.reddit.com/r/PrivacyGuides/comments/13spm4d/daniel_micay_steps_down_as_lead_developer_of/</a> and steps up again.</li>
</ul>
<p>Next level trolling.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grapheneos-attacks-kicksecure-what-should-the-response-be/739#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 08:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1730</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>GrapheneOS Attacks Kicksecure! What should the response be?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@qtzvytqr77x4t5cq]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I do not know what the correct forum category is to post this. I presume that this category is okay? Please move the topic if there is a better forum category for it.</p>
<p><a href="https://xcancel.com/GrapheneOS/status/1861465637886754839#m" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://xcancel.com/GrapheneOS/status/1861465637886754839#m</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Kicksecure is awful. Has a horrible choice of base OS for security and they don’t do valuable work to improve it. They sabotaged security efforts and are spreading misinformation about allocator hardening and other topics they don’t understand.</p>
<p>Secureblue is doing useful work.</p>
<p>The concept used by Whonix for forcing traffic through Tor makes sense but the OS has awful security, just like the Tor Browser itself having awful security. Someone making an equivalent out of Fedora Silverblue or Arch would obsolete it.</p>
<p>Kicksecure/Whonix doesn’t do any significant hardening and the efforts to do that were stalled and then rolled back when the person responsible for most of it left the project. It has some minor anonymity changes easily done elsewhere. Encrypted swap is widely used elsewhere.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Presumably, you all disagree with Daniel Micay / GrapheneOS. What is the rebuttal here?</p>
<p>Thank you for your responses.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/grapheneos-attacks-kicksecure-what-should-the-response-be/739#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1729</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="Patrick" data-post="8" data-topic="732">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Which are very hard to solve issues. I don’t think there’s much you can do. What you’re looking for is confidential computing. It doesn’t really exist at time of writing. Bits and pieces, our research can be found here:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Confidential Computing</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is it finally</p>
<p>I guessed that the computer freaks have chewed through all topics and everything related without exception</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 22:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1728</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>It did not help. Both options did not fix problem. Sleep mode and sddm hanging remained</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46?page=2#post_22</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 19:46:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1727</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Which are very hard to solve issues. I don’t think there’s much you can do. What you’re looking for is confidential computing. It doesn’t really exist at time of writing. Bits and pieces, our research can be found here:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="09:18PM - 31 October 2024">Kicksecure – 31 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/394;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/f/ff/Confidential_computing.jpeg?version=e8d28b4a626bbb896fb54671c36b43af" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="394"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Confidential Computing</a></h3>

  <p>Confidential computing is an advanced security technology that protects data while it's in use, complementing existing protections for data at rest and in transit. The goal is to isolate sensitive data from unauthorized access, even from the cloud...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>But very far from anything actionable by users.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 17:08:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1721</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Conclusion</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="732">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Which is provided by the cloud, under cloud provider control</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes its like amazon aws etc<br>
Vnc coud be used instead of glish .</p>
<p>But despite open source</p>
<p>memory can be inspected by the cloud’s owner - and the encryption key can be extracted wich is very unlikly and high risky for a company</p>
<p>As the main goal is only to protect files periodly  inside vm<br>
Fde woud be enough even not 100% secure .</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 17:02:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1720</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Okay. I will try on debian and mx kde</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_21</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 16:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1719</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>PRETTY_NAME=“Debian GNU/Linux 12 (bookworm)”<br>
NAME=“Debian GNU/Linux”<br>
VERSION_ID=“12”<br>
VERSION=“12 (bookworm)”<br>
VERSION_CODENAME=bookworm<br>
ID=debian<br>
I respect you very much. I recommend kicksecure os or kicksecure packages to everyone who works on any debian. and recommend whonix <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=12" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"><br>
if we talk about debian 12, then errors only in kde plasma. I noticed same errors (sddm, sleep) in sparky (debian trixie) in VM.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_20</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 16:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1718</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="17" data-topic="46">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We use standard debian. I dont even know where to find other debian repositories. According to cinnamon, problem was only in LMDE.<br>
But problems with kde plasma were on all computers and in all systems - debian, lmde, mx, sparky.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It would have been helpful to know this a few comments ago <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/sweat_smile.png?v=12" title=":sweat_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":sweat_smile:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> I spent an hour testing on physical hardware with Cinnamon last night thinking that was the most efficient way to test things, since I had been led to believe the issue was reproducible on Debian with the Cinnamon desktop earlier:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="9" data-topic="46">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I have not seen these problems in xfce. Only in Cinnamon and Kde Plasma. These problems are related to security-misc - removing package fixes these problems.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Anyway, no hard feelings, but when reporting issues, it’s better to give more details early on.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="17" data-topic="46">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>This topic is dedicated to other linuxes and is listed on the site as a discussion of kicksecure in other OS. That’s why I shared my experience here.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Sure, I get that and I respect that. But at the same time, it sounded like you had done experimentation on unsupported but still likely-to-work platforms, and ran into problems on a fully supported platform (i.e. distro-morphing vanilla Debian). Naturally this is concerning, so we did some bug hunting to see if we could reproduce the issue the same way.</p>
<p>Before I go and try to install Debian with KDE Plasma, could you please tell me <strong>which release of Debian are you using?</strong> You can find out by running <code>cat /etc/os-release</code> in a terminal. Please share the entire <code>VERSION</code> variable shown in the command’s output.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_19</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 15:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1717</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="suse211213" data-post="5" data-topic="732">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/35a633/48.png" class="avatar"> suse211213:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>From cloud manager dashboard and glish</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Which is provided by the cloud, under cloud provider control, there’s a logging risk and this is also most likely non-freedom software?</p>
<p>I am not considering that sort of vendor specific, non-freedom software specific implementations due to these security concerns.</p>
<p>related:</p><aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Avoid_nonfreedom_software">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Avoid_nonfreedom_software" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:18PM - 01 October 2023">Kicksecure – 1 Oct 23</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="500" height="500" src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/b/b8/No-admittance-98806-640.png?version=8c66f98157a3fea7e2b05bc42372fbea" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar">

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Avoid_nonfreedom_software" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Avoid Non-Freedom Software</a></h3>

  <p>Why you should avoid Non-Freedom Software</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 13:45:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1716</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Same installation steps but happening on some computers but not on others?</p>
<p>Instead of deleting all of security-misc, finding the offending setting in security-misc might be useful. It’s most likely a kernel parameter hardening setting.</p>
<p>For that purpose, <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Security-misc#Debugging">security-misc, Debugging</a> has been written now.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_18</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 13:42:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1715</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="11" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I see there’s already an open report that you’ve interacted with at <a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/issues/2137">Allow Calamares to set GRUB password · Issue #2137 · calamares/calamares · GitHub</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I forgot about it. Thanks for reminding me.</p>
<p>However, that ticket, while confusing, might be about grub disk encryption password prompt as opposed to grub boot menu authentication prompt.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="11" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Then again, do we <em>want</em> it in Calamares for Kicksecure? We’d be introducing more system state changing bits into the installer, which I know is something we’ve wanted to avoid in the past.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="11" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>though it may be worth looking for existing tools that do this.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That would be good.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 13:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1714</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>We use standard debian. I dont even know where to find other debian repositories. According to cinnamon, problem was only in LMDE.<br>
But problems with kde plasma were on all computers and in all systems - debian, lmde, mx, sparky. The main problem with sddm is precisely at startup (if autologin is disabled, which kicksecure launches by default). I also had this problem. It cannot be reproduced when changing user or ending session - only when starting. Sleep mode hung on 3 computers of which there are 5 - on debian and 2 on mx. Solution to problems has always been one - removing security-misc.<br>
This topic is dedicated to other linuxes and is listed on the site as a discussion of kicksecure in other OS. That’s why I shared my experience here. But, once again, debian kde plasma had all same problems. I helped friends to log debian 2 weeks ago, when sddm did not let them in after updating security-misc, They launched console mode and deleted security-misc - problem disappeared. Maybe it is a hardware issue. BUT it was also on old laptops and on new ones from 5 different companies</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_17</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 11:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1713</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I have now tested distro morphing Debian 12 Cinnamon into Kicksecure on physical hardware (my main development machine). I used <code>kicksecure-xfce-host</code> this time since it sounded like that’s what you were using. I still can’t reproduce the issue - the install works just fine, security-misc is present, LightDM doesn’t freeze whether I feed it good passwords or bad passwords, sleep works out of the box.</p>
<p>If you and your friend are both running into issues, it’s likely to be the result of one of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>What you’re calling Debian is not what I’m calling Debian. I’m using the official Debian 12 (Bookworm) netinstaller, which gives me a vanilla Debian installation. This is what Kicksecure supports, so it’s expected to work. If your “Debian” is Debian 11 (Bullseye) or Debian Testing (Trixie at the time of this writing), that could be the problem.</li>
<li>You and your friend happen to use the same third-party repository on your systems, and that repository is incompatible with Kicksecure in some way.</li>
<li>Both of you are shockingly unlucky when it comes to what hardware you ended up with. (Hardware-specific issues like this are relatively rare nowadays so I wouldn’t expect this to be the case.)</li>
</ul>
<p>I don’t know for sure if any of the above apply here, this is just what comes to mind initially. If there’s any further data you can give about how you’re reproducing this (what software versions you’re using, what steps you’re taking, even hardware info might come in handy), that might help debug this. Currently though I can’t get it to break.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_16</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 07:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1712</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>From cloud manager dashboard and glish<br>
First of all two config profiles are needed during netinstall</p>
<p>1- installer profile<br>
2- boot profile</p>
<p>Enable option full virtualization prefered over para-virtualization</p>
<p>Booting</p>
<p>Adde disc &amp; boot config<br>
Boot this config , once instance is running .you click on launch console then  click Glish then text pop up where luks passwd needed .</p>
<p>Not all cloud provider offer fde feature<br>
Some are worse</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 23:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1710</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hmm, I hadn’t thought about this being a Calamares feature request, though I guess that makes sense now that you mention it. I see there’s already an open report that you’ve interacted with at <a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/issues/2137" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Allow Calamares to set GRUB password · Issue #2137 · calamares/calamares · GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>Then again, do we <em>want</em> it in Calamares for Kicksecure? We’d be introducing more system state changing bits into the installer, which I know is something we’ve wanted to avoid in the past. It might be better to have a custom tool within the OS that the user can use to set or change the password. Such a tool would be usable in preinstalled VMs as well as newly installed systems.</p>
<p>If we were to use the custom tool solution, I don’t think this is something we could easily upstream somewhere, though it may be worth looking for existing tools that do this. If we want the installer-based solution, then naturally Calamares would be the best place to upstream it.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 22:38:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1709</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>kk, I’ll give it another shot with physical hardware and installing kicksecure-xfce-host instead.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_15</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 20:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1708</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#How_to_set_a_bootloader_password">How to set a bootloader password</a> has been documented thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/nurmagoz">@nurmagoz</a>.</p>
<p>If we had a simple script to automate these simple but non-trivial steps, that would be good progress.</p>
<p>Could that be upstreamed somewhere?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="9" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think the only thing I’d really like to add to all of the above is that we document how to make the Dracut recovery console available again. I’ve used it for multiple debugging sessions that would have been rendered impossible or close to impossible without it.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That’s for sure.</p>
<ul>
<li>documentation</li>
<li>added to debug-misc package</li>
</ul>
<p>(Completely separate things.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="9" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We should be careful with calling it more secure IMO - the bootloader password may be harder to bypass, but the BIOS password is necessary to complicate attacks that involve booting from an external USB drive. They both have their pros and cons, and ideally should be used together.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Alright.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="9" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Also, we should consider how whatever tooling we make for setting this password interacts with FDE. A user with high security requirements might use BIOS password, bootloader password, FDE passphrase, and a user account password, preferably all different. Most users with moderate security requirements will get away with just FDE though, and those with lower requirements can use a BIOS + bootloader password and avoid the overhead and potential data loss risk of FDE. Do we want our tool to tell the user “You’re using FDE, you probably don’t need a bootloader password”? If so, should we make some brief in-tool documentation that explains the threat models each configuration might be used to defend against?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Probably yes.</p>
<p>Step 1: Writing good documention explaining all of what we discussed in the wiki on <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks" class="inline-onebox">Protection against Physical Attacks</a>.</p>
<p>Step 2: This might be quite difficult to get the usability design right. Perhaps this should be discussed with calamares for wider input?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 20:05:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1707</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>And how do you boot the server and enter the full disk encryption password?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 19:45:41 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1706</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="732">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Probably, but solving FDE on the server will be hard.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>What u mean .<br>
You mean its hard to setup fde on server ?<br>
As some provider provide guide on how to setup this through netinstall</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 18:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1705</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>24GB of disk taken by fresh install Bookworm distromorph? + other notes</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Disks application says 24GB used?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Software#Disk_Space_Analyzer">Disk Space<br>
Analyzer</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sidenote: Installed tor browser which has started suggesting browsing history in address bar after starting tor browser. (Computer was powered on just prior to starting tor browser.) All browsing history settings are off and tor browser default settings should prevent any browsing history carry on from previous instanses.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Unspecific to Kicksecure.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732613425" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:10AM - 06 September 2024">Kicksecure – 6 Sep 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:250/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/7/74/Booster132.png?version=45557debf593fbb24d26970c477f16db" class="thumbnail" width="250" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Potential Solutions Beyond Kicksecure!</a></h3>

  <p>Explore resources outside of Kicksecure to address unspecific questions or issues.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<blockquote>
<p>Is there way to confirm things are the way they should be with the tor browser.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not much. You can compare with Debian.</p>
<p>See also:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/System_Audit">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732613425" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/System_Audit" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:43AM - 21 September 2024">Kicksecure – 21 Sep 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img width="500" height="500" src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/4/4a/Systemcheck1234640.png?version=a11126a6375fcc587b9175b32d5b34b2" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar">

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/System_Audit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">System Audit</a></h3>

  <p>Verifying the system is configured as intended</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<blockquote>
<p>Farsidenote: Also there was no calculator in applications. Had to install gnome calculator myself. Is this normal?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Morenote: Is it ok to install OpenSnitch on Kicksecure. Would like to see who is calling where. I have been using it as a comforting passifier or excuse, for years for not delving deeper into ip taples cringe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ok.</p>
<p>Not much advice available at this point. When this changes, the<br>
following wiki page will be updated:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Host_Firewall">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732613425" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Host_Firewall" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="12:42PM - 21 October 2024">Kicksecure – 21 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:466/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/9/9e/Firewall-34227640.png?version=59eb59ff4820ab81ba8c7b480fc7dbb5" class="thumbnail" width="466" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Host_Firewall" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Host Firewall</a></h3>

  <p>Host Firewall Installation and Configuration</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Updates will be posted here:</p>
<aside class="quote" data-post="1" data-topic="378">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/8491ac/48.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-firewall/378">Kicksecure Firewall</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/development/7"><span data-category-id="7" style="--category-badge-color: #25AAE2; --category-badge-text-color: #FFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="Development of Kicksecure software and source code."><span class="badge-category__name">Development</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    What is the Firewall comes with Kicksecure on CLI? ufw was not included anywhere in any metapackage.
  </blockquote>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/24gb-of-disk-taken-by-fresh-install-bookworm-distromorph-other-notes/731#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 17:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1704</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>suse211213 via Kicksecure Forums:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When using kicksecure as instance on cloud with FDE<br>
Where is key stored<br>
How is the privacy and security</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nothing special. Unspecific to Kicksecure.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Does cloud provider in this case act as host system where everething can be monitored accessed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ram wipe worth it ?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Probably, but solving FDE on the server will be hard.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Any related docs about vps to consider</p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SSH">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SSH" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:46PM - 26 November 2024">Kicksecure – 26 Nov 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:131/129;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/8d/Sshlogo.png?version=408127b3e46a9506f59d3da8f763f7e3" class="thumbnail" width="131" height="129"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/SSH" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Secure Shell (SSH)</a></h3>

  <p>SSH Hardening Tips; Recommended Client and Server Settings for better Security</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Full_Disk_Encryption">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Full_Disk_Encryption" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="12:28PM - 27 November 2024">Kicksecure – 27 Nov 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/426;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/0d/Fulldeskencryption423423.jpg?version=d499f65d45ec9fa7630b7a52e5dad247" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="426"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Full_Disk_Encryption" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Full Disk Encryption (FDE)</a></h3>

  <p>Full Disk Encryption, Additional Security Measures</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="01:16PM - 27 November 2024">Kicksecure – 27 Nov 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/426;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/d/d8/Protectionagainst234234234.jpg?version=be39d97982a001431c9c5b5eb98e0120" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="426"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Protection against Physical Attacks</a></h3>

  <p>BIOS Password, Problematic Interfaces, Screen Lock, Virtual Consoles, Login Screen, Side Channel Attacks</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732699825" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="09:18PM - 31 October 2024">Kicksecure – 31 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/394;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/f/ff/Confidential_computing.jpeg?version=e8d28b4a626bbb896fb54671c36b43af" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="394"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/confidential_computing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Confidential Computing</a></h3>

  <p>Confidential computing is an advanced security technology that protects data while it's in use, complementing existing protections for data at rest and in transit. The goal is to isolate sensitive data from unauthorized access, even from the cloud...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 17:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1703</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure on cloud</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@suse211213]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>When using kicksecure as instance on cloud with FDE<br>
Where is key stored<br>
How is the privacy and security<br>
Does cloud provider in this case act as host system where everething can be monitored accessed.</p>
<p>Ram wipe worth it ?</p>
<p>Any related docs about vps to consider</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-on-cloud/732#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 17:04:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1702</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>me and my friends used standard morphing installation. i would be grateful if you wrote installation for kde plasma and cinnamon. what commands to enter instead of sudo apt install --no-install-recommends kicksecure-xfce-host. But i also installed separate packages - grub-live, security-misc, tirdad and sdwdate - this also led to login hang. Perhaps there are nuances on the virtual machine, so there are no records of sleep mode and sddm. but i have not yet seen a host system that would not have sddm hang after last security-misc update. in some computers sddm hangs only after an incorrect password. in other computers (and mine) when entering any password. but sleep mode does not hang on my computer and on the computer of one friend, but on two other friends sleep mode always hangs - removing security-misc solved this problem. Even installing only one security-misc package on cde plasma and cinnamon caused freezes. I thought the conflict was only with cde plasma, but recently my friend’s LMDE also froze Lightdm</p>
<p>in old versions of security-misc, these problems were not there. only problem was the wrong password entry in sddm at startup. but sleep mode worked well for everyone. If you install kicksecure xfce morph and remove security-misc, then there are no problems and errors - this has been tested on all the OSes I mentioned</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_14</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 12:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1701</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>24GB of disk taken by fresh install Bookworm distromorph? + other notes</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@johnsmith1001]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Downloaded and verified Debian bookworm ISO.<br>
dd if=offed it to a usb stick.<br>
Installed Debian xfce to my laptops 80GB ssd.<br>
Distromorphed Kicksecure following these instructions:</p>
<p>trafotin com v kicksecure</p>
<p>When starting first time to the desktop the Disks application says 24GB used?</p>
<p>This cant be normal. Could some kicksecures memory security features cause this?</p>
<p>Sidenotes:<br>
-Installed tor browser bundle, which has now started suggesting browsing history in address bar after starting tor browser. (Computer was powered on just prior to starting tor browser.) All browsing history settings are off and tor browser default settings should prevent any browsing history carry on from previous instanses. Just mentioning this if it is related to other funnybusiness. Posting this to tor forum also. Search about it gave very little.</p>
<p>-Is it ok to install OpenSnitch on Kicksecure. Would like to see who is calling where. I have been using it as a comforting passifier or excuse, for years for not delving deeper into firewall and ip-taples cringe.</p>
<p>-CD/DVD wont play. VLC player gives error message:</p>
<p>-There was no calculator in applications? Installed Gnome Calculator myself.</p>
<p>Otherwise all is sweet so far.</p>
<p>Thank you for all the great work and effort you have put into this.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/24gb-of-disk-taken-by-fresh-install-bookworm-distromorph-other-notes/731#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 06:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1700</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You’ll have to give more specific steps for how to reproduce this. I’ve just attempted to reproduce the issue using Debian 12 + KDE Plasma, on a UEFI-based virt-manager machine. The exact steps taken are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Create a new virtual machine, specify that a Debian 12.7.0 netinst ISO should be used</li>
<li>Set RAM to 4 GB, disk space to 20 GB</li>
<li>Check “Customize configuration before installing” on the final screen of the VM creation wizard</li>
<li>Set firmware to UEFI (specifically <code>OVMF_CODE_4M.fd</code>)</li>
<li>Begin installation</li>
<li>Configure as follows:
<ul>
<li>Full Name: <code>User</code></li>
<li>Username: <code>user</code></li>
<li>Disk configuration:
<ul>
<li>Partition 1: EFI System Partition, 300 MB</li>
<li>Partition 2: ext4 mounted at <code>/</code>, use all remaining disk space</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Desktop environment: KDE Plasma</li>
<li>Timezone and locale settings set appropriately</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Once installation is complete, reboot</li>
<li>Carefully follow instructions at <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Debian" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Install Kicksecure inside Debian</a> to morph the distribution into Kicksecure, some notes as to how I followed the instructions:
<ul>
<li>When given the option of using extrepo or manual configuration for initially adding the Kicksecure repository, I chose manual configuration.</li>
<li>Signing key was downloaded using TLS.</li>
<li>“Clearnet Rep.” settings were used for manually configuring the Kicksecure repo.</li>
<li>The Kicksecure metapackage I installed was <code>kicksecure-cli-host</code>, to avoid pulling in XFCE</li>
<li>Before following post-installation steps, I rebooted, tested login via SDDM with both Plasma X11 and Plasma Wayland sessions, confirmed it worked, and confirmed <code>security-misc</code> was installed using <code>dpkg-query -s security-misc</code> (it came back as <code>install ok installed</code>)</li>
<li>In the post-installation steps, I used <code>sudo rm /etc/apt/sources.list</code> rather than <code>sudo mv /etc/apt/sources.list ~/</code> for getting rid of the original sources.list file, it contained nothing important</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With this setup, Kicksecure is installed, <code>security-misc</code> is installed, and SDDM login works just fine, both with Wayland and X11 options. <s>I did not test sleep since this is a virtual machine and getting a virt-manager VM out of sleep can be <em>really hard</em>, but I would expect it to work.</s> EDIT: Just tested sleep too, works without issues, even with <code>security-misc</code> installed.</p>
<p>Some things about your configuration that you may want to double-check that may be the source of some of the issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>Did you install <code>kicksecure-cli-host</code> or <code>kicksecure-xfce-host</code>? Doing the latter on a machine with another desktop environment already will end up installing XFCE on the machine, which could conflict with your existing desktop environment in interesting ways.</li>
<li>Is your user account named <code>user</code>? There are some subsystems in Kicksecure that only allow an account named <code>user</code> to take certain actions. It’s possible (though unlikely) that the inability to take those actions with another account could be causing the issue.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve not yet tested with the Cinnamon desktop, or with Debian derivatives such as Sparky or Mint.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_13</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 23:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1698</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think I like the idea, especially in combination with disabling “easy” recovery mode and the Dracut recovery console. I think the only thing I’d really like to add to all of the above is that we document how to make the Dracut recovery console available again. I’ve used it for multiple debugging sessions that would have been rendered impossible or close to impossible without it. Let’s go with requiring the password on every boot since that provides substantial benefits over just locking out the configuration options.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="8" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>GRUB bootloader password to prevent all boot menu entries could be considered more secure than BIOS power-on password, because it’s not a “hardware magic feature” but instead a software feature implemented in Freedom Software, GRUB.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We should be careful with calling it more secure IMO - the bootloader password may be harder to bypass, but the BIOS password is necessary to complicate attacks that involve booting from an external USB drive. They both have their pros and cons, and ideally should be used together.</p>
<p>Also, we should consider how whatever tooling we make for setting this password interacts with FDE. A user with high security requirements might use BIOS password, bootloader password, FDE passphrase, and a user account password, preferably all different. Most users with moderate security requirements will get away with just FDE though, and those with lower requirements can use a BIOS + bootloader password and avoid the overhead and potential data loss risk of FDE. Do we want our tool to tell the user “You’re using FDE, you probably don’t need a bootloader password”? If so, should we make some brief in-tool documentation that explains the threat models each configuration might be used to defend against?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 23:16:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1697</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>System freezes on startup after entering login and password</p>
<p>polkit-agent-helper-1[4010]: pam_exec(polkit-1:auth): usr/libexec/security-misc/pam_faillock_not_if_x failed: exit code 1<br>
pam_wheel(polkit-1:auth): Ignoring access request ‘user’ for ‘user’</p>
<p>sddm [1940] authentication information: "usr/libexec/security-misc/pam-info: WARNING: 1 failed login attempt<br>
sddm [1940] authentication information: “Login will be blocked after 50 attempts”<br>
sddm-helper-[4089]: pam_exec(sddm:auth): usr/libexec/security-misc/pam_faillocl_not_if_x failed: exit code 1<br>
sddm[1940]: Existing authentication ongoing, aborting</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_12</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 13:22:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1696</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>kernel: Low-power S0 idle used by default for system suspend<br>
kernel: nvme 0000:04:00.0: platform quirk: setting simple suspend<br>
kded5[2685]: kscreen.kded: PowerDevil SuspendSession action not available!<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[4816]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)<br>
kernel: printk: Suspending console(s) (use no_console_suspend to debug)<br>
kernel:  amdgpu_device_suspend+0x53/0x150 [amdgpu]<br>
kernel:  pci_pm_suspend+0x78/0x170<br>
kernel:  __device_suspend+0xf1/0x470<br>
kernel:  async_suspend+0x1a/0x80<br>
kernel: queueing ieee80211 work while going to suspend<br>
kernel: amd_pmc AMDI0009:00: Last suspend didn’t reach deepest state<br>
kernel: PM: suspend exit<br>
systemd[1]: systemd-suspend.service: Deactivated successfully.<br>
systemd[1]: Finished systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Reached target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Stopped target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[8743]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)<br>
kernel: printk: Suspending console(s) (use no_console_suspend to debug)<br>
kernel:  amdgpu_device_suspend+0x53/0x150 [amdgpu]<br>
kernel:  pci_pm_suspend+0x78/0x170<br>
kernel:  __device_suspend+0xf1/0x470<br>
kernel:  async_suspend+0x1a/0x80<br>
kernel: amd_pmc AMDI0009:00: Last suspend didn’t reach deepest state<br>
kernel: PM: suspend exit<br>
systemd[1]: systemd-suspend.service: Deactivated successfully.<br>
systemd[1]: Finished systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Reached target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd[1]: Stopped target suspend.target - Suspend.<br>
systemd-logind[1521]: The system will suspend now!<br>
ModemManager[1606]:   [sleep-monitor-systemd] system is about to suspend<br>
systemd[1]: Starting systemd-suspend.service - System Suspend…<br>
systemd-sleep[11869]: Entering sleep state ‘suspend’…<br>
kernel: PM: suspend entry (s2idle)</p>
<p>my friend’s journal. he has the most interesting situation in debian kde plasma - system does not want to go into sleep mode, desktop reboots only. then system started sleep mode and hung. He said he didnot notice any other errors in journal. but sleep mode error goes away immediately if you delete security-misc and reboot</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 13:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1694</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>There are many different options.</p>
<ul>
<li>F) BIOS power-on password</li>
<li>G) BIOS administrator password</li>
</ul>
<p>These can be different passwords. Administrator password can usually clear/change power-on password and is also allowed to boot.</p>
<p>In this discussion, I was revering to <code>F) BIOS power-on password</code>, a password that is required for every boot.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If the BIOS password prevents booting the machine too, then yes, it does do all of that already.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This was my assumption.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But in that situation a bootloader password isn’t all that useful, except as defense-in-depth against a relatively unskilled adversary. (Granted, most adversaries most of our users encounter will be relatively unskilled, and I can definitely imagine someone who can figure out a BIOS password reset via an article from the Internet but who can’t figure out how to get past a bootloader password.)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right. The the protection provided by the BIOS power-on password isn’t that great. It’s a “hardware magic feature”. Some BIOS can be reset with:</p>
<ul>
<li>recovery code provided by websites, and</li>
<li>removal of CMOS battery,</li>
<li>motherboard BIOS reset jumper.</li>
</ul>
<p>There might be some BIOS resistant to that, designed to not easily being reset, but that is dependent on the hardware producer and may be dependent on the BIOS settings.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The bootloader password is still valuable though, even against a non-technical attacker, if the passwords are being used to prevent bootup entirely.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>GRUB bootloader password to prevent all boot menu entries could be considered more secure than BIOS power-on password, because it’s not a “hardware magic feature” but instead a software feature implemented in Freedom Software, GRUB.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="7" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Obviously at this point an attacker with slightly more skill would insert a live USB into the victim machine and boot from that, but there are plenty of attackers who lack that skill, especially in domestic abuse situations, so this still seems valuable to me, even if the benefits are limited at best.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 11:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1692</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I think I see where I’m misunderstanding - I’m thinking of using BIOS and bootloader passwords specifically for preventing access to advanced configuration settings, i.e. the system can be <em>booted</em> without either password, but dropping to a GRUB shell or booting from an external drive using the BIOS should require one of the system passwords. In this context the passwords are only useful for preventing unauthorized root access and denying the ability to tamper with the system’s storage without removing the internal drive. Thus ability to gain root access on an unencrypted system has been the threat I’ve been considering most strongly. I think you’re thinking about these passwords being used to prevent even bootup, such that the system is essentially bricked unless you possess both BIOS and bootloader passwords. This way the passwords are used not just to prevent unauthorized root, but as a form of authentication to even use the system. We should decide on which one we’re discussing so that we’re both talking about the same thing.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Doesn’t a BIOS password alone already prevent all of that and requires taking out the drive or some other physical attack?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If the BIOS password only prevents getting into BIOS options, no, it does not. One simply has to drop to a GRUB console (trivially doable on many EFI systems by repeatedly pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> during bootup) and they can then boot any arbitrary OS by hand, including one provided on an external USB drive. Similarly, if you have a bootloader password but not BIOS password, you can trivially bypass it by booting from an external drive using the BIOS’s boot functionality. Only password-protecting both seriously complicates attacks that involve booting from an external drive.</p>
<p>If the BIOS password prevents booting the machine too, then yes, it does do all of that already. But in that situation a bootloader password isn’t all that useful, except as defense-in-depth against a relatively unskilled adversary. (Granted, most adversaries most of our users encounter will be relatively unskilled, and I can definitely imagine someone who can figure out a BIOS password reset via an article from the Internet but who can’t figure out how to get past a bootloader password.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Then surely the question will come up “in which cases it does not suffice?” The answer is most likely, in complex cases which are not applicable to the reader, because if these were applicable, the question would not come up. One case that can be constructed is some sort of corporate setup.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I think this is applicable to everyday users too though, whether you’re requiring passwords for bootup or for config access. Depending on the difficulty of opening a device, being forced to take the drive out of the machine to modify it is a very significant hurdle that an attacker may not have the opportunity to carry out (i.e. someone who gains physical access to a machine but only for a very short period of time, and who has to leave the machine more-or-less intact once their attack is complete, this is basically the classic evil maid scenario). Some machines even have soldered internal storage, especially cheap, lightweight devices like “HP Stream” and “onn.” machines - this makes this class of attack nearly impossible without access to advanced, expensive equipment for desoldering the storage chips and resoldering them onto something that allows reading and writing them.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A BIOS password alone will stop most non-technical attackers. More technical attackers who steal the hard drive would be stopped by FDE. That’s why BIOS password + FDE always seemed to be as the most important passwords.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The bootloader password is still valuable though, even against a non-technical attacker, if the passwords are being used to prevent bootup entirely. Many machines have a manufacturer-provided backdoor for resetting BIOS passwords, and tools for exploiting these backdoors are publicly available on the open Internet (<a href="https://bios-pw.org/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://bios-pw.org/</a> is a good example). For machines such as this, a non-technical attacker can probably bypass the BIOS password easily enough, but then they have the bootloader password to contend with. Obviously at this point an attacker with slightly more skill would insert a live USB into the victim machine and boot from that, but there are plenty of attackers who lack that skill, especially in domestic abuse situations, so this still seems valuable to me, even if the benefits are limited at best.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But a reboot will go through BIOS or are you referring to kexec? (I don’t know if GRUB can be load somehow using kexec.)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I meant a reboot that goes through BIOS. Assuming the system is not password-protected, you can easily gain a root shell on Kicksecure without the root or user passwords by following <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Recovery_Mode" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Recovery - Kicksecure</a>. An FDE password prevents this though.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In conclusion, the bootloader password seems to only make sense in niche cases.</p>
<ul>
<li>BIOS password bypass included in the threat model</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>corporate (alike) situations</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not necessarily.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="6" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>adversary taking out the hard drive and attempting to boot it in a different computer (circumventing BIOS password) (but then FDE would be much more important)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess sorta, though any attacker with the skill needed to move a drive between laptops probably also has the skill needed to boot a live USB to bypass the bootloader password. FDE would be much more important here, agreed.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1691</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Right. So similar to <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723/6" class="inline-onebox">Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password - #6 by Patrick</a> there could be a corporate setup use case.</p>
<p>A malicious employee could manage to corrupt some system files to then get a dracut recovery shell.</p>
<p>Or the complex VM related attack you’ve described.</p>
<p>We could set <code>rd.shell=0 rd.emergency=halt</code> in security-misc. (And then undo the setting in debug-misc, if not already the case.)</p>
<p>But we would only set it for <code>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</code> (default boot entry) or <code>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX</code> (all boot entries, including recovery boot entry)?</p>
<p>The kernel parameters <code>rd.shell=0 rd.emergency=halt</code> can be modified or unset from GRUB boot menu. But those who worry about that, can either set a BIOS password and/or a bootloader password, depending on their threat model.</p>
<p>Setting it for default (non-recovery) boot menu entries might makes sense. Because those who want to protect Linux recovery mode boot entries, need to set a GRUB root password anyhow.</p>
<p>Another related solution: <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/remove-linux-recovery-mode-boot-option-from-default-grub-boot-menu/727" class="inline-onebox">Remove Linux recovery mode boot option from default GRUB boot menu</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:13:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1690</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Remove Linux recovery mode boot option from default GRUB boot menu</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The default GRUB menu entry currently:</p>
<ul>
<li>sets: <code>loglevel=0 quiet</code></li>
</ul>
<p>The recovery mode GRUB menu entry</p>
<ul>
<li>does not set: <code>loglevel=0 quiet</code></li>
<li>sets <code>single</code></li>
</ul>
<p>That is not a massive difference.</p>
<p>Reasons for simplification:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-dracut-initramfs-generator-by-disabling-recovery-console/724" class="inline-onebox">Harden DRACUT initramfs-generator by disabling Recovery Console?</a> (we could disable dracut recovery console at the same time)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/boot_modes" class="inline-onebox">Role-Based Boot Modes (user versus admin) for Enhanced Security</a> (the more options, the more confusing and recovery mode might not be very important)</li>
</ul>
<p>Instead, for debugging, single user mode, dracut rescue shell we could instead document how to accomplish that on the <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery" class="inline-onebox">Recovery - Kicksecure</a> wiki page using <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub#Kernel_Boot_Parameter_Change">Kernel Boot Parameter Change</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/remove-linux-recovery-mode-boot-option-from-default-grub-boot-menu/727#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 15:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1689</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>If these should be fixed, please report a bug.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:40:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1688</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Harden GRUB bootloader using bootloader password</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>It might help to clarify under what situations a bootloader password provides a meaningful level of additional security.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>I am documenting that here: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Bootloader_Password">Bootloader Password</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>From my standpoint, you have to have at least a bootloader password, a root password, and a BIOS password for it to be useful at all (the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on, the bootloader password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting and entering recovery mode, and the BIOS password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting into an OS on an external drive).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doesn’t a BIOS password alone already prevent all of that and requires taking out the drive or some other physical attack?</p>
<p>Well, one could add the assumption that the adversary has a BIOS password bypass. Then the bootloader password might help. This might be an unrealistic assumption.</p>
<p>I think a BIOS password + FDE pre boot authentication password is sufficient “in most cases”.</p>
<p>Then surely the question will come up “in which cases it does not suffice?” The answer is most likely, in complex cases which are not applicable to the reader, because if these were applicable, the question would not come up. One case that can be constructed is some sort of corporate setup.</p>
<p>For example, an employee is given a BIOS password for booting from the internal hard drive, but not from other devices. Furthermore, the employee is allowed to boot using the standard/default option but prevented from booting the recovery boot option, because that password would be retained for system administrators only.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>(the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>That reminds me of, quote <a href="https://xkcd.com/1200/" class="inline-onebox">xkcd: Authorization</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>If someone steals my laptop while I’m logged in, they can read my email, take my money, and impersonate me to my friends, but at least they can’t install drivers without my permission.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But more seriously…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>(the root password keeps you from gaining privileges when powered on</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess it depends on the threat model. Physical attacks while powered on are always a very high risk situation.</p>
<p>I however was thinking of BIOS password, bootloader password, FDE password, Linux user password, Linux root/sudo password in terms physical attacks while the machine is powered off.</p>
<p>A BIOS password alone will stop most non-technical attackers. More technical attackers who steal the hard drive would be stopped by FDE. That’s why BIOS password + FDE always seemed to be as the most important passwords.</p>
<p>If a physical attacker gets to run (passwordless) sudo, as mentioned in the xkcd, I might not mind much, as most sensitive data is accessible already when logged in as user (not root).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the bootloader password keeps you from gaining privileges by rebooting</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But a reboot will go through BIOS or are you referring to kexec? (I don’t know if GRUB can be load somehow using kexec.)</p>
<p>Good, you could say not having a sudo password will allow a physical attacker to run kexec. But is that even still neeed? → xkcd</p>
<p>In that threat model that I am considering here now, physical attacks while powered are excluded. [1]</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="5" data-topic="723">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If you have passwordless sudo, you can just <code>sudo -i</code> and then remove the bootloader password or change bootloader config as you see fit. Granted, FDE would protect against that.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Right. I would exclude that form that threat model anyhow due to xkcd.</p>
<hr>
<p>In conclusion, the bootloader password seems to only make sense in niche cases.</p>
<ul>
<li>BIOS password bypass included in the threat model</li>
<li>corporate (alike) situations</li>
<li>adversary taking out the hard drive and attempting to boot it in a different computer (circumventing BIOS password) (but then FDE would be much more important)</li>
</ul>
<p>Please correct me if I am wrong. Happy to present the full threat model analysis in the wiki.</p>
<hr>
<p>[1] For physical attacks while powered on:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Protection_Against_Physical_Attacks#Screen_Lock">Screen Lock</a> (weak)</li>
<li><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/panic-button-panic-shutdown-buskill-the-usb-kill-cord-for-your-laptop/13755" class="inline-onebox">panic button / panic shutdown / BusKill - The USB kill cord for your laptop - Development - Whonix Forum</a> (ticket)</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/harden-grub-bootloader-using-bootloader-password/723#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1687</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I have not seen these problems in xfce. Only in Cinnamon and Kde Plasma. These problems are related to security-misc - removing package fixes these problems.<br>
I just shared observations for those who want to install a other desktop or another OS with Kicksecure</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 14:25:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1686</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="sam" data-post="7" data-topic="46">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/5f9b8f/48.png" class="avatar"> sam:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>These errors are in Debian,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If these error are happening on Debian without Kicksecure being involved, please report bugs against Debian.</p>
<p>If these error are happening on Kicksecure, please report bugs as per <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs" class="inline-onebox">Bug Reports, Software Development, and Feature Requests</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 13:53:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1685</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
