<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure Forums - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>How is Mullvad Browser supposed to be used in Qubes</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@cough]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>There is no .desktop file provided and putting /usr/bin/mulvadbrowser into a .desktop file also does not seem to work properly.</p>
<p>Only usable way is launching it in a terminal first then basing a dispvm on top of that appvm to use the generated .desktop file. But updating like that is a pain.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/how-is-mullvad-browser-supposed-to-be-used-in-qubes/1256#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 23:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3281</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@MetalMoxie]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Allow us to chose just like with the web browsers.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 21:38:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3277</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Packages Source for App-per-VM</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>What gets me about Android is how they do per-user storage, not global. I wish Debian’s APT did this but its limited due to the nature of its design.</p>
<p>I tried installing a <code>.deb</code> package locally with dpkg but it will always be system-wide unavoidly.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/packages-source-for-app-per-vm/1167#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 21:33:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3275</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Dual boot is not a good idea. If you want Kicksecure seperate from your OS <em>1.</em> use it in a VM or <em>2.</em> Install in on a external drive and boot into when you need to.</p>
<p>I dont know how you could go about stoping someone from installing a Duel Boot here?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot/1249#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 21:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3274</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>should be blocked or not blocked by default?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Webcams</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://thehackernews.com/2025/08/linux-based-lenovo-webcams-flaw-can-be.html" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://thehackernews.com/2025/08/linux-based-lenovo-webcams-flaw-can-be.html</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Microphones</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Same as webcams they can be used to record passwords and text via acoustic keyboard eavesdropping with tools like <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/kbd-audio" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Keytap2</a>. The best thing if someone was concerned would be to unplug these ribbon cables from their computer or de-solder them if its a newer (landfill device) where everything is soldered in.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>MIDI interfaces</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Arduinos can indeed be used as MIDI interfaces and are used in hacking peripheral devices</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Bluetooth dongles</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No brainer here Bluetooth is unsafe</p>
<hr>
<p>Thing I’m conflicted on here.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>USB Ethernet</p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="1" data-topic="1248">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I would consider this very high-risk and would NOT enable it.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I don’t get it considering there’s good amount of people that use them to get around Intel ME. Many people including myself would remove the WiFi card and us an external Ethernet USB Adapter as a mitigation technique.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Machines whose AMT version is 6.x (Q57/Q67/C206 chipsets, 2010-2011 (early 2012) Core i3/i5/i7) have ME that can talk only through the NIC that is soldered to the board, no external NIC will ever be visible to the ME.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s even debatable if it can communicate on newer device through an adapter in my opinion.</p>
<p>Not to mention people that only want wired many newer (landfill devices) computers require you to buy an USB adapter since they don’t seem to have them on boards anymore (laptops).</p>
<p>On the other hand external peripheral devices are generally no allowed by organizations and corporate companies due to attack vector with the exceptions of mouse and keyboard. Malicious USB ethernet devices exist but the general rule of thumb in this manner is don’t buy online and only buy locally from a trusted vendor (brand). Supply chain attack is a real threat but atleast is wouldn’t be targeted to you specifically unlike buying online.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 21:17:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3273</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>related:</p>
<aside class="onebox discoursetopic" data-onebox-src="https://forums.whonix.org/t/usbguard-on-kicksecure-to-prevent-hardware-keyloggers-badusb/11988">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/optimized/2X/3/37fe81e592143b0c01c9656c44069b4bfdd3990e_2_32x32.ico" class="site-icon" alt="" width="32" height="32">

      <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/usbguard-on-kicksecure-to-prevent-hardware-keyloggers-badusb/11988" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="05:04PM - 22 July 2021">Whonix Forum – 22 Jul 21</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/255;"><img src="https://forums.whonix.org/uploads/default/original/2X/5/5ac973ff4302e69269667e09e67d850c0b628c7a.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="255"></div>

<div class="title-wrapper">
  <h3><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/usbguard-on-kicksecure-to-prevent-hardware-keyloggers-badusb/11988" target="_blank" rel="noopener">USBGuard on Kicksecure to prevent hardware keyloggers/BadUSB</a></h3>
  <div class="topic-category">
      <span class="badge-wrapper bullet">
        <span class="badge-category-bg" style="background-color: #25AAE2;"></span>
        <span class="badge-category clear-badge">
          <span class="category-name">Development</span>
        </span>
      </span>
  </div>
</div>

  <p>“The USBGuard software framework helps to protect your computer against rogue USB devices (a.k.a. [BadUSB]) by implementing basic whitelisting and blacklisting capabilities based on device attributes.”  From their Github.  Maybe could help someone...</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Consider the impact of USBGuard in sys-usb</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-08-22" data-time="18:22:07" data-timezone="UTC">06:22PM - 22 Aug 25 UTC</span>
      </div>

        <div class="date">
          closed <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-08-23" data-time="00:42:19" data-timezone="UTC">12:42AM - 23 Aug 25 UTC</span>
        </div>

      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/104878738?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          ArrayBolt3
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          R: not applicable
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          P: default
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">[How to file a helpful issue](https://www.qubes-os.org/doc/issue-tracking/)

I a<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">pologize in advance if this isn't really the right spot for this, I couldn't find a "development" category on the forums so this is the closest I could figure out.

### The problem you're addressing (if any)

In Kicksecure 18 and higher, we're going to be shipping USBGuard, enabled by default, with a configuration that allows all devices that are present in the system on bootup, and blocks all non-whitelisted devices that are plugged in after bootup. By default, the whitelist in Kicksecure will allow USB mass storage devices, and will allow a single mouse and keyboard at a time (additional keyboards are rejected). All other devices are rejected, including devices that combine a USB mass storage interface with anything else, and devices that combine a keyboard or mouse interface with anything (except for "unified" keyboard/mouse devices like are common with some wireless receivers). The goal is to allow a limited subset of common USB devices to work out of the box, while also thwarting devices like the USB "rubber ducky".

This feature set makes good sense for Kicksecure on the desktop, but we're unsure if it makes sense in Qubes OS, if a user chooses to use Kicksecure on sys-usb. On the one hand, USBGuard in sys-usb could substantially increase the security of users who have to pass through USB keyboards and mice to dom0 (only one keyboard and mouse would be allowed, a keystroke injection device would be rejected so long as it was not present when sys-usb booted and a legitimate USB keyboard was already plugged in). On the other hand, USBGuard could frustrate users who need to work with things such as USB headsets, webcams, touchscreens, and other "advanced" devices. In theory a user could reboot sys-usb to get these devices to work (assuming our configuration actually does trust everything present on bootup), but maybe that's too much hassle?

The USBGuard configuration we intend to ship in Kicksecure 18 can be seen [here](https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/blob/master/etc/usbguard/rules.d/30_security-misc.conf).

### The solution you'd like

Determine if USBGuard in a Kicksecure-based sys-usb makes sense, and if any configuration changes are needed in the event it is useful in Qubes OS.

### The value to a user and who that user might be

If we choose to leave it enabled, users will be able to pass through input devices to dom0 with less risk of malicious devices being able to take over the system.

If we choose to disable it, users won't end up facing new issues with USB device passthrough.

### Completion criteria checklist

(This section is for developer use only. Please do not modify it.)</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/8820">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/8820" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/8820" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hardened option for single USB keyboard</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2024-01-02" data-time="12:29:26" data-timezone="UTC">12:29PM - 02 Jan 24 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/emanruse" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/40140013?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          emanruse
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          P: default
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          C: input proxy
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">### The problem you're addressing (if any)

Currently, on systems which can us<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">e only USB keyboards, it seems possible to have unrestricted number of such USB keyboards that are automatically allowed to connect to dom0 due to `/etc/qubes-rpc/policy/qubes.InputKeyboard` permissive policy. This makes it possible a malicious USB device (e.g. a USB memory stick) to represent itself as a keyboard, do its mischief, then switch back to being a non-keyboard.

Using usbguard inside sys-usb to allow only specific predefined keyboards is a possibility, however it might result in a situation when the user gets locked out of the system. Example: The user has only one physical keyboard and whitelists it in usbguard rules. If the keyboard hardware stops functioning (e.g. the keyboard is physically damaged), the user will be compelled to replace it with another. However, since the new keyboard will not be whitelisted, the user won't be able to access the system through it, regardless of the fact that it is a good (non-malicious) device.


### The solution you'd like

Provide an option (perhaps even enforced by default) which allows the user to restrict the number of possible USB keyboards on the system to 1 (one) at a time.


### The value to a user, and who that user might be

The proposed solution would make it impossible for a malicious device to act as described, as a second keyboard will be denied. The only way to use another USB keyboard would be to physically disconnect the first one, then connect another. That must also be documented properly.

#### Possible caveat

**I don't know if that is possible** (there are [some](https://forums.tomshardware.com/threads/every-usb-port-will-randomly-disconnect-for-a-few-seconds-on-new-pc.3793952/) [reports](https://superuser.com/questions/1450976/external-usb-hard-drive-momentarily-disconnects-when-additional-external-hard-dr)), but just for extra consideration:

If for some reason (e.g. a driver bug, power related issues or other) the malicious USB device is able to cause the original keyboard to (appear to) disconnect or simply "sneak in" while the original good keyboard is actually disconnected, the proposed solution will not work *per se* - the malicious device may still connect as a keyboard and accomplish the described attack, and during that period the actual keyboard will be blocked. To prevent such possibility, additional possible measures to the solution might be:

- Enable any newly connected USB keyboard **only after reboot**

In this way, even if a temporary disconnect happens, no other device would be able to take over a running the system, because to accomplish an attack the malicious device would have to cause a reboot of dom0 through sys-usb, which seems impossible in Qubes OS (at least not without a serious security bug).

- UI for easy whitelisting of newly connected keyboards (using usbguard rules in sys-usb)

Without other input device (e.g. at least a mouse able to click and confirm the newly connected keyboards), a possibility for user input might be the power button of the system. A service like `acpid` may be used to monitor for events. Example usage:

A new keyboard is connected. The UI dialog shows up and asks for confirmation. The user is required to press the power button of the system to activate the new keyboard, after which it gets whitelisted in `/etc/usbguard/rules`. The `acpid` service may probably run in a separate VM (sys-acpi), thus making it impossible for a malicious device to attack both sys-usb and sys-acpi. Having sys-acpi may even provide extra security, e.g. the number of presses within a period of time might be configurable, e.g. "must press 3 times within 10 seconds", and may serve as a "password" for allowing new USB devices.

**Additional notes**:

As by default passwordless root is enabled in VMs, whitelisting devices in sys-usb itself may turn out vulnerable. I don't know what inter-VM communication mechanism for this may be suitable but it seems better to isolate the "credentials" of devices - have another VM store and verify if a device is whitelisted, then report the result back to sys-usb.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 15:18:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3272</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>The workstation has stopped booting.</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>See also <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Recovery#Hard_Drive_Recovery">Hard Drive Recovery</a>.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/the-workstation-has-stopped-booting/1246#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 15:13:48 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3271</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li><strong>User documentation recommending against dual-boot / multi-boot:</strong> Wiki chapter <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/System_Configuration_and_Access#Use_a_Dedicated_Host_Operating_System_and_Computer">Use a Dedicated Host Operating System and Computer</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Security support:</strong> None required related specifically to dual/multi boot.</li>
<li><strong>Security impact:</strong> Almost entirely the same discussion as <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171" class="inline-onebox">No Rescue Mode</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Overhead from dual-boot / multi-boot technical/documentation/forum support requests:</strong> Non-existing at this point. I could not find any questions at this time on the topic of dual-boot / multi-boot support requests. If this were to happen minimal to no time would be spend on these requests as this is notoriously difficult to debug. This would most likely be redirected as per <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unspecific" class="inline-onebox">Potential Solutions Beyond Kicksecure!</a> and <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" class="inline-onebox">Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Developer use cases</strong>: These remain “supported” (as in “possible”) (as in developers can figure it out) without “support” from the project required. When Kicksecure is installed on standard Intel/AMD64 hardware, this feature is a by-product. There is nothing useful from a security point of view that we can do to stop “supporting” (meaning, this being possible) that feature.</li>
<li><strong>Future:</strong> As we make more progress towards <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot</a> (<a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/verified-boot-development-discussion/901" class="inline-onebox">Verified Boot - Development Discussion</a>), the issues discussed in <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/protecting-the-kernel-command-line/1251" class="inline-onebox">Protecting the Kernel Command Line</a> and <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/no-rescue-mode/1171" class="inline-onebox">No Rescue Mode</a> and this forum thread will organically be considered.</li>
<li><strong>Solution:</strong> Once hardware becomes available that supports <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Sovereign_Boot" class="inline-onebox">Sovereign Boot</a>, dual/multi boot security concerns can be addressed.</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot/1249#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 14:38:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3270</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Protecting the Kernel Command Line</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>new wiki chapter:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Verified_Boot#Protecting_the_Kernel_Command_Line">Protecting the Kernel Command Line</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/protecting-the-kernel-command-line/1251#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 14:31:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3269</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="1" data-topic="1248">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We don’t want to block so much that users disable USBGuard because they can’t live with it, but we also don’t want to allow so much that malicious devices work in common configurations.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If it were me, I wouldn’t have given this a second thought. If security requires disabling so much, then it is what it is.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="1" data-topic="1248">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>2FA keys</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Good to have.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="1" data-topic="1248">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Anything else we should consider allowing or not allowing by default?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Old bs stuff e.g:</p>
<ul>
<li>USB to VGA?</li>
<li>USB joysticks?</li>
<li>Consider to allow only 3 and above USB version?</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 08:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3267</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>This aligns with the OS/hardware relation, as I have pointed out (in “Operating System from Heaven”) the insecurity of having a separation between OS and hardware. There is another threat, which is having multiboot, as it poses stability and security issues.</p>
<p>So it’s like a path of a consistent, homogeneous methodology for security.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1249">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>multiboot may be very valuable for developer use cases</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>We should not have a single concern about what xyz wants to have on his laptop. Our concern is to deliver the best security possible for the end user while he’s using our OS/products. If something doesn’t work unless you allow insecurities, it is unsupported.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1249">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I for instance run a multiboot setup on my test laptop, Kubuntu/Lubuntu/Qubes OS/Debian/Arch.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The user is going to need to play with those on bare metal VM or emulator. Or buy insecure, testing purpose hardware (secure OS/hardware doesn’t support this).</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot/1249#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 07:42:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3266</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Might be worth drawing a line between “security support” and “technical support” here - multiboot may be very valuable for developer use cases (where all operating systems on the system are trusted equally). Such a setup may be discouraged from a security standpoint, but essential for development. I for instance run a multiboot setup on my test laptop, Kubuntu/Lubuntu/Qubes OS/Debian/Arch.</p>
<p>Qubes OS doesn’t <em>support</em> multiboot, but in practice it can be multibooted pretty easily.</p>
<p>Also, how would this interact with portable installations? They have some of the same risks, but may be very valuable because they can provide enhanced security even when a user has to use a machine that runs less secure operating systems other times.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot/1249#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 17:56:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3264</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unsupported Multi/Dual Boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Its not only can cause a usability issue as <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Troubleshooting#Dual_Boot">mentioned here</a>, but its a <a href="https://forum.qubes-os.org/t/multibooting-qubes/18988">security issue</a> as well:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One problem is that when you dual or multiboot, even if you are using encryption on your Qubes installation, /boot is still unprotected and could be maliciously modified by the other OS, possibly leading to Qubes itself being maliciously modified.</p>
<p>The other problem is firmware security - for example the other system could infect the BIOS firmware, which might enable compromise or spying on the Qubes system.</p>
</blockquote> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unsupported-multi-dual-boot/1249#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 17:29:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3263</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.mail-archive.com/qubes-devel@googlegroups.com/msg05626.html">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.mail-archive.com/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" alt="" width="16" height="16">

      <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/qubes-devel@googlegroups.com/msg05626.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">mail-archive.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/qubes-devel@googlegroups.com/msg05626.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">[qubes-devel] USBGuard in Kicksecure-based sys-usb?</a></h3>



  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 02:44:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3262</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>USBGuard - what should we allow or disallow by default?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Kicksecure 18 is intended to ship USBGuard by default, with a configuration that should block likely-malicious, unknown, and unusual devices. The hope is that it won’t block so much as to significantly increase the difficulty of using Kicksecure, while also making it more difficult to use devices such as the Hak5 rubber ducky or O.MG plug (popular keystroke injection devices).</p>
<p>Our current USBGuard configuration is visible at <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/blob/master/etc/usbguard/rules.d/30_security-misc.conf" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">security-misc/etc/usbguard/rules.d/30_security-misc.conf at master · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a>. The original intent was to allow everything connected at boot, and then disallow everything other than mass storage devices, keyboards, and mice, while also not allowing keyboards or mice to be combined with other interfaces, and not allowing additional keyboards and mice to be attached if one is already present. However, as pointed out by Marek (the lead Qubes OS developer), this is going to cause <em>tons</em> of legitimate devices to be blocked: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/commit/cba16879eff9d3d998c127e41c38d2067cdf04cc#r164474977" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Polish USBGuard configuration · Kicksecure/security-misc@cba1687 · GitHub</a></p>
<p>We have a pretty classic security vs. usability tradeoff here. We don’t want to block so much that users disable USBGuard because they can’t live with it, but we also don’t want to allow so much that malicious devices work in common configurations. It’s already risky enough allowing keyboards and mice to be attached after bootup, since if the only keyboard and mouse present on bootup is non-USB (as is the case with most laptops if you don’t plug additional devices into them), keystroke injection devices that present themselves as only a keyboard will be able to attack the system and succeed. But blocking <em>everything</em> other than keyboards, mice, and storage devices may be overkill also.</p>
<p>Does anyone have input on what should be blocked or not blocked by default? Some USB devices to think about here are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Webcams
<ul>
<li>On its own, a webcam probably can’t cause too much trouble… the worst it could do is video the user on the user’s own machine, it would probably be much more useful for an attacker to record the user with an <em>attacker-controlled</em> machine, which of course USBGuard can’t do anything about.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Microphones
<ul>
<li>Similar situation as webcams.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Headsets/speakers/miscellaneous other USB audio devices
<ul>
<li>Similar situation as webcams.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Printers
<ul>
<li>Could introduce attack surface that we don’t want, see <a href="https://www.evilsocket.net/2024/09/26/Attacking-UNIX-systems-via-CUPS-Part-I/" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Attacking UNIX Systems via CUPS, Part I</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>MIDI interfaces
<ul>
<li>Probably pretty rare, no idea what the risks are of allowing these to be used by default, would probably block them just in case.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Touchscreens
<ul>
<li>Input device, similar to a mouse, might even be handled already by allowing mice in the system. Dangers are similar or identical to allowing mice.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Android devices
<ul>
<li>Uses or at least used to use Media Transfer Protocol. Unsure what the risks are here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>USB Ethernet
<ul>
<li>Oftentimes uses RNDIS, which the Linux kernel maintainer Greg Kroah-Hartman has tried to get disabled in Linux at least <em>three times</em> due to supposedly unfixable security issues. (<a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-Disabling-RNDIS-Drivers" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-Disabling-RNDIS-Drivers</a>, <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-Disable-RNDIS-Drivers" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-Disable-RNDIS-Drivers</a>, <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-RNDIS-Removal-EOY2024" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-RNDIS-Removal-EOY2024</a>) I would consider this very high-risk and would NOT enable it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bluetooth dongles
<ul>
<li>Could be used to attach arbitrary devices to systems remotely, but this would require some user interaction. Unsure what the implications of a malicious Bluetooth dongle would be. Internal Bluetooth cards actually use the USB bus, but they’ll be present on boot and thus allowed, if everything works as expected.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>2FA keys
<ul>
<li>I believe these present themselves as a human interface device, not sure how safe or unsafe this is or if it’s feasible to allow it by default.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Anything else we should consider allowing or not allowing by default?</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/usbguard-what-should-we-allow-or-disallow-by-default/1248#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 02:33:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3261</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>The workstation has stopped booting.</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p><code>Failed to start systemd-fsck-root.service</code></p>
</blockquote>
<p>That sounds like the filesystem was corrupted by an improper shutdown (which would happen if the power went out). On the bright side, It’s very unlikely the filesystem is so corrupted that the data on it is inaccessible.</p>
<p>Probably the best course of action is to create a new virtual machine, then attach the old virtual machine’s disk to the new virtual machine. Then you can open the drive and copy your files to the new VM.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/the-workstation-has-stopped-booting/1246#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 01:45:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3260</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>The workstation has stopped booting.</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@amnez]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, after my power went out, I can’t log into WorkStation. When loading the system, the following errors are shown, which are visible on my screenshot. The data inside the system is very important to me, is there a way to extract it somehow?</p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/51d831ab6ec5ecd6b31b769d27cd3765cf0e2708.png" data-download-href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/51d831ab6ec5ecd6b31b769d27cd3765cf0e2708" title="{E32631A9-4D75-4B88-8006-F86712D9EFE1}"><img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/uploads/default/original/1X/51d831ab6ec5ecd6b31b769d27cd3765cf0e2708.png" alt="{E32631A9-4D75-4B88-8006-F86712D9EFE1}" data-base62-sha1="bG1RR8B644GIhqk3BB8RZlY6jgI" width="690" height="169" data-dominant-color="120D0D"></a></div><p></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/the-workstation-has-stopped-booting/1246#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 17:16:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3258</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/qubes-issues/issues/10174" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Consider the impact of USBGuard in sys-usb</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-08-22" data-time="18:22:07" data-timezone="UTC">06:22PM - 22 Aug 25 UTC</span>
      </div>

        <div class="date">
          closed <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-08-23" data-time="00:42:19" data-timezone="UTC">12:42AM - 23 Aug 25 UTC</span>
        </div>

      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/104878738?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          ArrayBolt3
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          R: not applicable
        </span>
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          P: default
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">[How to file a helpful issue](https://www.qubes-os.org/doc/issue-tracking/)

I a<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">pologize in advance if this isn't really the right spot for this, I couldn't find a "development" category on the forums so this is the closest I could figure out.

### The problem you're addressing (if any)

In Kicksecure 18 and higher, we're going to be shipping USBGuard, enabled by default, with a configuration that allows all devices that are present in the system on bootup, and blocks all non-whitelisted devices that are plugged in after bootup. By default, the whitelist in Kicksecure will allow USB mass storage devices, and will allow a single mouse and keyboard at a time (additional keyboards are rejected). All other devices are rejected, including devices that combine a USB mass storage interface with anything else, and devices that combine a keyboard or mouse interface with anything (except for "unified" keyboard/mouse devices like are common with some wireless receivers). The goal is to allow a limited subset of common USB devices to work out of the box, while also thwarting devices like the USB "rubber ducky".

This feature set makes good sense for Kicksecure on the desktop, but we're unsure if it makes sense in Qubes OS, if a user chooses to use Kicksecure on sys-usb. On the one hand, USBGuard in sys-usb could substantially increase the security of users who have to pass through USB keyboards and mice to dom0 (only one keyboard and mouse would be allowed, a keystroke injection device would be rejected so long as it was not present when sys-usb booted and a legitimate USB keyboard was already plugged in). On the other hand, USBGuard could frustrate users who need to work with things such as USB headsets, webcams, touchscreens, and other "advanced" devices. In theory a user could reboot sys-usb to get these devices to work (assuming our configuration actually does trust everything present on bootup), but maybe that's too much hassle?

The USBGuard configuration we intend to ship in Kicksecure 18 can be seen [here](https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/blob/master/etc/usbguard/rules.d/30_security-misc.conf).

### The solution you'd like

Determine if USBGuard in a Kicksecure-based sys-usb makes sense, and if any configuration changes are needed in the event it is useful in Qubes OS.

### The value to a user and who that user might be

If we choose to leave it enabled, users will be able to pass through input devices to dom0 with less risk of malicious devices being able to take over the system.

If we choose to disable it, users won't end up facing new issues with USB device passthrough.

### Completion criteria checklist

(This section is for developer use only. Please do not modify it.)</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_25</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 10:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3254</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Qubes Template Development - Qubes Integration</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/5920">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/5920" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/QubesOS/updates-status</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/QubesOS/updates-status/issues/5920" target="_blank" rel="noopener">qubes-template-kicksecure-17 4.2.0-202508121120 (r4.2)</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2025-08-12" data-time="11:20:53" data-timezone="UTC">11:20AM - 12 Aug 25 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/fepitre-bot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/48861364?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          fepitre-bot
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
        <span style="display:inline-block;margin-top:2px;background-color: #B8B8B8;padding: 2px;border-radius: 4px;color: #fff;margin-left: 3px;">
          r4.2-testing
        </span>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">Template kicksecure-17 4.2.0-202508121120 for Qubes OS r4.2, see comments below <span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">for details and build status.

If you're release manager, you can issue GPG-inline signed command (depending on template):

* `Upload-template r4.2 kicksecure-17 4.2.0-202508121120 templates-itl` (available 5 days from now)
* `Upload-template r4.2 kicksecure-17 4.2.0-202508121120 templates-community` (available 5 days from now)

Above commands will work only if package in testing repository isn't superseded by newer version.

For more information on how to test this update, please take a look at https://www.qubes-os.org/doc/testing/#updates.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-qubes-template-development-qubes-integration/679#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 08:51:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3251</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="onebox githubissue" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/184">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/184" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row">
  <div class="github-icon-container" title="Issue" data-github-private-repo="false">
	  <svg width="60" height="60" class="github-icon" viewBox="0 0 14 16" aria-hidden="true"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg>
  </div>

  <div class="github-info-container">
    <h4>
      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/issues/184" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MAC randomization breaks root server and VirtualBox DHCP / IPv6PrivacyExtensions might be problematic</a>
    </h4>

    <div class="github-info">
      <div class="date">
        opened <span class="discourse-local-date" data-format="ll" data-date="2024-01-06" data-time="13:11:20" data-timezone="UTC">01:11PM - 06 Jan 24 UTC</span>
      </div>


      <div class="user">
        <a href="https://github.com/adrelanos" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
          <img alt="" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/1985040?v=4" class="onebox-avatar-inline" width="20" height="20">
          adrelanos
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div class="labels">
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

  <div class="github-row">
    <p class="github-body-container">https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/blob/master/usr/lib/NetworkManager/c<span class="show-more-container"><a href="" rel="noopener" class="show-more">…</a></span><span class="excerpt hidden">onf.d/80_randomize-mac.conf

```
[device-mac-randomization]
wifi.scan-rand-mac-address=yes

[connection-mac-randomization]
ethernet.cloned-mac-address=random
wifi.cloned-mac-address=random
```

1) Breaks root servers, namely broke kicksecure.com. This is what the server provide sent by e-mail.

```
We have detected that your server is using different MAC addresses from those allowed by your Robot account.

Please take all necessary measures to avoid this in the future and to solve the issue.
We also request that you send a short response to us. This response should contain information about how this could have happened and what you intend to do about it.
In the event that the following steps are not completed successfully, your server can be locked at any time after 2024-01-17 16:51:11 +0100.

How to proceed:
- Solve the issue
- Please note, in case you have fixed the problem, please wait at least 10 minutes before rechecking: ...
- After successfully testing that the issue is resolved, send us a statement by using the following link:...

Please visit our FAQ here, if you are unsure how to proceed:
https://docs.hetzner.com/robot/dedicated-server/faq/error-faq/#mac-errors

Important note:
When replying to us, please leave the abuse ID [...] unchanged in the subject line. Manual replies will only be handled in the event of a lock.
Please note that we do not provide telephone support in our department. If you have any questions, please send them to us by responding to this email.

Kind regards

Network department
```

2) Breaks VirtualBox DHCP when using Network Manger (in Kicksecure) after VM reboot (`sudo reboot`). It is functional for the first start after powering off and powering on the VM. [1]

Might be related:
https://forums.virtualbox.org/viewtopic.php?t=86753

Could be a Network Manager issue:
https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/network-manager/+bug/1116421
https://askubuntu.com/questions/307717/networkmanager-problem-with-cloned-mac-address

----

[1] Before someone says that's a VirtualBox issue, no, I mean, maybe, but that doesn't matter.
VirtualBox is a valid environment. If that breaks, other environments will break as well.
Broken networking is extremely frustrating. MAC randomization would be suitable for Kicksecure, but only if stable.

It's not important enough to break common network configurations in common environments.

----

TODO: This bug has to be reported to Network Manager (NM) as above bug reports apparently never have reached upstream NM.</span></p>
  </div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
 ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 05:31:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3250</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Could you share a screenshot of the livecheck window so I can see the message you’re getting?</p>
<p>Yes, I am sure it works either the same or better than previously. The previous live mode implementation simply used a Dracut module to mount the root filesystem read-only, then put an in-memory overlay on it. That meant that any filesystem mounted thereafter (like /boot, /boot/efi, /home if you installed it on a separate partition, etc.) would still be read-write. The thing that changed is that livecheck now detects these other writable filesystems and reports about them, and a new service (live-hardener) attempts to remount more filesystems read-only and then mounts in-memory overlays on them. The original, dracut-based root overlay is still in place, so worst-case-scenario, live mode works as good or better than it used to.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_11</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 02:34:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3249</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Jac]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Previously it was Persistent Mode Active: no, but now it shows<br>
Persistent Mode Active: Yes (writable filesystems are mounted). Are you sure it works the same as before?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_10</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3248</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ricardo.martinez]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>After reading your response, and quicksilver’s response, I checked again with</p>
<p>[ -f /proc/net/if_inet6 ] &amp;&amp; echo ‘IPv6 ready system!’ || echo ‘No IPv6 support found!’</p>
<p>Apparently ipv6 is enabled, so now I think the issue I am having with reticulum may be related to apparmor blocking access to my wifi/ethernet for the app.</p>
<p>I think I may need to create an apparmor profile for reticulum</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 14:41:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3247</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Reproduced issue on Kicksecure 17.4.4.6 using VirtualBox with EFI enabled.</p>
<p>Looks like the issue is that live-hardener tries to remount <code>/boot/efi</code> read-only after it mounts a read-write overlay on <code>/boot</code>. Mounts don’t “show through” an overlayfs, so <code>/boot/efi</code> isn’t even accessible in live mode, and remounting <code>/boot/efi</code> doesn’t do anything in this situation.</p>
<p>Created a fix at <a href="https://github.com/ArrayBolt3/grub-live/tree/arraybolt3/live-hardener-fix" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - ArrayBolt3/grub-live at arraybolt3/live-hardener-fix</a> which is pending review. I’m unsure if this will end up in Kicksecure 17 or if it will have to wait until Kicksecure 18, but there’s a known fix now.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 16:00:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3246</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>You should be able to keep using live mode without issues. The warning you see isn’t because something broke that wasn’t broken before, but because hardening features we added to make live mode more effective aren’t fully working. At worst, live mode should be at least as effective as how it used to work (assuming the only directory livecheck warns about is /boot/efi).</p>
<p>I’ll continue looking into this to see if I can find the bug.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 02:23:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3244</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Jac]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="6" data-topic="1221">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>live-hardener</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Thanks for your reply. Rebooting does not solve the problem. I don’t know what to do. Real-time mode is very important for me. Version 17.3.9.9. worked without problems on my computer.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3243</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure distro specific keyboard shortcuts</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I just wanted to say I like these ideas very much.<br>
The windows superkey for menu and lockscreen shortcut being the ones I like the most.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-distro-specific-keyboard-shortcuts/1147#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 18:06:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3241</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Very nice work arraybolt3</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994?page=2#post_24</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 18:03:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3240</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Firewall</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The only issue from research is I’m not sure how you would go about enabling the custom ruleset by default?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-firewall/378#post_17</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 18:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3239</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Firewall</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Add Firewall option to sysmaint pannel</li>
</ul>
<p>I think the best way would be to add nftables rules sets for different usecases but the default being blocking incoming and forwarding and allow outgoing by default.</p>
<p>Another menu in sysmaint panel for firewalls could be added to select or manage firewall rulesets.</p>
<p><code>/etc/nftables/kicksecure_default.nft</code></p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">#!/usr/sbin/nft -f

table inet filter {
    chain input {
        type filter hook input priority 0;
        policy drop;
    }

    chain forward {
        type filter hook forward priority 0;
        policy drop;
    }

    chain output {
        type filter hook output priority 0;
        policy accept;
    }
}
</code></pre>
<p>Another example these rules Blocks all incoming and forwarding traffic and allows HTTP, HTTPS, DNS, and limited SSH traffic. Also allows Tor port to ensure it continues to work correctly for torified apt and time sync via sdwdate.</p>
<p><code>/etc/nftables/kicksecure_restrictive.nft</code></p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">#!/usr/sbin/nft -f

table inet filter {
    chain input {
        type filter hook input priority 0;
        policy drop;

        # Allow loopback interface
        iif "lo" accept

        # Allow established connections
        ct state {established, related} accept
    }

    chain forward {
        type filter hook forward priority 0;
        policy drop;

        # Allow established connections
        ct state {established, related} accept
    }

    chain output {
        type filter hook output priority 0;
        policy drop;

        # Allow loopback interface
        oif "lo" accept

        # Allow HTTP (port 80)
        tcp dport 80 accept

        # Allow HTTPS (port 443)
        tcp dport 443 accept

        # Allow DNS (port 53)
        udp dport 53 accept
        tcp dport 53 accept

        # Allow SSH (port 22) but limit it to a specific number of connections per minute
        tcp dport 22 limit rate 5/minute accept

        # Allow Tor (port 9050)
        tcp dport 9050 accept
    }
}
</code></pre> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-firewall/378#post_16</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3238</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1231">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>On my end, IPv6 is enabled by default.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>As far as I can tell IPv6 isn’t disabled in 40_kernel_hardnening.cfg (commented out) so it should be enabled? If it is not specifically disabled then IPv6 Privacy should be enabled by default by Kicksecure in my opinion I’m not quite sure why its not (maybe something related to virtual box)?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 17:56:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3237</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="ricardo.martinez" data-post="1" data-topic="1231">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/r/8baadc/48.png" class="avatar"> ricardo.martinez:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>should I take any additional security/privacy measures if I decide to enable it?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, you should enable IPv6 privacy extensions these aren’t enabled by default but are optional for you to un-comment if you need them. <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/03/22/legacy_ipv6_addressing_standard_enables/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">IPv6 has privacy issues by default as it relates to MAC Address in the addresses it uses</a></p>
<aside class="onebox githubrepo" data-onebox-src="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc?tab=readme-ov-file#network-hardening">
  <header class="source">

      <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc?tab=readme-ov-file#network-hardening" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">github.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="github-row" data-github-private-repo="false">
  <img width="690" height="344" src="https://opengraph.githubassets.com/b327564ef54f3f145ee509c167ab4dca/Kicksecure/security-misc?tab=readme-ov-file#network-hardening" class="thumbnail">

  <h3><a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc?tab=readme-ov-file#network-hardening" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/security-misc: Kernel Hardening; Protect Linux User Accounts...</a></h3>

    <p><span class="github-repo-description">Kernel Hardening; Protect Linux User Accounts against Brute Force Attacks; Improve Entropy Collection; Strong Linux User Account Separation; Enhances Misc Security Settings - https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Security-misc</span></p>
</div>

  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>What you need to do to enable is you need to un-comment # <code>ipv6.ip6-privacy=2</code> in <code>/usr/lib/NetworkManager/conf.d/80_ipv6-privacy.conf</code></p>
<p>and <code>IPv6PrivacyExtensions=kernel</code> and <code>/usr/lib/systemd/networkd.conf.d/80_ipv6-privacy-extensions.conf</code> to enable “Privacy Extensions”.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 17:55:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3236</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Firewall</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="SteveK1978" data-post="14" data-topic="378" data-full="true">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/s/8491ac/48.png" class="avatar"> SteveK1978:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I don’t think Tor is necessary for Kicksecure. We can have everything Tor into a separate package and allow user to not install it by default.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not planned due to:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/About#torified_updates">Protection from Targeted Malicious Updates</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-firewall/378#post_15</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 16:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3235</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Illegal instruction (core dumped)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/illegal-instruction-core-dumped/556#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:17:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3234</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Illegal instruction (core dumped)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I used * because I forgot the name of the file. And comment everyline that may disable SMT/AVX/AES with #, save it, exit. Then execute <code>update-grub</code> command, then reboot.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/illegal-instruction-core-dumped/556#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:17:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3233</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Avoid clearnet traffic in Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I recommend you to have a dedicated machine as gateway or just use Whonix</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/avoid-clearnet-traffic-in-kicksecure/1055#post_7</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3232</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure Firewall</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>We can have per-application level firewall control. I am currently using Kicksecure as virtual machines. I don’t think Tor is necessary for Kicksecure. We can have everything Tor into a separate package and allow user to not install it by default.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-firewall/378#post_14</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:12:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3230</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>OpenBSD’s malloc as hardened malloc alternative?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@SteveK1978]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thank you!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/openbsd-s-malloc-as-hardened-malloc-alternative/386#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:08:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3229</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>That’s weird then… if live-hardener ran, /boot/efi should not be writable when booted in live mode. I’d see if the problem automatically goes away after a reboot (if you haven’t already). If it doesn’t, there’s probably a bug in live-hardener.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 22:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3227</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Jac]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>[root ~]# systemctl status live-hardener.service<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only &gt;<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset&gt;<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, &gt;<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point no&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more in&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hard&gt;<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)…skipping…<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset: enabled)<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mkdir --parents – /var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_re&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -t overlay overlay -o lowerdir=/boot -o upperdir&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -o remount,ro – /boot/efi<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on t&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point not mounted or bad option.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more information after failed mount system call.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Non-zero exit code.<br>
~</p>
<p>~<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)…skipping…<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset: enabled)<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mkdir --parents – /var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/work<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -t overlay overlay -o lowerdir=/boot -o upperdir=/var/lib/grub-live/ove&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -o remount,ro – /boot/efi<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point not mounted or bad option.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more information after failed mount system call.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Non-zero exit code.<br>
~</p>
<p>~<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)…skipping…<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset: enabled)<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mkdir --parents – /var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/work<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -t overlay overlay -o lowerdir=/boot -o upperdir=/var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/upper -o wor&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -o remount,ro – /boot/efi<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point not mounted or bad option.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more information after failed mount system call.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Non-zero exit code.<br>
~<br>
~<br>
~<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)…skipping…<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset: enabled)<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mkdir --parents – /var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/work<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -t overlay overlay -o lowerdir=/boot -o upperdir=/var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/upper -o workdir=/var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo&gt;<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -o remount,ro – /boot/efi<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point not mounted or bad option.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more information after failed mount system call.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Non-zero exit code.<br>
~</p>
<p>~<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)…skipping…<br>
● live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them<br>
Loaded: loaded (/lib/systemd/system/live-hardener.service; enabled; preset: enabled)<br>
Active: active (exited) since Fri 2025-08-15 00:30:18 EDT; 23min ago<br>
Docs: <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/grub-live" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/grub-live: optional grub live boot menu entry as second option https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live</a><br>
Process: 1137 ExecStart=/usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
Main PID: 1137 (code=exited, status=0/SUCCESS)<br>
CPU: 107ms</p>
<p>Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mkdir --parents – /var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/work<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -t overlay overlay -o lowerdir=/boot -o upperdir=/var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/upper -o workdir=/var/lib/grub-live/overlay_tmpfs_repo/2/work – /boot<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Success.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: executing: mount -o remount,ro – /boot/efi<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost systemd[1]: Finished live-hardener.service - Remounts auxiliary writable filesystems as read-only and applies a tmpfs overlay on them.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]: mount: /boot/efi: mount point not mounted or bad option.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1369]:        dmesg(1) may have more information after failed mount system call.<br>
Aug 15 00:30:18 localhost live-hardener[1137]: /usr/libexec/grub-live/live-hardener: INFO: Non-zero exit code.<br>
~</p>
<p>~<br>
lines 1-18/18 (END)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:37:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3225</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Can you share the output of <code>systemctl status live-hardener.service</code>?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 03:35:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3224</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Jac]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hello, I have a similar problem, after installing the new version of KickSecure, in live mode, I get a red icon in the upper right part of the screen. How to solve this problem? (The system is installed on the main hard drive). I am a newbie and I do not understand how to fix this</p>
<p>Live Mode Active: Yes (grub-live semi-persistent)<br>
Persistent Mode Active: Yes (writable filesystems are mounted)</p>
<p>Changes to the system should be lost after a reboot, but this is not guaranteed.</p>
<ul>
<li>The following removable media directories have a writable filesystem mounted to them:<br>
*none</li>
<li>The following directories have an unexpected writable filesystem mounted to them:</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>/boot/efi<br>
You should unmount all of the above listed directories to ensure changes made will not persist through a reboot.</li>
</ul> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 03:22:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3223</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="ricardo.martinez" data-post="1" data-topic="1231">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/r/8baadc/48.png" class="avatar"> ricardo.martinez:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>When I checked if IPv6 was enabled in Kicksecure, it says it is not.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>How exactly did you check? On my end, IPv6 is enabled by default. Your network needs to support it for it to work obviously, but if your network supports IPv6, Kicksecure should just use IPv6 by default.</p>
<p>(Note that if you’re using Kicksecure in KVM, it’s very possibly IPv6 won’t be working for you. It looks like however libvirt/QEMU handles networking, IPv6 doesn’t work out of the box, at least not on an Ubuntu host. That’s and example the network not supporting IPv6.)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 02:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3220</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about IPv6</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ricardo.martinez]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hey everyone! I am not sure if this the best place to post this, so if it is not, sorry in advance.</p>
<p>I am trying to configure reticulum which is a new kind of decentralized network and it auto connects over IPv6 to other nodes on the network.</p>
<p>When I checked if IPv6 was enabled in Kicksecure, it says it is not.</p>
<p>Reading the docs, I found this on the DNS security page:<br>
/wiki/DNS_Security</p>
<p>" * The user’s computer has a local IPv6 but no actual IPv6 connectivity which might confuse DNS resolvers such as <code>unbound</code>."</p>
<p>My question is: is it safe to enable IPv6?</p>
<p>Why is turned off by default, and should I take any additional security/privacy measures if I decide to enable it?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-ipv6/1231#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:51:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3217</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The current live mode detection code isn’t Veracrypt-volume aware, so it can’t tell the difference between a container located on an ephemeral live filesystem, and a container located on a writable disk device. It just sees that you have a writable mounted device and warns you about it.</p>
<p>It might be possible to add code that is aware of Veracrypt volumes, but that would only make it work with Veracrypt specifically. There are a lot of applications that may mount a writable container that our code would have to be aware of, so in general this isn’t an easy problem to solve.</p>
<p>If the container itself is located on an ephemeral filesystem, then your writes to it should disappear on reboot, just like with any file on the ephemeral filesystem.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 22:33:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3207</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Question about grub-live and writable file system</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@whkicks]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>When I mount a Veracrypt container inside a grub-live session. The I get the red warning that there is a writable file system mounted.</p>
<p>Is there a chance that traces are left on my disk now? How does this work? The whole veracrypt container is written to disk? The files are? Are there no traces. Please clarify</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/question-about-grub-live-and-writable-file-system/1221#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 22:20:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3206</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>About new Kernel</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="InTheAir" data-post="1" data-topic="1219">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/278dde/48.png" class="avatar"> InTheAir:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Is this system secure or is more vulnerable?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It depends on how promptly the Debian kernel backporters update the kernel. The backported kernel doesn’t get official security support from Debian to my awareness like the stable kernel does, but people use backports kernels to I assume they’re maintained.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="InTheAir" data-post="1" data-topic="1219">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/278dde/48.png" class="avatar"> InTheAir:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>When kicksecure will use this kernel in the stable repository?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It probably won’t. We’re using kernels directly from Debian’s repository, and Debian won’t be upgrading past Linux 6.1 in Bookworm (instead, they will backporting bug and security fixes to the older kernel as appropriate). However, a significantly newer kernel will be present by default in Kicksecure 18, which will be based on Debian Trixie.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="InTheAir" data-post="1" data-topic="1219">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/i/278dde/48.png" class="avatar"> InTheAir:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Should I now remove this file: /etc/apt/sources.list.d/backports.list ?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>No, you need that to get kernel updates for the backported kernel.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/about-new-kernel/1219#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 20:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3205</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>About new Kernel</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@InTheAir]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi.</p>
<p>I’m installing kicksecure in a new laptop. The network wasn’t working and I’ve tried installing drivers but no luck. The only thing that has worked is installing a different version of the kernel and now the wifi is working fine.</p>
<p>For the installation of the new kernel I’ve followed this:<br>
kicksecure(.)com/wiki/Kernel#Package_Installation</p>
<p>Now this command <code>uname -r</code> give me this: <code>6.12.38+deb12-amd64</code></p>
<p>The questions:<br>
Is this system secure or is more vulnerable?<br>
When kicksecure will use this kernel in the stable repository?<br>
Should I now remove this file: /etc/apt/sources.list.d/backports.list ?<br>
I think not, but I guess that I should remove it only when the kernel I need is in the stable repository…</p>
<p>Thanks</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/about-new-kernel/1219#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 19:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3203</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live mode option boots into persistent sysmaint</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>No problem, it is a significant departure from the old behavior and I can definitely see how it can be confusing. (We changed how the live indicator worked too since the old one was Xfce-specific and we wanted a desktop-agnostic indicator instead, so that’s why the indicator moved.) Glad I was able to help!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-option-boots-into-persistent-sysmaint/1216#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 23:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3201</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Live mode option boots into persistent sysmaint</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@jma197]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Ah, my bad, so I was confused! Clicking the green indicator in the top right shows that is in Live mode and not persistent.</p>
<p>I’m so sorry to have wasted your time with this, I didn’t read into the update much at all and was going off past indicators. Thank you again for explaining the changes!</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/live-mode-option-boots-into-persistent-sysmaint/1216#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 22:18:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-3200</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
