<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Noob questions about sudo and suid, CLI vs. GUI</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99</link>
    <description>I am evaluating Kicksecure for my desktop.  I have some initial questions that I hope someone can answer:

- Is it possible to use Kicksecure without enabling sudo for any users without loss of normal functionality?  In other words, rely entirely on the rescue/recovery boot option to do any root operations like apt upgrade, etc.?  Without the logged in user even being a member of privileged groups like wheel?  I know doing so would be inconvenient.  But I&#39;m wondering if there are activities Kicksecure expects of users that require sudo.

- Is there a place where one can put suid exes (not root-owned, and chattr +i&#39;ed to prevent modification) that is safe from suid-prevention scripts and/or mount nosuid points?  I plan to use multiple system user accounts controlled by suid exes, but I read that either Kicksecure currently checks or will in the near future check to prevent suids.

- I plan on using bwrap for sandboxing.  Does anyone in the Kicksecure community have opinions as to whether it should be installed and used suid with unprivileged namespaces disabled, or non-suid with unprivileged namespaces enabled?  I&#39;m on the fence about this.  The biggest difference in functionality is that without unprivileged namespaces, there is no way to nest bwrap sandboxes.  But I read that enabling unprivileged namespaces is risky.

- I am considering starting with CLI Kicksecure and installing my own GUI configuration in order to sandbox Xorg and other parts of the desktop (a Qubes-like setup with sandboxes instead of VMs).  What packages of the GUI Kicksecure should I consider after doing this, and are they separated enough from the standard XFCE install to use without it?  Or am I better off starting with the XFCE GUI Kicksecure and retrofitting sandboxes?

Thanks in advance for any help with these questions!</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 20:40:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Noob questions about sudo and suid, CLI vs. GUI</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ike]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Further study shows:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>. /etc/permission-hardening.d controls what execs don’t lose suid due to kicksecure additions.  There appears to be an expectation that user entries would be added to /etc/permission-hardening.d/20_user.conf.  OK!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>bwrap is in /etc/permission-hardening.d so as to retain suid, but /proc/sys/kernel/unprivileged_userns_clone is 1.  But, bwrap is not installed with suid.  I guess that the kicksecure developers don’t have a conclusion about whether it should or should not be suid, and are allowing user preference.  Is that correct?  I see that chrome-sandbox is set up similarly.</p>
</li>
</ul>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99/2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 20:40:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-99-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99.rss">Noob questions about sudo and suid, CLI vs. GUI</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Noob questions about sudo and suid, CLI vs. GUI</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ike]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am evaluating Kicksecure for my desktop.  I have some initial questions that I hope someone can answer:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Is it possible to use Kicksecure without enabling sudo for any users without loss of normal functionality?  In other words, rely entirely on the rescue/recovery boot option to do any root operations like apt upgrade, etc.?  Without the logged in user even being a member of privileged groups like wheel?  I know doing so would be inconvenient.  But I’m wondering if there are activities Kicksecure expects of users that require sudo.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Is there a place where one can put suid exes (not root-owned, and chattr +i’ed to prevent modification) that is safe from suid-prevention scripts and/or mount nosuid points?  I plan to use multiple system user accounts controlled by suid exes, but I read that either Kicksecure currently checks or will in the near future check to prevent suids.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I plan on using bwrap for sandboxing.  Does anyone in the Kicksecure community have opinions as to whether it should be installed and used suid with unprivileged namespaces disabled, or non-suid with unprivileged namespaces enabled?  I’m on the fence about this.  The biggest difference in functionality is that without unprivileged namespaces, there is no way to nest bwrap sandboxes.  But I read that enabling unprivileged namespaces is risky.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I am considering starting with CLI Kicksecure and installing my own GUI configuration in order to sandbox Xorg and other parts of the desktop (a Qubes-like setup with sandboxes instead of VMs).  What packages of the GUI Kicksecure should I consider after doing this, and are they separated enough from the standard XFCE install to use without it?  Or am I better off starting with the XFCE GUI Kicksecure and retrofitting sandboxes?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Thanks in advance for any help with these questions!</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 19:49:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-99-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/noob-questions-about-sudo-and-suid-cli-vs-gui/99.rss">Noob questions about sudo and suid, CLI vs. GUI</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
