<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Printer Troubles</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236</link>
    <description>Hello.

I am having troubles connecting to my Brother HL-L2350DW WiFi printer (no USB; it&#39;s a laptop).  I just installed Kicksecure, so I am trying to figure out *why* my LibreOffice documents won&#39;t print.  I installed the `system-config-printer` app to connect to my printer.  I asked the Debian community in another forum what packages I&#39;m missing.  They told me to install some packages from the Debian repos (which they kindly provided), and I obliged.  My printer *does show up* in the Printer Config app under the Network section when you try to add a printer.

But I cannot connect to it.  Everytime I think I have made a successful connection to my Brother printer, I cannot print a test page.  So I delete the entry and start over again!

I either get 2 things:  The previously mentioned &quot;successful connection&quot;, OR this error message POP-UP `CUPS server error. There was an error during the CUPS operation: &#39;server-error-internal-error&#39;.`

I have tried disabling CUPS&#39;s AppArmor profiles into complain mode, but still no avail!

I have even tried this solution with Brother&#39;s official &quot;.deb&quot; printer package:

httpswwwlinuxquestionsorgquestions/linux-hardware-18/installation-of-brother-printer-drivers-and-device-uri-number-4175698450

I ultimately believe I am fundamentally encountering a skill issue:  I do not adequately know how to troubleshoot printer problems on Linux.  I don&#39;t know where to look on my system!  Is it `/var/logs`??  Do I look there?  I know my printer **DOES WORK** because I have successfully printed a CUPS Test Page from Linux Mint.  I just did that 4 weeks ago!

Please help me.  Debian *or* Kicksecure is kicking my ass.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 02:50:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Printer Troubles</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[moar.secur]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thank you for your reply.</p>
<p>I will try to reproduce this error on a vanilla Debian install.</p>
<p>Thank you for suggesting journalctl.  I will try to Scooby Doo this further.</p>
<p>Like, tyvm for replying.  I am very aware this is a small forum and just receiving a reply is reward enough.  Thank you!</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 02:50:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-236-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236.rss">Printer Troubles</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Printer Troubles</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I don’t know that either. That stuff can be tough.</p>
<p>This is a small forum and I guess unfortunately it’s unlikely someone will be able to help with such a specific issue.</p>
<p>The boilerplate reply in these case:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<ol>
<li> → Issue reproducible on Debian? →  <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Self_Support_First_Policy" class="inline-onebox">Self Support First Policy for Kicksecure</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<ol start="2">
<li> → Issue not happening in Debian but only in Kicksecure? <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Reporting_Bugs#Generic_Bug_Reproduction">Generic Bug Reproduction in Kicksecure wiki</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="moar.secur" data-post="1" data-topic="236">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/m/df705f/48.png" class="avatar"> moar.secur:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I don’t know where to look on my system! Is it <code>/var/logs</code>??</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Could be.</p>
<p>Mostly journalctl nowadays for systems based on systemd. → <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Troubleshooting#System_Logs">Troubleshooting - Kicksecure chapter System Logs in Kicksecure wiki</a></p>
<p>But printer specific log files could be elsewhere.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 11:33:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-236-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236.rss">Printer Troubles</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Printer Troubles</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[moar.secur]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello.</p>
<p>I am having troubles connecting to my Brother HL-L2350DW WiFi printer (no USB; it’s a laptop).  I just installed Kicksecure, so I am trying to figure out <em>why</em> my LibreOffice documents won’t print.  I installed the <code>system-config-printer</code> app to connect to my printer.  I asked the Debian community in another forum what packages I’m missing.  They told me to install some packages from the Debian repos (which they kindly provided), and I obliged.  My printer <em>does show up</em> in the Printer Config app under the Network section when you try to add a printer.</p>
<p>But I cannot connect to it.  Everytime I think I have made a successful connection to my Brother printer, I cannot print a test page.  So I delete the entry and start over again!</p>
<p>I either get 2 things:  The previously mentioned “successful connection”, OR this error message POP-UP <code>CUPS server error. There was an error during the CUPS operation: 'server-error-internal-error'.</code></p>
<p>I have tried disabling CUPS’s AppArmor profiles into complain mode, but still no avail!</p>
<p>I have even tried this solution with Brother’s official “.deb” printer package:</p>
<p>httpswwwlinuxquestionsorgquestions/linux-hardware-18/installation-of-brother-printer-drivers-and-device-uri-number-4175698450</p>
<p>I ultimately believe I am fundamentally encountering a skill issue:  I do not adequately know how to troubleshoot printer problems on Linux.  I don’t know where to look on my system!  Is it <code>/var/logs</code>??  Do I look there?  I know my printer <strong>DOES WORK</strong> because I have successfully printed a CUPS Test Page from Linux Mint.  I just did that 4 weeks ago!</p>
<p>Please help me.  Debian <em>or</em> Kicksecure is kicking my ass.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236/1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 21:26:35 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-236-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/printer-troubles/236.rss">Printer Troubles</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
