<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Getting some strange errors in Whonix on a new PC</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/getting-some-strange-errors-in-whonix-on-a-new-pc/748</link>
    <description>I&#39;ve been using Whonix which is based on Kicksecure for many years but I just got a new PC and now I&#39;m having problems booting it in VirtualBox. I tried posting this on the Whonix forums but they suggested I ask here.

Sometimes it will boot correctly and sometimes it will get stuck. I&#39;m often seeing strange errors/warnings around where it gets stuck which could be related. Unfortunately this forum won&#39;t allow me to post a link or upload an image.

The errors seem to refer to the CPU so it might be worth mentioning I have an AMD Ryzen 7 9800x3d which has only just come out recently. Is there a known issue with this CPU?</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 14:21:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/getting-some-strange-errors-in-whonix-on-a-new-pc/748.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Getting some strange errors in Whonix on a new PC</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kobrakai]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I’ve been using Whonix which is based on Kicksecure for many years but I just got a new PC and now I’m having problems booting it in VirtualBox. I tried posting this on the Whonix forums but they suggested I ask here.</p>
<p>Sometimes it will boot correctly and sometimes it will get stuck. I’m often seeing strange errors/warnings around where it gets stuck which could be related. Unfortunately this forum won’t allow me to post a link or upload an image.</p>
<p>The errors seem to refer to the CPU so it might be worth mentioning I have an AMD Ryzen 7 9800x3d which has only just come out recently. Is there a known issue with this CPU?</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/getting-some-strange-errors-in-whonix-on-a-new-pc/748/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/getting-some-strange-errors-in-whonix-on-a-new-pc/748/1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 14:21:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-748-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/getting-some-strange-errors-in-whonix-on-a-new-pc/748.rss">Getting some strange errors in Whonix on a new PC</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
