<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Metapackages tweak suggestions</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/metapackages-tweak-suggestions/663</link>
    <description>Looked through Kicksecure&#39;s metapackages to see what depends on what, and determine if some enhancements could be made. I added a rather lengthy suggestion for restructuring the metapackages to https://www.kicksecure.com/w/index.php?title=Dev/Metapackages&amp;stable=0, which would be something we could consider for Trixie. While Kicksecure is still based on Bookworm however, I came up with some possibly useful changes we could apply now:

* Add `apt-transport-https` to `kicksecure-dependencies-cli`? This will make it easier for people to use certain third-party repos, potentially.
* Does `timesanitycheck` need updated? It&#39;s &quot;expiration date&quot; is some time in 2023.
* Consider adding `vim-tiny` or even `vim` to `kicksecure-recommended-cli`? `nano` is oftentimes tricky to use for me, and I spin up new VMs often enough that installing Vim later is something I have to keep redoing.
* Does `open-link-confirmation` still work? If so, I notice that the Git page for it (https://github.com/Kicksecure/open-link-confirmation) states &quot;On an Anonymity Gateway (when the `anon-gw-base-files` package is installed), it honors the `$EDITOR` environment variable (falls back to kwrite if unset), asks if a file should be opened in an editor before opening it and informs, that opening links on a Gateway is unsupported for security reasons.&quot; Maybe the default text editor should be changed to Mousepad?
* Why are the following packages part of `kicksecure-default-applications-cli`, shouldn&#39;t they be part of a GUI metapackage instead, like `kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce`?
  * `catfish` (appears to be primarily a GUI application)
  * `flatpak` (flatpaks are only supposed to be GUI applications)
Why are the following applications part of `kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce`, shouldn&#39;t they be part of a CLI package like `kicksecure-recommended-cli` or `kicksecure-default-applications-cli`?
  * `p7zip-full`
  * `unar`
  * `unzip`
  * `xz-utils`
  * `zip`
* CLI/TUI tools can use `hunspell` (nano for instance has spell checking functionality that uses it according to `apt-cache rdepends`), should it be moved from kicksecure-desktop-applications-recommended to `kicksecure-recommended-cli` or even `kicksecure-dependencies-cli`? (The latter has a &quot;Do not remove.&quot; warning similar to `kicksecure-desktop-applications-recommended`).
* Hexchat is officially abandoned upstream. See https://hexchat.github.io/news/2.16.2.html. Might be a good idea to find a different IRC client and make an apparmor-profile package for it, since Hexchat may not be secure in the long run?
* tirdad may actually be useful under Qubes OS, assuming the VM runs its own kernel which I think it does (although there is a Qubes OS setting that makes me unsure there). If it is usable on Qubes, perhaps it should be moved from `kicksecure-cli-host-packages-recommended` to `kicksecure-recommended-cli` or even `kicksecure-dependencies-cli`? This needs testing.

Assuming no one brings up any objections, I&#39;ll be submitting some changes for review that implement some or all of the above.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 19:34:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Development</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/metapackages-tweak-suggestions/663.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Metapackages tweak suggestions</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Looked through Kicksecure’s metapackages to see what depends on what, and determine if some enhancements could be made. I added a rather lengthy suggestion for restructuring the metapackages to <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/index.php?title=Dev/Metapackages&amp;stable=0" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Dev/Metapackages - Kicksecure</a>, which would be something we could consider for Trixie. While Kicksecure is still based on Bookworm however, I came up with some possibly useful changes we could apply now:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add <code>apt-transport-https</code> to <code>kicksecure-dependencies-cli</code>? This will make it easier for people to use certain third-party repos, potentially.</li>
<li>Does <code>timesanitycheck</code> need updated? It’s “expiration date” is some time in 2023.</li>
<li>Consider adding <code>vim-tiny</code> or even <code>vim</code> to <code>kicksecure-recommended-cli</code>? <code>nano</code> is oftentimes tricky to use for me, and I spin up new VMs often enough that installing Vim later is something I have to keep redoing.</li>
<li>Does <code>open-link-confirmation</code> still work? If so, I notice that the Git page for it (<a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/open-link-confirmation" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - Kicksecure/open-link-confirmation: Asks for confirmation before opening links - For better security. - Asks before a link is (accidentally) opened in a browser to avoid linking activities.</a>) states “On an Anonymity Gateway (when the <code>anon-gw-base-files</code> package is installed), it honors the <code>$EDITOR</code> environment variable (falls back to kwrite if unset), asks if a file should be opened in an editor before opening it and informs, that opening links on a Gateway is unsupported for security reasons.” Maybe the default text editor should be changed to Mousepad?</li>
<li>Why are the following packages part of <code>kicksecure-default-applications-cli</code>, shouldn’t they be part of a GUI metapackage instead, like <code>kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce</code>?
<ul>
<li><code>catfish</code> (appears to be primarily a GUI application)</li>
<li><code>flatpak</code> (flatpaks are only supposed to be GUI applications)<br>
Why are the following applications part of <code>kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce</code>, shouldn’t they be part of a CLI package like <code>kicksecure-recommended-cli</code> or <code>kicksecure-default-applications-cli</code>?</li>
<li><code>p7zip-full</code></li>
<li><code>unar</code></li>
<li><code>unzip</code></li>
<li><code>xz-utils</code></li>
<li><code>zip</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>CLI/TUI tools can use <code>hunspell</code> (nano for instance has spell checking functionality that uses it according to <code>apt-cache rdepends</code>), should it be moved from kicksecure-desktop-applications-recommended to <code>kicksecure-recommended-cli</code> or even <code>kicksecure-dependencies-cli</code>? (The latter has a “Do not remove.” warning similar to <code>kicksecure-desktop-applications-recommended</code>).</li>
<li>Hexchat is officially abandoned upstream. See <a href="https://hexchat.github.io/news/2.16.2.html" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">2.16.2, The Final Release – HexChat</a>. Might be a good idea to find a different IRC client and make an apparmor-profile package for it, since Hexchat may not be secure in the long run?</li>
<li>tirdad may actually be useful under Qubes OS, assuming the VM runs its own kernel which I think it does (although there is a Qubes OS setting that makes me unsure there). If it is usable on Qubes, perhaps it should be moved from <code>kicksecure-cli-host-packages-recommended</code> to <code>kicksecure-recommended-cli</code> or even <code>kicksecure-dependencies-cli</code>? This needs testing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Assuming no one brings up any objections, I’ll be submitting some changes for review that implement some or all of the above.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/metapackages-tweak-suggestions/663/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/metapackages-tweak-suggestions/663/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 19:34:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-663-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/metapackages-tweak-suggestions/663.rss">Metapackages tweak suggestions</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
