<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Whonix / Oracle Security</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152</link>
    <description>I&#39;ve used only Windows since the 80s, so my experience is limited. As I&#39;ve learned about security I&#39;ve become aware of the &quot;Lack&quot; thereof. Last couple of years I&#39;ve been wanting to learn about Whonix which has a reputation for being Secure. However, I don&#39;t know if I should keep the installation of Whonix as a goal in light of the interview with a Whistleblower US Gov&#39;t IT specialist I heard the other night on a Podcast? He worded for US Gov&#39;t in 2016 to a latter date. He became high ranking, and knowledgeable. He reports Microsoft as having the contract with all systems across the Federal Gov&#39;t. He also reports he witnessed Microsoft Tech were ordered to act as &quot;Escorts&quot; to Chinese IT Tech personnel who were stationed in China. These &quot;Escorts&quot; supposedly acted as guides to allow access to the Chinese Tech on all levels? This will become very controversial since the President at the time (Obama) reportedly signed off on it. This is the background to my question since the Whistleblower also reported the &quot;Escorts&quot; also were used with Oracle! So, my question is was or is your Whonix product compromised, and/or is it now secure?</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:48:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Virtualbox</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Whonix / Oracle Security</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Wrong forum.</p>
<p>This is not a Whonix forum.</p>
<p>This is the Kicksecure forum.</p>
<p>Therefore closing.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/3</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:48:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1152-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152.rss">Whonix / Oracle Security</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Whonix / Oracle Security</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1152-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152.rss">Whonix / Oracle Security</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Whonix / Oracle Security</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[jashep]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I’ve used only Windows since the 80s, so my experience is limited. As I’ve learned about security I’ve become aware of the “Lack” thereof. Last couple of years I’ve been wanting to learn about Whonix which has a reputation for being Secure. However, I don’t know if I should keep the installation of Whonix as a goal in light of the interview with a Whistleblower US Gov’t IT specialist I heard the other night on a Podcast? He worded for US Gov’t in 2016 to a latter date. He became high ranking, and knowledgeable. He reports Microsoft as having the contract with all systems across the Federal Gov’t. He also reports he witnessed Microsoft Tech were ordered to act as “Escorts” to Chinese IT Tech personnel who were stationed in China. These “Escorts” supposedly acted as guides to allow access to the Chinese Tech on all levels? This will become very controversial since the President at the time (Obama) reportedly signed off on it. This is the background to my question since the Whistleblower also reported the “Escorts” also were used with Oracle! So, my question is was or is your Whonix product compromised, and/or is it now secure?</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152/1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:45:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1152-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-oracle-security/1152.rss">Whonix / Oracle Security</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
