<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641</link>
    <description>sudo apt install --no-install-recommends kicksecure-xfce-host - Conflict with Plymouth after entering this command when morphing Debian, MX Linux and LMDE. This error was made by me and all my friends. Today, my friend also received it. *sudo apt remove plymouth* resolves problem. Write about it in morphing instructions so that people know what to do in this situation. It seems that someone has complained about this error on this forum</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 01:51:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Quiksilver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>What is plymouth used for… is it really needed for the splash screen?<br>
Slick Greeter should be looked into for the greeter login screen shipped with Kicksecure.<br>
It is what comes with Linux Mint however it does not come bundled with the Cinnamon desktop environment itself. So if other DE shipped ISO’s for Kicksecure where to be released like with Cinnamon it wouldn’t come included.</p>
<p><strong>Slick Greeter</strong> (slick-greeter) does not require Plymouth. Slick Greeter is a lightweight GTK+ greeter for LightDM, and it is primarily responsible for providing the graphical login interface. It can function independently of Plymouth.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641/2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 01:51:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-641-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641.rss">Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>sudo apt install --no-install-recommends kicksecure-xfce-host - Conflict with Plymouth after entering this command when morphing Debian, MX Linux and LMDE. This error was made by me and all my friends. Today, my friend also received it. <em>sudo apt remove plymouth</em> resolves problem. Write about it in morphing instructions so that people know what to do in this situation. It seems that someone has complained about this error on this forum</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641/1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 19:23:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-641-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/error-plymouth-conflict-in-debian-morphing/641.rss">Error: Plymouth conflict in Debian morphing</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
