<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kali and Parrot Morph</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538</link>
    <description>I morphed Kali xfce and Parrot Mate into Kicksecure. All main functions work (some issues arise only during package updates, which need to be resolved manually). This could turn hacker Linux distributions into a powerful weapon (but I&#39;m not sure that devs approve of this). User has all restrictions in live-mode: password prompt, sudo limitations, and no autologin for user. In standard Kicksecure, user has root privileges without password and auto-login in live-mode. I just shared my experience.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 17:17:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Kali and Parrot Morph</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>UPD Tirdad and some other tools cause a lot of conflict. I do not recommend installing kicksecure on these Linux. But grub-live, security-misc and sdwdate worked fine</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538/2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 17:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-538-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538.rss">Kali and Parrot Morph</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Kali and Parrot Morph</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I morphed Kali xfce and Parrot Mate into Kicksecure. All main functions work (some issues arise only during package updates, which need to be resolved manually). This could turn hacker Linux distributions into a powerful weapon (but I’m not sure that devs approve of this). User has all restrictions in live-mode: password prompt, sudo limitations, and no autologin for user. In standard Kicksecure, user has root privileges without password and auto-login in live-mode. I just shared my experience.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538/1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 12:57:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-538-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kali-and-parrot-morph/538.rss">Kali and Parrot Morph</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
