<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022</link>
    <description>Hi, Patrick. I really love Kicksecure and Whonix. For enhanced protection wiki recommended to use Whonix on a Kicksecure host in live mode. My laptop has 16 gigs of memory - this is now standard for many budget mid-range computers. Most of my friends also have 16 gigs. If I run Whonix on Kicksecure-host in live mode, I practically have no memory left even for the simplest actions. But if VM took up 1 gigabyte less memory, that would be enough for browsing internet and simple actions on laptops with 16 gigs of memory. Can Gateway be changed to user-sysmaint-split level so that the Gateway only has the panel for connecting to Tor, and desktop, browsers, and unnecessary systemd services are removed to save disk space and increase protection? Overall 1 gigabyte, and many users of Kicksecure could have maximum protection in live mode. I know that size of Whonix has been reduced in past. Or maybe you can advise me on what can be removed from Gateway manually without compromising the system&#39;s functionality.
Maybe you will scold me that this is a question for Whonix forum, but I don&#39;t have invite for registration. I apologize. Thank you</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 14:06:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 14:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1022-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022.rss">Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The invite code can be seen on the registration page.</p>
<p>The invite code is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Whonix</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Closing because wrong forum.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 14:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1022-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022.rss">Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rico]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi, Patrick. I really love Kicksecure and Whonix. For enhanced protection wiki recommended to use Whonix on a Kicksecure host in live mode. My laptop has 16 gigs of memory - this is now standard for many budget mid-range computers. Most of my friends also have 16 gigs. If I run Whonix on Kicksecure-host in live mode, I practically have no memory left even for the simplest actions. But if VM took up 1 gigabyte less memory, that would be enough for browsing internet and simple actions on laptops with 16 gigs of memory. Can Gateway be changed to user-sysmaint-split level so that the Gateway only has the panel for connecting to Tor, and desktop, browsers, and unnecessary systemd services are removed to save disk space and increase protection? Overall 1 gigabyte, and many users of Kicksecure could have maximum protection in live mode. I know that size of Whonix has been reduced in past. Or maybe you can advise me on what can be removed from Gateway manually without compromising the system’s functionality.<br>
Maybe you will scold me that this is a question for Whonix forum, but I don’t have invite for registration. I apologize. Thank you</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 13:29:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1022-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/whonix-over-kicksecure-host-live/1022.rss">Whonix over Kicksecure-host-live</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
