<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Modernize Website</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/modernize-website/370</link>
    <description>Current state of the website is not the best. It looks obsolete. Images are pixelated in most instances. And even if they were not pixelated, they would still be archaic, because they are basically windows xp era icons.

Second problem: website is badly structured. Too many unnecessary pieces if you ask me. Also the website does not make the organization clear.

Also the name kicksecure is just too long. And also, having a .com domain makes the wrong impression.

Suggestion:

* Modernize images
* Too many images also tbh, you don&#39;t need to declare thunderbird and vlc are default on the homepage. Also the thunderbird logo is more than a year old. Anyway
* Modernize logo (simplify)
* Consider using kicksec instead of kicksecure
* Write a manifesto where you declare the principles (can draft one if you like)
* Write policies and stuff clearly
* Lay down a structure. What is kicksecure? I don&#39;t know some random set of repos and a website. Make it more organized and organizaiton like. Make it possible to become members. Levels of memebership I don&#39;t know something. Make the impression that you are organized (and also be organized).
* Consider posting regular blogs or whatever, keep in touch with the peasants
* Where is the sauce? What if I have a pull for the website? Consider making it public or making it easier to find out
* Have a voting and proposal mechanisms based on members
* Declare principles and whatnot like other free software projects (clearly)

What is kicksecure? If the answer is something other than &quot;whonix without tor&quot;, than the website gives the wrong impression. 450 links and sections for virtualbox and kvm and stuff. Wow, is this a virtual only os? Well I guess, no one ever has this kind of stuff on the front page.

So I suggest: No vm stuff ever. One link and one download to rule them all, a live installation image. For this another post is coming.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 16:11:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Website</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/modernize-website/370.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Modernize Website</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[monsieur]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Current state of the website is not the best. It looks obsolete. Images are pixelated in most instances. And even if they were not pixelated, they would still be archaic, because they are basically windows xp era icons.</p>
<p>Second problem: website is badly structured. Too many unnecessary pieces if you ask me. Also the website does not make the organization clear.</p>
<p>Also the name kicksecure is just too long. And also, having a .com domain makes the wrong impression.</p>
<p>Suggestion:</p>
<ul>
<li>Modernize images</li>
<li>Too many images also tbh, you don’t need to declare thunderbird and vlc are default on the homepage. Also the thunderbird logo is more than a year old. Anyway</li>
<li>Modernize logo (simplify)</li>
<li>Consider using kicksec instead of kicksecure</li>
<li>Write a manifesto where you declare the principles (can draft one if you like)</li>
<li>Write policies and stuff clearly</li>
<li>Lay down a structure. What is kicksecure? I don’t know some random set of repos and a website. Make it more organized and organizaiton like. Make it possible to become members. Levels of memebership I don’t know something. Make the impression that you are organized (and also be organized).</li>
<li>Consider posting regular blogs or whatever, keep in touch with the peasants</li>
<li>Where is the sauce? What if I have a pull for the website? Consider making it public or making it easier to find out</li>
<li>Have a voting and proposal mechanisms based on members</li>
<li>Declare principles and whatnot like other free software projects (clearly)</li>
</ul>
<p>What is kicksecure? If the answer is something other than “whonix without tor”, than the website gives the wrong impression. 450 links and sections for virtualbox and kvm and stuff. Wow, is this a virtual only os? Well I guess, no one ever has this kind of stuff on the front page.</p>
<p>So I suggest: No vm stuff ever. One link and one download to rule them all, a live installation image. For this another post is coming.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/modernize-website/370/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/modernize-website/370/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-370-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/modernize-website/370.rss">Modernize Website</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
