<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722</link>
    <description>HI all,
I realise morphing Linux Mint Debian edition to Kicksecure is unsupported, but I&#39;m interested in learning from the experience of anyone who has done this. One thing I&#39;m wondering is how updates will work after morphing. Will I continue to get updates from Linux Mint? Are there any big problems you&#39;ve encountered?
Thanks

Edit: 
Hi Patrick,
Thanks for replying. Yes, I&#39;m aware of those links/options. That&#39;s why I specifically stated I know it&#39;s unsupported. I was hoping for some feedback and discussion from other users, not support from the team. 

If such discussions are not allowed here, can you direct me to somewhere they are allowed? 

I&#39;ve searched and there are very few discussions of Kicksecure + Linux Mint elsewhere on the web. I&#39;m not surprised as it&#39;s increasingly difficult to ask questions anywhere these days. 

I&#39;ve asked a similar question on the Linux Mint forums and they also closed the topic, saying it wasnt relevant to Mint and I should ask the question on Kicksecure forums. The rules for posting on Reddit forums are labyrinthine and arbitrary at the same time. 

So, if such a discussion can&#39;t be allowed here either, where are Kicksecure users supposed to learn from each other? Please consider reopening this topic or else consider adding a forum section where users are able to discuss things among themselves without expecting involvement from the Kicksecure team. This would be another valuable learning resource.
Regards</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 09:04:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 09:04:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-722-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722.rss">Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1732267825" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:13PM - 22 October 2024">Kicksecure – 22 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/436;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/1/1a/Usesearchengine.jpg?version=5e9554ee776455694f21fc054f14be65" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="436"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Please_Use_Search_Engines_And_See_Documentation_First" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Utilize Search Engines, Documentation and AI</a></h3>

  <p>Avoid basic questions. Effective use of search engines and AI (Artificial Intelligence). Utilizing extensive Kicksecure documentation.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote" data-post="1" data-topic="46">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img loading="lazy" alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/h/8491ac/48.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-inside-lmde-5/46">Kicksecure inside LMDE 5?</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/support/6"><span data-category-id="6" style="--category-badge-color: #0088CC; --category-badge-text-color: #FFFFFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="User support for the Kicksecure operating system."><span class="badge-category__name">Support</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    Hi! 
Anyone tried to install Kicksecure on top of Linux Mint Debian Edition? 
The recently released version of LMDE 5 is based on Debian 11 Bullseye. 
Is there a chance it will work properly?
  </blockquote>
</aside>

          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 09:04:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-722-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722.rss">Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[LMDE]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>HI all,<br>
I realise morphing Linux Mint Debian edition to Kicksecure is unsupported, but I’m interested in learning from the experience of anyone who has done this. One thing I’m wondering is how updates will work after morphing. Will I continue to get updates from Linux Mint? Are there any big problems you’ve encountered?<br>
Thanks</p>
<p>Edit:<br>
Hi Patrick,<br>
Thanks for replying. Yes, I’m aware of those links/options. That’s why I specifically stated I know it’s unsupported. I was hoping for some feedback and discussion from other users, not support from the team.</p>
<p>If such discussions are not allowed here, can you direct me to somewhere they are allowed?</p>
<p>I’ve searched and there are very few discussions of Kicksecure + Linux Mint elsewhere on the web. I’m not surprised as it’s increasingly difficult to ask questions anywhere these days.</p>
<p>I’ve asked a similar question on the Linux Mint forums and they also closed the topic, saying it wasnt relevant to Mint and I should ask the question on Kicksecure forums. The rules for posting on Reddit forums are labyrinthine and arbitrary at the same time.</p>
<p>So, if such a discussion can’t be allowed here either, where are Kicksecure users supposed to learn from each other? Please consider reopening this topic or else consider adding a forum section where users are able to discuss things among themselves without expecting involvement from the Kicksecure team. This would be another valuable learning resource.<br>
Regards</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 16:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-722-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/morphing-lmde-6-to-kicksecure/722.rss">Morphing LMDE 6 to Kicksecure</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
