<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992</link>
    <description>Hello. I really like the idea of kicksecure-welcome-page. It&#39;s very convenient to have buttons for different search engines. I think it would be excellent for convenience and privacy if you add the SearXNG search engine in the new update - according to many ratings, for example, https://searchengine.party, it is the most private and secure search engine. And it provides good search results. And you can also add the popular search engine Startpage, which can hide users&#39; IP.
Thank you for your work :heart:</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 16:58:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[sam]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Yes, that would be a very convenient solution, since firefox esr does not have startpage search by default. And <a href="https://searx.space/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://searx.space/</a> is also very useful. It is very convenient to have such buttons at hand when launching browser.</p>
<p>And maybe it would be worth changing elephant pic to a darker one so that buttons at top and  doc search are more contrasting and stand out better agains white clouds? Perhaps this way users will more often search for solutions to popular documented problems in documentation (visual memory will remember doc search on the homepage). Sorry if I am too picky about aesthetic. I love elephants and I greatly appreciate your fantastic work. All my friends are using Kicksecure now. Sometimes my friends (new users to Linux and Kicksecure) ask me about some problem. I tell them, “on browser’s homepage, there is a search for documentation, and it seems there is an instruction there to solve your problem”, and they respond “Yeah, right, I hadnt paid attention to this search before. It blends with background”</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 16:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-992-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992.rss">Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rico]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello. I really like the idea of kicksecure-welcome-page. It’s very convenient to have buttons for different search engines. I think it would be excellent for convenience and privacy if you add the SearXNG search engine in the new update - according to many ratings, for example, <a href="https://searchengine.party" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://searchengine.party</a>, it is the most private and secure search engine. And it provides good search results. And you can also add the popular search engine Startpage, which can hide users’ IP.<br>
Thank you for your work <img src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/images/emoji/twitter/heart.png?v=12" title=":heart:" class="emoji" alt=":heart:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 09:15:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-992-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/add-searxng-and-startpage-buttons-to-kicksecure-welcome-page/992.rss">Add SearXNG and Startpage buttons to kicksecure-welcome-page</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
