<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Swap-file-creator missing when in Qubes templates (morphing &amp; official derivative templates)</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644</link>
    <description>Hi,

I&#39;ve been using Kicksecure and it&#39;s derivatives for a good while by now in Qubes VMs and on servers (Kicksecure in Qubes and on server is morphed, Whonix 17 templates are official Qubes templates) and just realized that I have a seemingly plain, unencrypted swap partition on all Qubes templates. The morphed version on the server host looks correct, if I am not mistaken. Reading the documentation, my impression is that  `swap-file-creator` should change this by default on Kicksecure systems.

Examples:

[details=&quot;/etc/fstab entry in morphed Debian template on Qubes OS&quot;]
`/dev/xvdc1           swap           swap    defaults                    0 0`
[/details]

[details=&quot;/etc/fstab entry in my Whonix-Workstation AppVM installed from the official template on Qubes OS&quot;]
`/dev/xvdc1           swap           swap    defaults                    0 0`
[/details]

[details=&quot;Several command outputs from my morphed Kicksecure on a virtual server&quot;]
`swapon --show`
`/dev/dm-0 partition 5.7G   0B   -2`

More information on the device:
`sudo dmsetup info /dev/dm-0`
---snip---
`UUID: CRYPT-PLAIN-swapfile`

This looks correct I think?
[/details]

The package is also not installed on any of the machines except for the morphed host (actually a VPS). It looks like I chose `kicksecure-qubes-cli` for the Kicksecure template on Qubes while morphing and, again, the Whonix templates were not built by myself. On the VPS, I chose `kicksecure-cli-host`. (Writing this... is there potentially a difference between the `host` and the `qubes` packages in regards to the package being installed/not installed?)

Trying to find an answer to this still left me with two related questions:

* Is the documentation outdated? It states that it should be installed by default: /wiki/Swap-file-creator#Installation (posting the link resulted in an error, sorry)
That said, I don&#39;t know what cases ***&quot;otherwise&quot;*** covers or what history, intention or background the sentence has, though.
* Is there any other countermeasure against potentially sensitive information being written to the disk via swapping, which I was not able to find in the wiki, or may, for instance, keys have ended up on my disk?

[details=&quot;Unrelated&quot;]
Big thanks for all you do!
[/details]</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 22:55:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Swap-file-creator missing when in Qubes templates (morphing &amp; official derivative templates)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Crok]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I tend to have a promising idea for digging into something right after posting a question.</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">apt-cache rdepends swap-file-creator

swap-file-creator
Reverse Depends:
  non-qubes-enhancements-cli
  non-qubes-vm-enhancements-cli
</code></pre>
<p>I would interpret this as it being only relevant for <code>non-qubes</code> systems? Can someone point me towards some kind of documentation or explanation why this is?<br>
Is it related to Qubes already being installed on an encrypted disk by default? Wouldn’t there be a benefit from a per-boot encrypted file still, which Qubes has been talking about for something close to a decade?</p>
<p>Just throwing around theories as to why this is, I might be missing something in the related docs.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 22:55:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-644-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644.rss">Swap-file-creator missing when in Qubes templates (morphing &amp; official derivative templates)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Swap-file-creator missing when in Qubes templates (morphing &amp; official derivative templates)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Crok]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi,</p>
<p>I’ve been using Kicksecure and it’s derivatives for a good while by now in Qubes VMs and on servers (Kicksecure in Qubes and on server is morphed, Whonix 17 templates are official Qubes templates) and just realized that I have a seemingly plain, unencrypted swap partition on all Qubes templates. The morphed version on the server host looks correct, if I am not mistaken. Reading the documentation, my impression is that  <code>swap-file-creator</code> should change this by default on Kicksecure systems.</p>
<p>Examples:</p>

/etc/fstab entry in morphed Debian template on Qubes OS <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1">(click for more details)</a>

/etc/fstab entry in my Whonix-Workstation AppVM installed from the official template on Qubes OS <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1">(click for more details)</a>

Several command outputs from my morphed Kicksecure on a virtual server <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1">(click for more details)</a>
<p>The package is also not installed on any of the machines except for the morphed host (actually a VPS). It looks like I chose <code>kicksecure-qubes-cli</code> for the Kicksecure template on Qubes while morphing and, again, the Whonix templates were not built by myself. On the VPS, I chose <code>kicksecure-cli-host</code>. (Writing this… is there potentially a difference between the <code>host</code> and the <code>qubes</code> packages in regards to the package being installed/not installed?)</p>
<p>Trying to find an answer to this still left me with two related questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is the documentation outdated? It states that it should be installed by default: /wiki/Swap-file-creator#Installation (posting the link resulted in an error, sorry)<br>
That said, I don’t know what cases <em><strong>“otherwise”</strong></em> covers or what history, intention or background the sentence has, though.</li>
<li>Is there any other countermeasure against potentially sensitive information being written to the disk via swapping, which I was not able to find in the wiki, or may, for instance, keys have ended up on my disk?</li>
</ul>

Unrelated <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1">(click for more details)</a>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644/1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 22:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-644-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/swap-file-creator-missing-when-in-qubes-templates-morphing-official-derivative-templates/644.rss">Swap-file-creator missing when in Qubes templates (morphing &amp; official derivative templates)</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
