<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157</link>
    <description>The package is only going to be as secure and up-to-date as the upstream developers made it. There must be no interference or external involvement in adding or removing code from any package (no package maintainer, only to make the package work as is from the upstream).

### Why

We have the Debian design, and we&#39;ve seen how flawed it is when it comes to security and feature fixes. It&#39;s horrible in every aspect. What we get from Debian is, at best, working software, but that doesn’t mean it’s secure, up-to-date, or even always stable. Issues like packages crashing on shutdown when clicking X or freezing on specific Y action, are common (because they are already in the distro passing freeze timeline without upstream fixes), and such bugs when occurs are unlikely to be addressed in a timely manner.

A major security flaw in Debian and Debian-like philosophies is that if the upstream of a package fixes a security issue and pushes it to their users, Debian remains unaware of it and will not include the fix in their own package unless it is documented or assigned a CVE. As a result, users remain vulnerable for up to maybe entire five years.

Another issue is the complexity trust in the chain of delivery. The more people who can add, remove, or manipulate the code, the more trust becomes a concern. If the code goes from developer X to intermediary Y (or even more intermediaries) before reaching the user, then the user must trust not only X but also Y and anyone else in the chain. Moreover, X doesn&#39;t know Y or their practices, so X must also trust Y not to tamper with the code before reaching the user. This design introduces unnecessary trust assumptions. Code must be delivered directly from X to the user.

Note: Operating system developers should only interact with core/system-level packages, such as the kernel or desktop environment or VM configs or so.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 12:26:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Development</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>More or less it was explanation for the issues not solutions for them:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The init system requires a configuration file.</p>
<ul>
<li>systemd: a getty systemd unit file</li>
<li>SysVinit: a SysVinit uses service configuration files</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Thats a system base/core thing, its responsibility of the OS maintainers to figure out that.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>for packaging work</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>To make a package working when installed from the repository thats for sure the OS maintainers job, but dont modify the upstream code to remove certain stuff or add or keep it old or so.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Open Source Linux distributions do not have this power</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Its really achievable, just simple thing, is the upstream doine 123 or not, no then tickets and until fixed bye. Its not hard to remove x browser because its dead or vulnerable or so.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>That is an unfortunate Arch Linux incident. For context:</p>
<ul>
<li>It was AUR: <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Arch_User_Repository">Arch User Repository - ArchWiki</a></li>
<li>It was not: <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Official_repositories">Official repositories - ArchWiki</a></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Unrelated, what happened from AUR can happen from official, same power, blind trust based…etc.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Similar to above.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Kurt Roeckx was a debian maintainer. Like i said before it doesnt matter, im talking about the flawed concept not who done it.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Packaging will be imperfect, there can be issues, yes, but unavoidable.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Unrelated, its not about packaging, debian played with the upstream package to keep it using iptables because they are stuck with it and not yet on nftables, because of keep it old policy. if debian were using latest updates it wouldnt have this issue.</p>
<p>Important Note: App-per-VM will provide the app needs in the VM, meaning if the upstream assumed glibc to be there then it will be there, if musl then it is, and so on. So there wont need to be a patch to make the apps working in the distro, because the apps will not be attached to what the distro is actually using, instead only in the VM containing it.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In that case, we won’t realistically would not reach reproducible builds.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It is what it is. If the upstream lazy or dump then let it be, we wont interfere to make their code better or worse.</p>
<p>Note: base system/core since its the responsibility of the OS maintainers, then patches are allowed anyway so it must meet the best expectations from reproducibility/bootstrappability.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="4" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In any case, bootstrapping a base distribution at this point is entirely unrealistic. We don’t have even remotely enough developers / funding to make that happen.</p>
<p>Kicksecure for the foreseeable future will remain a derivative of a base distribution.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Indeed, hope one day a distro will change its behavior to a better future.</p>
<p>Note: Fedora is doing some extreme changes to its future, worth to keep an eye on (in linux kernel world) .</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/5">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 09:37:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1157-5</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss">Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>One cannot educate oneself based on news alone. News is all about sensational, exceptional, negative, and current events. In that case, one will lack the required foundational knowledge.</p>
<p>Medical analogy:<br>
To be able to research and contribute to improved heart surgery procedures, one needs to be a heart surgeon (or other qualified medical researcher). For example, I am not active in this field, hence cannot talk with certainty, demand heart surgeons times making suggestions on how to change their procedures.</p>
<p>Back to Linux distribution maintenance / operation system development:<br>
To be able to contribute to Linux distribution maintenance, one needs to be a Linux distribution maintainer.</p>
<p>The problem is, that Linux distribution maintainers are not particularly good at marketing, advertising their hard work. They’re not creating engaging texts, flashy graphics, arguments, memes and videos. Hence, their hard work goes easily unnoticed.</p>
<p>What do all Linux distributions no matter how different they are in common? They do packaging. (And there is any that does not, they’ll have scripts or other files which replace this purpose.)</p>
<p>Alright. So you’ll start with a source code folder such as the source code of grub2. Select files from grub2 source code folder:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">asm-tests
build-aux
conf
config.h.in
configure
configure.ac
INSTALL
and so forth
</code></pre>
<p>But a different structure is required for the binary installable package:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">* etc/grub.d/10_linux
* usr/bin/grub-install
* and so forth
</code></pre>
<p>How do you get from source package to binary installable package? Answer: packaging. Who provides the package? The distribution maintainer. Who distributes the package? The distribution.</p>
<p>Alternative? Linux From Scratch. Read upstream’s readme, manually install the dependency and follow the upstream’s instruction for compilation, installation - if available.</p>
<p>We want a console login. How to do that? The standard Open Source tool for that is <code>getty</code>. But getty even if compiled and lingering on the hard drive as perfectly compiled binary does nothing. It needs to be started. How to start it? The init system starts it. How does the init system start it?</p>
<p>The init system requires a configuration file.</p>
<ul>
<li>systemd: a getty systemd unit file</li>
<li>SysVinit: a SysVinit uses service configuration files</li>
</ul>
<p>Who provides the init system configuration file for getty? Upstream getty? No.</p>
<p>Then who else does the Linux distribution integration work? The distribution maintainer, the Linux distribution.</p>
<p>Refer to <a href="https://www.debian.org/doc/debian-policy/index.html" class="inline-onebox">Debian Policy Manual — Debian Policy Manual v4.7.2.0</a> for other packaging tasks.</p>
<p>This process is an absolute necessity. There is no (universally accepted) standard (file structure, compile command, init system, compile options, …) that all upstream projects follow to completely avoid any necessity for packaging work. If there was a standard or convention, there would not be enough participating upstream’s to build a functional Linux distribution.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, all of this necessary packaging work allows for vulnerabilities and/or malicious backdoors to be injected.</p>
<p>There are certainly different opinions on how to package, what should, should not be done and other specifics. That’s why many different Linux base distributions exist. However, unfortunately it’s not possible to completely wipe away.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>This is followed in windows, google, apple…etc if they find an app having issue/s they will notify upstream or just remove it and thats it.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Multi-billion surveillance capitalism corporations with power to do that. Open Source Linux distributions do not have this power due to the organisational differences, which are documented here: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Linux_User_Experience_versus_Commercial_Operating_Systems" class="inline-onebox">Linux User Experience versus Commercial Operating Systems</a></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/22/arch_aur_browsers_compromised/">Injecting a malware</a></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/22/arch_aur_browsers_compromised/">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.theregister.com/design_picker/13249a2e80709c7ff2e57dd3d49801cd534f2094/graphics/favicons/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="48" height="48">

      <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/22/arch_aur_browsers_compromised/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">theregister.com</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/455;"><img src="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/06/25/poison_shutterstock.jpg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="455"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/22/arch_aur_browsers_compromised/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arch user-contributed browsers compromised</a></h3>

  <p>: The distro's greatest asset is arguably also its greatest weakness</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>That is an unfortunate Arch Linux incident. For context:</p>
<ul>
<li>It was AUR: <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Arch_User_Repository" class="inline-onebox">Arch User Repository - ArchWiki</a></li>
<li>It was not: <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Official_repositories" class="inline-onebox">Official repositories - ArchWiki</a></li>
</ul>
<p>As established above, packaging is unavoidable. Packaging files (and packages) must either be trusted and/or audited (preferably).</p>
<p>This issue could not have been prevented by a “no packaging policy”. That option does not exist.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://github.blog/news-insights/ssh-keys-generated-on-debian-ubuntu-compromised/">corrupt a security library</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Similar to above.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Can add stupid configurations and lower good features, but upstream doing it right and dont know the solution e.g <a href="https://gitlab.com/libvirt/libvirt/-/issues/406#note_1176654618">kvm + nftable in bookworm</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Packaging will be imperfect, there can be issues, yes, but unavoidable.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Or surrender and do nothing, cant solve adding a package which is not on the keep it old and patch small, rather its continuously updated and comes with many features at once e.g virtualbox.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If there was a suitable base distribution that does that is of a higher quality then that would be an option.</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Operating_System">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1753435825" class="site-icon" width="151" height="151">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Operating_System" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="04:44AM - 25 July 2025">Kicksecure – 25 Jul 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/5/51/Kicksecure-image-twitter-post.jpg?version=30a0ad75271a4836786771c345c960b8" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Operating_System" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Security-Focused Operating System Comparison as Base for Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Comparison and Consideration of various Operating Systems as base for the Kicksecure Security Operating System. Design Documentation.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>…So someone has the ability to modify the upstream code before reaching the user, he can do it for good or for bad,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I haven’t seen any Linux distribution yet that doesn’t add patches. They may or may not patch more minimally and the policy on what is acceptable versus unacceptable is probably different but they do patch.</p>
<ul>
<li>Manjaro (probably similar to Arch Linux’s packaging): <a href="https://gitlab.manjaro.org/packages/core/grub" class="inline-onebox">Packages / core / grub · GitLab</a> (refer to the patch files starting with <code>000</code>)</li>
<li>Gentoo: <a href="https://gitweb.gentoo.org/repo/gentoo.git/tree/sys-boot/grub/grub-2.12-r7.ebuild" class="inline-onebox">grub-2.12-r7.ebuild « grub « sys-boot - repo/gentoo.git - Official Gentoo ebuild repository</a> (refer to <code>sed</code> command which makes changes to upstream source code)</li>
</ul>
<p>In any case, this is up to the base distribution.</p>
<p>And Kicksecure is a “patch” on top of Debian. (<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Comparison_with_Others" class="inline-onebox">Security Operating System Comparison - Kicksecure vs Debian</a>)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A) non-reproducible and no patch, or</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>upstream issue, if not fixed then flagged as non-reproducible due to upstream 123 issues. tickets for upstream if they dont fix then it is what it is.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In that case, we won’t realistically would not reach reproducible builds. I decided on preferring patches + reproducible builds instead of patch-less and unreproducible builds.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="3" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t want any intermediaries? Use Linux From Scratch.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If you want to have your pure own distro, you should have the original kernel code and add your own configs to follow the project policy:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In any case, bootstrapping a base distribution at this point is entirely unrealistic. We don’t have even remotely enough developers / funding to make that happen.</p>
<p>Kicksecure for the foreseeable future will remain a derivative of a base distribution.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/4">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 08:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1157-4</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss">Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>DMs can and do sometimes add:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mandatory access control</li>
<li>systemd hardening (capabilities… some introduction found here: <a href="https://github.com/alegrey91/systemd-service-hardening">GitHub - alegrey91/systemd-service-hardening: Basic guide to harden systemd services</a>)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/22/arch_aur_browsers_compromised/">Injecting a malware</a> or <a href="https://github.blog/news-insights/ssh-keys-generated-on-debian-ubuntu-compromised/">corrupt a security library</a>.</li>
<li>Can add stupid configurations and lower good features, but upstream doing it right and dont know the solution e.g <a href="https://gitlab.com/libvirt/libvirt/-/issues/406#note_1176654618">kvm + nftable in bookworm</a>.</li>
<li>Or surrender and do nothing, cant solve adding a package which is not on the keep it old and patch small, rather its continuously updated and comes with many features at once e.g virtualbox.</li>
</ul>
<p>…So someone has the ability to modify the upstream code before reaching the user, he can do it for good or for bad, and thats wrong to leave this hanging on blind trust in people. Good or bad code is the responsibility of the main/upstream developer not the distro/OS. This is followed in windows, google, apple…etc if they find an app having issue/s they will notify upstream or just remove it and thats it.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A) non-reproducible and no patch, or</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>upstream issue, if not fixed then flagged as non-reproducible due to upstream 123 issues. tickets for upstream if they dont fix then it is what it is.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="Patrick" data-post="2" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar"> Patrick Schleizer:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t want any intermediaries? Use Linux From Scratch.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If you want to have your pure own distro, you should have the original kernel code and add your own configs to follow the project policy:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: Operating system developers should only interact with core/system-level packages, such as the kernel or desktop environment or VM configs or so.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 18:55:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1157-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss">Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>DM = distribution maintainer</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The package is only going to be as secure and up-to-date as the upstream developers made it.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>secure:<br>
DMs can and do sometimes add:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mandatory access control</li>
<li>systemd hardening (capabilities… some introduction found here: <a href="https://github.com/alegrey91/systemd-service-hardening" class="inline-onebox">GitHub - alegrey91/systemd-service-hardening: Basic guide to harden systemd services</a>)</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>There must be no interference or external involvement in adding or removing code from any package (no package maintainer, only to make the package work as is from the upstream).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This interference as you call it is an expression of values.</p>
<p>values:</p><aside class="quote quote-modified" data-post="1" data-topic="1159">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/p/b2d939/48.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/proprietary-tyrant-competitors-and-project-values/1159">Proprietary tyrant competitors and project values</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/development/7"><span data-category-id="7" style="--category-badge-color: #25AAE2; --category-badge-text-color: #FFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="Development of Kicksecure software and source code."><span class="badge-category__name">Development</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    I am not worried about this. 
Related wiki chapter: 
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Miscellaneous_Threats_to_User_Freedom#Freedom_vs_Tyrant_Security">Freedom vs Tyrant Security</a> 
Hypothetical user quote: 

Due to lack of &lt;insert cool security feature&gt; by proprietary tyrant, I switched from Debian/Kicksecure to Google Android/iOS. 

That user doesn’t exist or is a minority infeasible to chase. 
In any case, we obviously cannot directly compete with proprietary tyrant companies with billions of USD in funding. That’s mission impossible. 
We can only compete on values. 
Such values include (no…
  </blockquote>
</aside>

<p>Packing policy is based on the values of the distribution:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/About_Debian_Packaging#Purpose_of_Packaging">Purpose of Packaging</a></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Issues like packages crashing on shutdown when clicking X or freezing on specific Y action, are common (because they are already in the distro passing freeze timeline without upstream fixes), and such bugs when occurs are unlikely to be addressed in a timely manner.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Rolling will have more issues constantly introduced. Debian stable has a purpose: It’s stable.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>What we get from Debian is, at best, working software, but that doesn’t mean it’s secure, up-to-date, or even always stable.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>A major security flaw in Debian and Debian-like philosophies is that if the upstream of a package fixes a security issue and pushes it to their users, Debian remains unaware of it and will not include the fix in their own package unless it is documented or assigned a CVE.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Needs to be contextualized.</p>
<p>Kicksecure, Whonix server running Debian stable /  Kicksecure:<br>
12 years at time of writing.</p>
<p>Website known hacked, defaced through server hacking: 0</p>
<p>affected by xz backdoor: no</p>
<p>Rolling distributions: affected by xz backdoor: yes.</p>
<p>Ticket:</p>
<aside class="quote quote-modified" data-post="1" data-topic="1139">
  <div class="title">
    <div class="quote-controls"></div>
    <img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar">
    <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/rolling-vs-stable-release-brainstorming/1139">Rolling vs. Stable release brainstorming</a> <a class="badge-category__wrapper " href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/c/development/7"><span data-category-id="7" style="--category-badge-color: #25AAE2; --category-badge-text-color: #FFF;" data-drop-close="true" class="badge-category " title="Development of Kicksecure software and source code."><span class="badge-category__name">Development</span></span></a>
  </div>
  <blockquote>
    Detailed overview of the issues with stable and rolling release distributions: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Stable_vs_Rolling_Distributions" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Stable vs Rolling Distributions - Security Analysis</a> 
Kicksecure’s current development strategy for the most part has been to harden Debian as much as is practically possible. This seems to have been working well for the most part, but there are some worries about the safety of some of the rather outdated software that Debian provides us. In particular: 

Critical, extremely complicated software like Firefox ESR and Th…
  </blockquote>
</aside>

<p>Related:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Stable_Version_User_Experience">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1753349424" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Stable_Version_User_Experience" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="10:41AM - 28 April 2025">Kicksecure – 28 Apr 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Stable_Version_User_Experience" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kicksecure Stable Version User Experience</a></h3>

  <p>Aims for a seamless and robust user experience in the stable release of Kicksecure</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>(Wiki spam / forum spam does not count. Not based on hacking.)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nurmagoz" data-post="1" data-topic="1157">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8e7dd6/48.png" class="avatar"> nurmagoz:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Another issue is the complexity trust in the chain of delivery. The more people who can add, remove, or manipulate the code, the more trust becomes a concern. If the code goes from developer X to intermediary Y (or even more intermediaries) before reaching the user, then the user must trust not only X but also Y and anyone else in the chain. Moreover, X doesn’t know Y or their practices, so X must also trust Y not to tamper with the code before reaching the user. This design introduces unnecessary trust assumptions. Code must be delivered directly from X to the user.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>again:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/About_Debian_Packaging#Purpose_of_Packaging">Purpose of Packaging</a></p>
<p>Example… Reproducible builds…</p>
<p>Do you want grub or any other package reproducible?</p>
<p>Take the patch, here example for grub:</p>
<p><a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=787795" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=787795</a></p>
<p>Here’s a “small” list of patches:<br>
<a href="https://udd.debian.org/dev/bugs.cgi?release=any&amp;patch=only&amp;merged=ign&amp;reproducible=1&amp;sortby=id&amp;sorto=asc&amp;format=html#results" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://udd.debian.org/dev/bugs.cgi?release=any&amp;patch=only&amp;merged=ign&amp;reproducible=1&amp;sortby=id&amp;sorto=asc&amp;format=html#results</a></p>
<p>(There’s also a larger list of patches for reproducible builds.)</p>
<p>Either,</p>
<ul>
<li>A) non-reproducible and no patch, or</li>
<li>B) reproducible and patched</li>
</ul>
<p>Choose one.</p>
<p>Want both? Maybe. If the patch gets merged upstream.</p>
<p>Sure. That’s the plan.</p>
<p>But what when upstream is slow and/or patch change requests?</p>
<p>That’s the case for grub:<br>
<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/boot#GRUB_Slow_Upstream">GRUB Slow Upstream</a></p>
<p>Meanwhile the choice is between A and B.</p>
<p>Don’t want any intermediaries? Use Linux From Scratch.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linuxfromscratch.org/" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linuxfromscratch.org/</a></p>
<p>Too complicated? Use a Linux distribution.</p>
<p>Want both no intermediaries and easy? Unavailable.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/2</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 13:56:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1157-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss">Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[nurmagoz]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The package is only going to be as secure and up-to-date as the upstream developers made it. There must be no interference or external involvement in adding or removing code from any package (no package maintainer, only to make the package work as is from the upstream).</p>
<h3><a name="p-2991-why-1" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-2991-why-1"></a>Why</h3>
<p>We have the Debian design, and we’ve seen how flawed it is when it comes to security and feature fixes. It’s horrible in every aspect. What we get from Debian is, at best, working software, but that doesn’t mean it’s secure, up-to-date, or even always stable. Issues like packages crashing on shutdown when clicking X or freezing on specific Y action, are common (because they are already in the distro passing freeze timeline without upstream fixes), and such bugs when occurs are unlikely to be addressed in a timely manner.</p>
<p>A major security flaw in Debian and Debian-like philosophies is that if the upstream of a package fixes a security issue and pushes it to their users, Debian remains unaware of it and will not include the fix in their own package unless it is documented or assigned a CVE. As a result, users remain vulnerable for up to maybe entire five years.</p>
<p>Another issue is the complexity trust in the chain of delivery. The more people who can add, remove, or manipulate the code, the more trust becomes a concern. If the code goes from developer X to intermediary Y (or even more intermediaries) before reaching the user, then the user must trust not only X but also Y and anyone else in the chain. Moreover, X doesn’t know Y or their practices, so X must also trust Y not to tamper with the code before reaching the user. This design introduces unnecessary trust assumptions. Code must be delivered directly from X to the user.</p>
<p>Note: Operating system developers should only interact with core/system-level packages, such as the kernel or desktop environment or VM configs or so.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157/1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 10:38:42 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1157-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/secure-and-trustless-trust-minimal-package-policy/1157.rss">Secure and Trustless/Trust Minimal Package Policy</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
