<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Struggling with the point release update</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051</link>
    <description>Hi guys, using the new updated kicksecure, but since the user and sysmaint account is seperated, I don&#39;t know how to access files between the accounts. For instance, I have an openvpn script in user but I can&#39;t run it if I have to reboot after using sudo. I also may have other times where I need ro run sudo on user files specificly and directories are not linked afaik. Can anyone support me here? Thanks.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 04:31:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Struggling with the point release update</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Shouldn’t OpenVPN things be doable via the network manager widget and not need root permissions?</p>
<p>In general, there are a few solutions if the reboot isn’t an option:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can remove user-sysmaint-split and go back to having a sudo-enabled user account. You can do this by rebooting the system, then selecting <code>REMOVE user-sysmaint-split | enable unrestricted admin mode</code> in the boot menu. Follow the on-screen directions after doing this.</li>
<li>You can automatically run things as root on bootup or login by creating a systemd unit for it.</li>
<li>You can place your script under <code>/usr/local/bin</code>, then create a privleap action that runs it with the appropriate arguments. Then you can use the <code>leaprun</code> utility to run the script as root even while booted into a user session. The <code>privleap.conf.d</code> and <code>leaprun</code> manpages should give you the needed info to do that, and there are lots of existing privleap config files in <code>/etc/privleap/conf.d</code> to give you examples of what to do. You can put your new config file in <code>/etc/privleap.conf.d</code>.</li>
</ul>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 04:31:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1051-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051.rss">Struggling with the point release update</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Struggling with the point release update</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Bob]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi guys, using the new updated kicksecure, but since the user and sysmaint account is seperated, I don’t know how to access files between the accounts. For instance, I have an openvpn script in user but I can’t run it if I have to reboot after using sudo. I also may have other times where I need ro run sudo on user files specificly and directories are not linked afaik. Can anyone support me here? Thanks.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 21:37:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1051-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/struggling-with-the-point-release-update/1051.rss">Struggling with the point release update</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
