<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Install on usb don&#39;t boot</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/install-on-usb-dont-boot/574</link>
    <description>hi friends

I&#39;m very interested in kicksecure and wanted to have it installed on a usb drive to test it longer before installing on hard drive, but i&#39;ve got a serious problem. I can&#39;t have the usb drive running the totally standard install

I run from a ventoy usb with kicksecure 17 iso; and install on another usb drive.
Config is standard : erase complete sdb device, and automatic partitioning

BUT, whether I choose luks crypted or not, the USBN isn&#39;t bootable
a few errors appears before grub shell starts : I reach GNU GRUB version 2.06 etc... minimal bash-like line editing.

errors very briefly appears just before : 
`error : no such device: /.disk/info.`
`.................&#39;&#39;...../.disk/mini-info.`
`.................&#39;&#39;...../26adaabd-0000-0000...etc...`

and then go to gnu grub bash like command line

I don&#39;t know how to get kicksecure installed on the usb, although I keept all the standard ready to go parameters.
I looked on the net, and didn&#39;t find much. The tutorial from kicksecure for installing on a usb is very limited ; i found no indication on partitioning nor on how to manage luks encrypted partitions
I&#39;d be glad to have any indications or help to deal with this, many thanks !</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 22:00:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/install-on-usb-dont-boot/574.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Install on usb don&#39;t boot</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ted]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>hi friends</p>
<p>I’m very interested in kicksecure and wanted to have it installed on a usb drive to test it longer before installing on hard drive, but i’ve got a serious problem. I can’t have the usb drive running the totally standard install</p>
<p>I run from a ventoy usb with kicksecure 17 iso; and install on another usb drive.<br>
Config is standard : erase complete sdb device, and automatic partitioning</p>
<p>BUT, whether I choose luks crypted or not, the USBN isn’t bootable<br>
a few errors appears before grub shell starts : I reach GNU GRUB version 2.06 etc… minimal bash-like line editing.</p>
<p>errors very briefly appears just before :<br>
<code>error : no such device: /.disk/info.</code><br>
<code>.................''...../.disk/mini-info.</code><br>
<code>.................''...../26adaabd-0000-0000...etc...</code></p>
<p>and then go to gnu grub bash like command line</p>
<p>I don’t know how to get kicksecure installed on the usb, although I keept all the standard ready to go parameters.<br>
I looked on the net, and didn’t find much. The tutorial from kicksecure for installing on a usb is very limited ; i found no indication on partitioning nor on how to manage luks encrypted partitions<br>
I’d be glad to have any indications or help to deal with this, many thanks !</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/install-on-usb-dont-boot/574/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/install-on-usb-dont-boot/574/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 22:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-574-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/install-on-usb-dont-boot/574.rss">Install on usb don&#39;t boot</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
