<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Kicksecure 17.4.4.6 - Point Release!</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-4-4-6-point-release/1213</link>
    <description># Download

https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Download

([What is a point release?](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Point_Release))

----

# Upgrade

Alternatively, an in-place release upgrade is possible using the [Kicksecure repository](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Project-APT-Repository).

----

This release would not have been possible without the numerous supporters of Kicksecure!

----

Please Donate!

https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate

----

Please Contribute!

https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute

----

# Special Notices

* This is probably the last release based on Debian `12` / `bookworm`.
* We are working towards porting to Debian `13` / `trixie`.
  * There is no ETA (estimated time of arrival).

----

# Major Changes

* No longer install Firefox by default.
  * Reason: [Mozilla terms of service change related to selling user data](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Default_Browser#Firefox_Selling_User_Data)
* No longer install Thunderbird by default.
  * Reason: Same as above.
* Implemented and installed Browser Choice by default. (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * user documentation: https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Browser-choice
  * developer documentation: https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice
* [grub-live](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live)
  * added [live-hardener]([Implementation](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live#Implementation))
    * &gt; `live-hardener` detects writable filesystems and remounts most of them read-only, then adds a live overlay on top. This is similar to what Debian&#39;s dracut&#39;s 90overlay-root does for the root filesystem, but applies to most other writable filesystems on the system, thus reducing persistence even in more complex setups.
    * Therefore, it is now compatible with the `btrfs` file system.
      * As a result, feature request https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/use-btrfs-as-the-default-journaling-file-system/626/8 is now unblocked.
* fix bootloader upgrades (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/issues/297
  * https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/pull/299
* new Linux user group `privleap`:
  * Linux user account members of the group `privleap` are allowed to use `privleap` actions by default (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* improve `/etc/profile.d` scripts error handling
* created an aggregation of https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Project_Policies, an overview of confirmed, proposed, and rejected policies guiding Kicksecure&#39;s development, philosophy, and legal framework.

# Progress Towards

* https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994
* https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199
* https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197

# Changelog

* bootclockrandomization:
  * Add hwclock synchronization (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* desktop-config-dist:
  * Improve zsh configuration usability and security (https://forums.whonix.org/t/change-default-shell-from-bash-to-zsh-by-default/14792/171) (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * sysmaint session: Show power manager widget and notifications by default (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * livecheck improvements (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
    * rewritten in Python
      * therefore should now be compatible with any desktop environment that supports systray
      * deprecated Xfce genmon implementation
    * Add read-only mode detection
      * make sure livecheck-lsblk.service runs early enough
      * add Calamares integration (tone down the message when Calamares mounts a disk as read-write during installation, as this is expected)
    * Add better handling of removable media, NFS, and VM shared folders (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* dist-base-files:
  * Switch to xz compression for initramfs (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* genmkfile:
  * Port to `approx` package caching proxy (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Respect `APTGETOPT_SERIALIZED` from environment when installing packages (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* grub-live:
  * Disable systemd-remount-fs and systemd-growfs-root in live mode (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* helper-scripts:
  * get-password-status-list: Make it more obvious when an account has no password set (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * screen locking in sysmaint session: Don&#39;t lock the screen if the user&#39;s password would make this insecure or cause breakage (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add basic network access checker (taken from updatecheck) (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add root user to list returned by get-user-list (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Implement sanitize-string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add HTML stripping utility (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * unicode: avoid warning message:
    * &gt; `grep: PCRE2 does not support \F, \L, \l, \N{name}, \U, or \u` by no longer using `--perl-regexp` for grep number three
  * Bring back read-only mode detection (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add unicode-testscript run to run-tests (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix `stcatn` failing to trim whitespace from all but the last line of an input file (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Improve `get_writable_fs_lists.sh` (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Refactor `live_mode.sh` to allow reducing logic duplication with livecheck (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add better handling of removable media, NFS, and VM shared folders (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Rework `live-mode.sh` to provide more detailed info (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * protect against `printf`, `grep --quiet` broken pipe
  * `/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/root_cmd.sh`: fix error message in case no privilege escalation tool can be found
  * test that `wc` is functional; add `/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/wc-test.sh` https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246
  * Add script for finding the device providing a mountpoint, for emergency shutdown feature (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix anondate-get so it actually uses anondate&#39;s output (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix get-backing-devices-for-mountpoint bug causing it to fail in live mode (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* kicksecure-base-files:
  * revert to the original DPKG origins file. No longer divert `/etc/dpkg/origins/default` because it breaks `reverse-depends`.
* kicksecure-meta-packages:
  * no longer install firmware-b43-installer by default due to upstream bug: firmware-b43-installer: firmware download fails due to a broken upstream URL and checksum mismatch. Debian bug report: [firmware-b43-installer: firmware download fails due to broken upstream URL and checksum mismatch](https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1109025)
  * Add XScreenSaver to kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * no longer install ZuluCrypt by default (https://forums.whonix.org/t/zulucrypt-luks-container-gui-cli/4876/19)
* live-config-dist:
  * Bring back BTRFS support (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Inform livecheck when an install starts and finishes (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* msgcollector:
  * Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * mandatory strip-html
  * Implement chunking for very long messages (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Switch to using helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * improve ARG_MAX check
  * fix: unbreak msgcollector in case the folder `/run/user/$(id -u)` does not exist (such as in a minimal environment, a chroot, or an SSH session with `UsePAM no`)
* open-link-confirmation:
  * Improve sysmaint session link rejection message (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix browser prioritization, add Brave and Mullvad to the list of candidates in alphabetical order (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* ram-wipe:
  * enable kernel parameters `init_on_free` and `init_on_alloc`
* sdwdate:
  * Remove non-working mirrors (Thanks to @Nurmagoz!)
  * fix: `TypeError: SdwdateClass.run_sclockadj_and_hwclock() takes 1 positional argument but 2 were given`
  * Don&#39;t try to sync hardware clock on Qubes OS (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add hardware clock syncing (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port strip_markup calls to sanitize_string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Switch to using helper-scripts strip_markup (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * seccomp fixes
    * https://forums.whonix.org/t/broken-sdwdate-after-latest-upgrade/21590/5
    * Thanks to @anonimac for the bug report and solution contribution!
* security-misc:
  * Improve emerg-shutdown usage documentation (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Use Ctrl+Alt+End as the default panic key (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Integrate emerg-shutdown into the initramfs (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Enable `indirect_target_selection=force` (Thanks to @raja!)
  * remove misleading TemporaryTimeout=0 in Bluetooth config (Thanks to Kevin Agwaze!)
  * Add comment related to approx package caching proxy (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * fix(permission-hardener): ssh-agent gets 2755 perms. Change from exactwhitelist to matchwhitelist. Discussion revealed that there&#39;s a good reason to leave setgid in here, which is essentially defense-in-depth (sometimes users may want to revert Kicksecure&#39;s default of kernel.yama.ptrace_scope=2, e.g. to debug a program, and Kicksecure should not be less secure than vanilla Debian in that situation). (Thanks to Ashlen!)
  * protect against grep pipefail
  * further validation of output of `faillock`
  * test that `wc` is functional https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246
  * pam-info: improve error handling https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246
  * pam-info: fix, consistently write errors and warnings to stderr
  * pam-info: fix: consistently write errors and warnings to stderr
  * perf(permission-hardener): optimize string match. Replace subprocess grep calls with bash substring matching in check_nosuid_whitelist function. This eliminates ~10k unneeded subprocess spawns that were causing significant performance degradation. In testing, it improves overall script execution speed by an order of magnitude. (Thanks to Ashlen!)
  * fix(permission-hardener): add exactwhitelist permissions for ssh-agent. (Thanks to Ashlen!)
  * fix(permission-hardener): ssh-agent gets 755 perms. Replace the commented-out matchwhitelist entry for ssh-agent with an explicit permission entry (755) for /usr/bin/ssh-agent. When ssh-agent&#39;s matchwhitelist entry was commented out in commit 7a5f8b87af, permission-hardener began resetting it to restrictive defaults (744), preventing non-root users from executing ssh-agent. This broke split SSH functionality in Qubes OS for me because I was using Kicksecure in the vault qube, and ssh-agent runs under a non-root user in that configuration (see https://forum.qubes-os.org/t/split-ssh/19060. As noted in the comment, Debian installs with 2755 permissions as a way to mitigate ptrace attacks, but this rationale doesn&#39;t apply due to kernel.yama.ptrace_scope=2 being set in Kicksecure. (Thanks to Ashlen!)
  * handle case of non-existence of /proc/cmdline
  * Set `erst_disable` (Thanks to @raja!)
  * Prevent erroneous &quot;`Login blocked after [negative number] attempts`&quot; errors for root. (Thanks to DMHalford!)
* setup-wizard-dist:
  * Add mention of browser-choice for Kicksecure, fix outdated boot mode string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* sysmaint-panel:
  * Add &quot;Install a Browser&quot; button (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add clean mechanism for UI build artifacts, remove autogenerated code from repo (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Remove obsolete live mode indicator (replaced by livecheck applet from desktop-config-dist) (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* systemcheck:
  * show disabled as per default/expected `su` access check result only when using `--verbose`
  * Warn about absent locked or restricted passwords for the sysmaint account (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add `su` permissions check (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Enable `check_login_security` on Qubes OS, fix autologin check (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Silence spurious warnings, fix AppArmor issues (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Split out network access check code into helper-scripts (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix color for root login security warnings (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix check_login_security regexes, increase warning severity for root password and autologin issues (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add &#39;Locked (Present)&#39; and &#39;Restricted (Present)&#39; password statuses (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add additional checks for locked and disabled (restricted) passwords (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port sanitize_variable calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string, make apparmor config handle both /bin and /usr/bin properly (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * non-zero exit code if tirdad kernel module is not loaded (Non-Qubes only)
  * non-zero exit code if Debian is LTS or EOL (show Debian still supported message only in verbose mode) (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * improve tirdad kernel module loaded test help output
  * output more information about Secure Boot status when not booted into EFI mode and when using Qubes
  * Don&#39;t block the livecheck-lsblk file in the apparmor policy (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Skip user-sysmaint-split check in Whonix-Gateway if package is not installed, add new checks (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * ignore more journal messages when using `--verbose`
  * add support for ignoring journal messages in systemcheck configuration file using `grep --fixed-strings`
  * sort into literal and non-literal grep for ignored journal messages
  * fix apparmor issue https://forums.whonix.org/t/systemcheck-gui-fails-with-error-arg-max-exceeded/21715 (Thanks to @marmarek for the bug report and fix suggestion!)
  * simplified virtualizer check
  * fix: in `--verbose` mode, in Qubes: exit non-zero when missing the tirdad kernel module
  * new unwanted package: `stardict` due to [privacy concerns associated with stardict](https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Debian#startdict https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki
* tb-updater:
  * check if network interface exists
  * update to new version file web link
  * sanitize-string
  * Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
* timesanitycheck:
  * updated minimum_unixtime
* tor-control-panel:
  * improve robustness of proxy configuration code
  * fix adding custom bridges
* usability-misc:
  * Make mousepad open files in a new window rather than a new tab (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * dist-installer-cli (Linux VirtualBox installer:) detect whether the installer is run in live mode
  * protect against grep broken pipe
  * dist-installer-cli: fix `bash -x`
  * test that `wc` is functional https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246
* user-sysmaint-split:
  * Update ensure-shutdown enablement code (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * If ensure-shutdown is enabled, enable it for sysmaint mode also (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Indentation fix, silence stderr from accountctl when necessary (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Fix sysmaint mode compatibility with Qubes StandaloneVMs (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * non-Qubes: Add xfce4-power-manager to user service list (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Make compatible with new boot menu scripts (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * run livecheck systray in sysmaint session (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add optional systemd unit mechanism, and add ufw and firewalld by default also in sysmaint session if installed (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * fix: show /etc/profile.d sysmaint account notification only if tty has been detected. This is to avoid confusing non-login scripts with terminal output.
* vm-config-dist:
  * Add shared folder README, add shared folder shortcut to Thunar (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Refactor/unbreak automatic shared folder mounting, harden permissions on shared folders (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Add XScreenSaver configuration for VMs (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * no longer disable KDE screensaver by default in VMs, reasons:
    * KDE only; Missing implementation with the main supported desktop environment (Xfce at the time of writing); Inconsistent versus systemcheck notifying about autologin check and user account password check.
* derivative-maker:
  * Introduced `derivative-update` (Thanks to major contributions by @ArrayBolt3 and @tabletseeker!)
    * https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Build_Documentation/derivative-update
    * Verify digital signatures and key fingerprints of signed git commits when `derivative-maker` is invoked.
      * Trust on First Use (TOFU). Initial source code digital signature verification - as already previously documented - is still recommended.
  * work towards [Docker Container that builds Whonix Images](https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494) (Thanks to major contributions by @ArrayBolt3 and @tabletseeker!)
    * status at time of writing: https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494/163
  * Port from `apt-cacher-ng` to the `approx` package as a caching proxy (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * Remove obsolete image-to-iso references (Thanks to @ArrayBolt3!)
  * unmount stray loop devices in case kpartx fails to remove them (happens inside Docker) ([Thanks to @e-coin for the bug report!](https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494/43))
  * always run sanity tests during official builds
  * fix `grep --quiet` versus pipefail
  * test that `wc` does not core dump
  * improve prepare-release relative path support

----

# Full difference of all changes

[https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.3.9.9-developers-only...17.4.4.3-developers-only](https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.3.9.9-developers-only...17.4.4.3-developers-only)</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 11:16:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>News</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-4-4-6-point-release/1213.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Kicksecure 17.4.4.6 - Point Release!</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <h1><a name="p-3191-download-1" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-download-1"></a>Download</h1>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Download">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1754904625" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Download" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="11:26AM - 15 May 2025">Kicksecure – 15 May 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/387;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/6/63/Download-kicksecure.jpg?version=9adcc5bcba92e65719a7341228d32e1c" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="388"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Download" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Download Kicksecure (FREE)</a></h3>

  <p>FREE Download Kicksecure. Kicksecure can be installed on a physical machine as a host operating system (OS), as a guest OS inside a virtual machine, or as a portable host OS on a USB data stick.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>(<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Point_Release">What is a point release?</a>)</p>
<hr>
<h1><a name="p-3191-upgrade-2" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-upgrade-2"></a>Upgrade</h1>
<p>Alternatively, an in-place release upgrade is possible using the <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Project-APT-Repository">Kicksecure repository</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>This release would not have been possible without the numerous supporters of Kicksecure!</p>
<hr>
<p>Please Donate!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1754904625" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="08:43AM - 10 October 2024">Kicksecure – 10 Oct 24</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/432;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/8/83/Payment.jpg?version=82f3e45ee49a6c0df81431424ee3fc2f" class="thumbnail" width="640" height="432"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Donate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Donating to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>PayPal, Bitcoin (BTC), Monero (XMR), Ethereum (ETH) or Token, Credit Card, Bank Wire, Others</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<p>Please Contribute!</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric" data-onebox-src="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/favicon.svg?hsversion-headscript-replacement-by-server=1&amp;hsversion_from_server_replacement_unixtime=1754904625" class="site-icon" width="40" height="40">

      <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="02:15PM - 07 August 2025">Kicksecure – 7 Aug 25</a>
  </header>

  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:483/500;"><img src="https://www.kicksecure.com/w/images/0/07/Computer_n_screen.png?version=b6cc9963027950ad5fd1793106674efb" class="thumbnail" width="483" height="500"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Contribute" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contribute to Kicksecure</a></h3>

  <p>Spread, Follow, Develop, Testing, Donate. Contribute to Freedom Software / Open Source.</p>


  </article>

  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>

  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<hr>
<h1><a name="p-3191-special-notices-3" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-special-notices-3"></a>Special Notices</h1>
<ul>
<li>This is probably the last release based on Debian <code>12</code> / <code>bookworm</code>.</li>
<li>We are working towards porting to Debian <code>13</code> / <code>trixie</code>.
<ul>
<li>There is no ETA (estimated time of arrival).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h1><a name="p-3191-major-changes-4" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-major-changes-4"></a>Major Changes</h1>
<ul>
<li>No longer install Firefox by default.
<ul>
<li>Reason: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Default_Browser#Firefox_Selling_User_Data">Mozilla terms of service change related to selling user data</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>No longer install Thunderbird by default.
<ul>
<li>Reason: Same as above.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Implemented and installed Browser Choice by default. (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)
<ul>
<li>user documentation: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Browser-choice" class="inline-onebox">Browser Choice - Browser Selection Installer Dialog</a></li>
<li>developer documentation: <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/browser-choice" class="inline-onebox">Browser Choice</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Grub-live">grub-live</a>
<ul>
<li>added <a>live-hardener</a>
<ul>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p><code>live-hardener</code> detects writable filesystems and remounts most of them read-only, then adds a live overlay on top. This is similar to what Debian’s dracut’s 90overlay-root does for the root filesystem, but applies to most other writable filesystems on the system, thus reducing persistence even in more complex setups.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>Therefore, it is now compatible with the <code>btrfs</code> file system.
<ul>
<li>As a result, feature request <a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/use-btrfs-as-the-default-journaling-file-system/626/8" class="inline-onebox">Use Btrfs as the default journaling file system - #8 by Patrick</a> is now unblocked.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>fix bootloader upgrades (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/issues/297" class="inline-onebox">UEFI bootloader updates seem broken · Issue #297 · grml/grml-debootstrap · GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/grml/grml-debootstrap/pull/299" class="inline-onebox">Make bootloader updates on UEFI-based systems work by ArrayBolt3 · Pull Request #299 · grml/grml-debootstrap · GitHub</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>new Linux user group <code>privleap</code>:
<ul>
<li>Linux user account members of the group <code>privleap</code> are allowed to use <code>privleap</code> actions by default (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>improve <code>/etc/profile.d</code> scripts error handling</li>
<li>created an aggregation of <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Project_Policies" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure Project Policies</a>, an overview of confirmed, proposed, and rejected policies guiding Kicksecure’s development, philosophy, and legal framework.</li>
</ul>
<h1><a name="p-3191-progress-towards-5" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-progress-towards-5"></a>Progress Towards</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/unplugging-external-drive-should-trigger-a-shutdown/994" class="inline-onebox">Unplugging external drive should trigger a shutdown</a></li>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/emergency-key-press-shutdown-sequence/1199" class="inline-onebox">Emergency key press shutdown sequence</a></li>
<li><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/ctrl-alt-del-three-finger-salute-action/1197" class="inline-onebox">Ctrl+Alt+Del (three-finger salute) action</a></li>
</ul>
<h1><a name="p-3191-changelog-6" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-changelog-6"></a>Changelog</h1>
<ul>
<li>bootclockrandomization:
<ul>
<li>Add hwclock synchronization (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>desktop-config-dist:
<ul>
<li>Improve zsh configuration usability and security (<a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/change-default-shell-from-bash-to-zsh-by-default/14792/171" class="inline-onebox">Change default shell from bash to zsh by default? - #171 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a>) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>sysmaint session: Show power manager widget and notifications by default (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>livecheck improvements (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)
<ul>
<li>rewritten in Python
<ul>
<li>therefore should now be compatible with any desktop environment that supports systray</li>
<li>deprecated Xfce genmon implementation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Add read-only mode detection
<ul>
<li>make sure livecheck-lsblk.service runs early enough</li>
<li>add Calamares integration (tone down the message when Calamares mounts a disk as read-write during installation, as this is expected)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Add better handling of removable media, NFS, and VM shared folders (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>dist-base-files:
<ul>
<li>Switch to xz compression for initramfs (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>genmkfile:
<ul>
<li>Port to <code>approx</code> package caching proxy (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Respect <code>APTGETOPT_SERIALIZED</code> from environment when installing packages (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>grub-live:
<ul>
<li>Disable systemd-remount-fs and systemd-growfs-root in live mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>helper-scripts:
<ul>
<li>get-password-status-list: Make it more obvious when an account has no password set (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>screen locking in sysmaint session: Don’t lock the screen if the user’s password would make this insecure or cause breakage (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add basic network access checker (taken from updatecheck) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add root user to list returned by get-user-list (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Implement sanitize-string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add HTML stripping utility (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>unicode: avoid warning message:
<ul>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p><code>grep: PCRE2 does not support \F, \L, \l, \N{name}, \U, or \u</code> by no longer using <code>--perl-regexp</code> for grep number three</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bring back read-only mode detection (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add unicode-testscript run to run-tests (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix <code>stcatn</code> failing to trim whitespace from all but the last line of an input file (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Improve <code>get_writable_fs_lists.sh</code> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Refactor <code>live_mode.sh</code> to allow reducing logic duplication with livecheck (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add better handling of removable media, NFS, and VM shared folders (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Rework <code>live-mode.sh</code> to provide more detailed info (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>protect against <code>printf</code>, <code>grep --quiet</code> broken pipe</li>
<li><code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/root_cmd.sh</code>: fix error message in case no privilege escalation tool can be found</li>
<li>test that <code>wc</code> is functional; add <code>/usr/libexec/helper-scripts/wc-test.sh</code> <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246" class="inline-onebox">Prevent erroneous "Login blocked after [negative number] attempts" errors by DMHalford · Pull Request #305 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>Add script for finding the device providing a mountpoint, for emergency shutdown feature (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix anondate-get so it actually uses anondate’s output (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix get-backing-devices-for-mountpoint bug causing it to fail in live mode (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>kicksecure-base-files:
<ul>
<li>revert to the original DPKG origins file. No longer divert <code>/etc/dpkg/origins/default</code> because it breaks <code>reverse-depends</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>kicksecure-meta-packages:
<ul>
<li>no longer install firmware-b43-installer by default due to upstream bug: firmware-b43-installer: firmware download fails due to a broken upstream URL and checksum mismatch. Debian bug report: <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1109025">firmware-b43-installer: firmware download fails due to broken upstream URL and checksum mismatch</a></li>
<li>Add XScreenSaver to kicksecure-desktop-applications-xfce (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>no longer install ZuluCrypt by default (<a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/zulucrypt-luks-container-gui-cli/4876/19" class="inline-onebox">zulucrypt (LUKS container GUI / CLI) - #19 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>live-config-dist:
<ul>
<li>Bring back BTRFS support (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Inform livecheck when an install starts and finishes (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>msgcollector:
<ul>
<li>Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>mandatory strip-html</li>
<li>Implement chunking for very long messages (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Switch to using helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>improve ARG_MAX check</li>
<li>fix: unbreak msgcollector in case the folder <code>/run/user/$(id -u)</code> does not exist (such as in a minimal environment, a chroot, or an SSH session with <code>UsePAM no</code>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>open-link-confirmation:
<ul>
<li>Improve sysmaint session link rejection message (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix browser prioritization, add Brave and Mullvad to the list of candidates in alphabetical order (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ram-wipe:
<ul>
<li>enable kernel parameters <code>init_on_free</code> and <code>init_on_alloc</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>sdwdate:
<ul>
<li>Remove non-working mirrors (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/nurmagoz">@Nurmagoz</a>!)</li>
<li>fix: <code>TypeError: SdwdateClass.run_sclockadj_and_hwclock() takes 1 positional argument but 2 were given</code></li>
<li>Don’t try to sync hardware clock on Qubes OS (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add hardware clock syncing (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port strip_markup calls to sanitize_string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Switch to using helper-scripts strip_markup (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>seccomp fixes
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/broken-sdwdate-after-latest-upgrade/21590/5" class="inline-onebox">Broken sdwdate after latest upgrade - #5 by anonimac - Support - Whonix Forum</a></li>
<li>Thanks to <span class="mention">@anonimac</span> for the bug report and solution contribution!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>security-misc:
<ul>
<li>Improve emerg-shutdown usage documentation (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Use Ctrl+Alt+End as the default panic key (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Integrate emerg-shutdown into the initramfs (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Enable <code>indirect_target_selection=force</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>remove misleading TemporaryTimeout=0 in Bluetooth config (Thanks to Kevin Agwaze!)</li>
<li>Add comment related to approx package caching proxy (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>fix(permission-hardener): ssh-agent gets 2755 perms. Change from exactwhitelist to matchwhitelist. Discussion revealed that there’s a good reason to leave setgid in here, which is essentially defense-in-depth (sometimes users may want to revert Kicksecure’s default of kernel.yama.ptrace_scope=2, e.g. to debug a program, and Kicksecure should not be less secure than vanilla Debian in that situation). (Thanks to Ashlen!)</li>
<li>protect against grep pipefail</li>
<li>further validation of output of <code>faillock</code></li>
<li>test that <code>wc</code> is functional <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246" class="inline-onebox">Prevent erroneous "Login blocked after [negative number] attempts" errors by DMHalford · Pull Request #305 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>pam-info: improve error handling <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246" class="inline-onebox">Prevent erroneous "Login blocked after [negative number] attempts" errors by DMHalford · Pull Request #305 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
<li>pam-info: fix, consistently write errors and warnings to stderr</li>
<li>pam-info: fix: consistently write errors and warnings to stderr</li>
<li>perf(permission-hardener): optimize string match. Replace subprocess grep calls with bash substring matching in check_nosuid_whitelist function. This eliminates ~10k unneeded subprocess spawns that were causing significant performance degradation. In testing, it improves overall script execution speed by an order of magnitude. (Thanks to Ashlen!)</li>
<li>fix(permission-hardener): add exactwhitelist permissions for ssh-agent. (Thanks to Ashlen!)</li>
<li>fix(permission-hardener): ssh-agent gets 755 perms. Replace the commented-out matchwhitelist entry for ssh-agent with an explicit permission entry (755) for /usr/bin/ssh-agent. When ssh-agent’s matchwhitelist entry was commented out in commit 7a5f8b87af, permission-hardener began resetting it to restrictive defaults (744), preventing non-root users from executing ssh-agent. This broke split SSH functionality in Qubes OS for me because I was using Kicksecure in the vault qube, and ssh-agent runs under a non-root user in that configuration (see <a href="https://forum.qubes-os.org/t/split-ssh/19060" class="inline-onebox">Split SSH - Community Guides - Qubes OS Forum</a>. As noted in the comment, Debian installs with 2755 permissions as a way to mitigate ptrace attacks, but this rationale doesn’t apply due to kernel.yama.ptrace_scope=2 being set in Kicksecure. (Thanks to Ashlen!)</li>
<li>handle case of non-existence of /proc/cmdline</li>
<li>Set <code>erst_disable</code> (Thanks to <span class="mention">@raja</span>!)</li>
<li>Prevent erroneous “<code>Login blocked after [negative number] attempts</code>” errors for root. (Thanks to DMHalford!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>setup-wizard-dist:
<ul>
<li>Add mention of browser-choice for Kicksecure, fix outdated boot mode string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>sysmaint-panel:
<ul>
<li>Add “Install a Browser” button (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add clean mechanism for UI build artifacts, remove autogenerated code from repo (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Remove obsolete live mode indicator (replaced by livecheck applet from desktop-config-dist) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>systemcheck:
<ul>
<li>show disabled as per default/expected <code>su</code> access check result only when using <code>--verbose</code></li>
<li>Warn about absent locked or restricted passwords for the sysmaint account (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add <code>su</code> permissions check (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Enable <code>check_login_security</code> on Qubes OS, fix autologin check (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Silence spurious warnings, fix AppArmor issues (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Split out network access check code into helper-scripts (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix color for root login security warnings (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix check_login_security regexes, increase warning severity for root password and autologin issues (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add ‘Locked (Present)’ and ‘Restricted (Present)’ password statuses (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add additional checks for locked and disabled (restricted) passwords (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port sanitize_variable calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string, make apparmor config handle both /bin and /usr/bin properly (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>non-zero exit code if tirdad kernel module is not loaded (Non-Qubes only)</li>
<li>non-zero exit code if Debian is LTS or EOL (show Debian still supported message only in verbose mode) (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>improve tirdad kernel module loaded test help output</li>
<li>output more information about Secure Boot status when not booted into EFI mode and when using Qubes</li>
<li>Don’t block the livecheck-lsblk file in the apparmor policy (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Skip user-sysmaint-split check in Whonix-Gateway if package is not installed, add new checks (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>ignore more journal messages when using <code>--verbose</code></li>
<li>add support for ignoring journal messages in systemcheck configuration file using <code>grep --fixed-strings</code></li>
<li>sort into literal and non-literal grep for ignored journal messages</li>
<li>fix apparmor issue <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/systemcheck-gui-fails-with-error-arg-max-exceeded/21715" class="inline-onebox">'systemcheck --gui' fails with `ERROR: ARG_MAX exceeded!` - Support - Whonix Forum</a> (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/marmarek">@marmarek</a> for the bug report and fix suggestion!)</li>
<li>simplified virtualizer check</li>
<li>fix: in <code>--verbose</code> mode, in Qubes: exit non-zero when missing the tirdad kernel module</li>
<li>new unwanted package: <code>stardict</code> due to [privacy concerns associated with stardict](<a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Debian#startdict" class="inline-onebox">Dev/Debian</a> <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure Documentation</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tb-updater:
<ul>
<li>check if network interface exists</li>
<li>update to new version file web link</li>
<li>sanitize-string</li>
<li>Port strip-html calls to sanitize-string (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Port to helper-scripts strip-html (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>timesanitycheck:
<ul>
<li>updated minimum_unixtime</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>tor-control-panel:
<ul>
<li>improve robustness of proxy configuration code</li>
<li>fix adding custom bridges</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>usability-misc:
<ul>
<li>Make mousepad open files in a new window rather than a new tab (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli (Linux VirtualBox installer:) detect whether the installer is run in live mode</li>
<li>protect against grep broken pipe</li>
<li>dist-installer-cli: fix <code>bash -x</code></li>
<li>test that <code>wc</code> is functional <a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/security-misc/pull/305#issuecomment-2892378246" class="inline-onebox">Prevent erroneous "Login blocked after [negative number] attempts" errors by DMHalford · Pull Request #305 · Kicksecure/security-misc · GitHub</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>user-sysmaint-split:
<ul>
<li>Update ensure-shutdown enablement code (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>If ensure-shutdown is enabled, enable it for sysmaint mode also (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Indentation fix, silence stderr from accountctl when necessary (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Fix sysmaint mode compatibility with Qubes StandaloneVMs (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>non-Qubes: Add xfce4-power-manager to user service list (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Make compatible with new boot menu scripts (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>run livecheck systray in sysmaint session (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add optional systemd unit mechanism, and add ufw and firewalld by default also in sysmaint session if installed (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>fix: show /etc/profile.d sysmaint account notification only if tty has been detected. This is to avoid confusing non-login scripts with terminal output.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>vm-config-dist:
<ul>
<li>Add shared folder README, add shared folder shortcut to Thunar (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Refactor/unbreak automatic shared folder mounting, harden permissions on shared folders (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Add XScreenSaver configuration for VMs (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>no longer disable KDE screensaver by default in VMs, reasons:
<ul>
<li>KDE only; Missing implementation with the main supported desktop environment (Xfce at the time of writing); Inconsistent versus systemcheck notifying about autologin check and user account password check.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>derivative-maker:
<ul>
<li>Introduced <code>derivative-update</code> (Thanks to major contributions by <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a> and <span class="mention">@tabletseeker</span>!)
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Dev/Build_Documentation/derivative-update" class="inline-onebox">Kicksecure derivative-updater Documentation</a></li>
<li>Verify digital signatures and key fingerprints of signed git commits when <code>derivative-maker</code> is invoked.
<ul>
<li>Trust on First Use (TOFU). Initial source code digital signature verification - as already previously documented - is still recommended.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>work towards <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494">Docker Container that builds Whonix Images</a> (Thanks to major contributions by <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a> and <span class="mention">@tabletseeker</span>!)
<ul>
<li>status at time of writing: <a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494/163" class="inline-onebox">Docker Container that builds Whonix Images - #163 by Patrick - Development - Whonix Forum</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Port from <code>apt-cacher-ng</code> to the <code>approx</code> package as a caching proxy (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>Remove obsolete image-to-iso references (Thanks to <a class="mention" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/u/arraybolt3">@ArrayBolt3</a>!)</li>
<li>unmount stray loop devices in case kpartx fails to remove them (happens inside Docker) (<a href="https://forums.whonix.org/t/docker-container-that-builds-whonix-images/17494/43">Thanks to @e-coin for the bug report!</a>)</li>
<li>always run sanity tests during official builds</li>
<li>fix <code>grep --quiet</code> versus pipefail</li>
<li>test that <code>wc</code> does not core dump</li>
<li>improve prepare-release relative path support</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h1><a name="p-3191-full-difference-of-all-changes-7" class="anchor" href="https://forums.kicksecure.com#p-3191-full-difference-of-all-changes-7"></a>Full difference of all changes</h1>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.3.9.9-developers-only...17.4.4.3-developers-only">https://github.com/Kicksecure/derivative-maker/compare/17.3.9.9-developers-only…17.4.4.3-developers-only</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-4-4-6-point-release/1213/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-4-4-6-point-release/1213/1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 11:16:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1213-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/kicksecure-17-4-4-6-point-release/1213.rss">Kicksecure 17.4.4.6 - Point Release!</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
