<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108</link>
    <description>I am reaching out to share some observations regarding missing panel items in the desktop settings for the two users (boot sessions), USER and USERMAINT. These issues were noticed while booting in Live Mode USB, and I believe it would be beneficial to me to provide my feedback.

- **USER**

  - *Power Manager Icon Missing* 
  The battery level indicator is absent from the system tray. This is particularly inconvenient for laptop users who rely on this feature to monitor their battery life.

- **USERMAINT**

  - *Power Manager Icon Missing* 
  Similar to USER, the battery level indicator is also missing.
  - *Time Clock Item Missing* 
  The Time Clock item is absent from the panel, which is a useful feature for quick access to the current time.
  - *Window Buttons Missing* 
  The absence of window indicators making it difficult to manage open windows. This has led to me to frustration while multitasking, such as when using the terminal to launch Firefox (look up issues) and Mousepad (take notes) and another xterm for debugging commands.
  
Its good to leave the USERMAINT desktop minimal but the three above would not be too much to add to the panel.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 21:29:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Development</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I found out why the battery level indicator is missing. XFCE’s power manager is installed, but for some reason it’s not set to enable the system tray icon. You can fix it by clicking on <code>Application Menu &gt; Settings &gt; Power Manager</code> and then switch on “System tray icon”. You may want to enable “Status notifications” at the same time.</p>
<p>I’ll work on implementing a fix for this.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/4">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 21:29:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1108-4</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108.rss">Panel items missing [feedback]</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The missing power manager icon is weird, I’ll double-check on my end but I think that’s supposed to be there by default. If it’s not, it’s possible the OS isn’t detecting your system’s battery. Will investigate.</p>
<hr>
<p>On the sysmaint session, just from a standpoint of what is or isn’t good to implement:</p>
<p>Adding a clock to the sysmaint session sounds like a good idea, especially since time can be security-related due to its effect on things like SSL.</p>
<p>I don’t think adding window buttons is a good idea, as much as they would be convenient. The sysmaint session is intentionally designed to be a bit annoying to use as a general-purpose session because using it as a general-purpose session is a security hazard. This is why we have a separate sysmaint session, so that it’s hard to get to Firefox or other complex apps that interact with the network.</p>
<hr>
<p>From a standpoint of implementation difficulty:</p>
<p>Right now the sysmaint session panel is implemented using <a href="https://packages.debian.org/bookworm/trayer" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">trayer</a>, which only supports system tray icons, not other widgets like clocks, power indicators, or window buttons. We’d have to use a more complete panel implementation (maybe xfce4-panel could be configured to work right somehow?) to introduce those elements, and I don’t really want us to use a panel implementation that’s <em>too</em> complete or easily reconfigured in order to keep the sysmaint session from being used for general-purpose tasks. It may be possible to pull in a good power manager applet from the Debian repos, and there might be a clock applet that could work in a similar way. (If a clock applet proves to be impossible, that could be worked into the system maintenance panel itself.) Window buttons are probably not going to be possible. It might be possible to get xfwm4 to minimize windows in such a way that they remain partially visible, we could look into that.</p>
<p>If the permissions limitations in a user session and the functionality limitations in a sysmaint session are too limiting for your use case, you can revert back to “unrestricted admin mode” by booting into the <code>REMOVE user-sysmaint-split | enable unrestricted admin mode</code> boot option. This will get rid of the sysmaint session and bring back <code>sudo</code> access in normal user sessions. See <a href="https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/Unrestricted_admin_mode" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Unrestricted Admin Mode</a> for details.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/3</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 15:17:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1108-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108.rss">Panel items missing [feedback]</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>USERMAINT? You mean sysmaint? Please edit.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 08:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1108-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108.rss">Panel items missing [feedback]</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Panel items missing [feedback]</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am reaching out to share some observations regarding missing panel items in the desktop settings for the two users (boot sessions), USER and USERMAINT. These issues were noticed while booting in Live Mode USB, and I believe it would be beneficial to me to provide my feedback.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>USER</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Power Manager Icon Missing</em><br>
The battery level indicator is absent from the system tray. This is particularly inconvenient for laptop users who rely on this feature to monitor their battery life.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>USERMAINT</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Power Manager Icon Missing</em><br>
Similar to USER, the battery level indicator is also missing.</li>
<li><em>Time Clock Item Missing</em><br>
The Time Clock item is absent from the panel, which is a useful feature for quick access to the current time.</li>
<li><em>Window Buttons Missing</em><br>
The absence of window indicators making it difficult to manage open windows. This has led to me to frustration while multitasking, such as when using the terminal to launch Firefox (look up issues) and Mousepad (take notes) and another xterm for debugging commands.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Its good to leave the USERMAINT desktop minimal but the three above would not be too much to add to the panel.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 23:52:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1108-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/panel-items-missing-feedback/1108.rss">Panel items missing [feedback]</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
