<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107</link>
    <description>I wanted to share a minor suggestion regarding the default behavior of Mousepad, the text editor included in Xfce. While the default tabbed interface works well for many users, I personally find it a bit inconvenient or more like annoying. Hope this post doesn&#39;t come across as annoying cause its nothing on Kicksecure but Xfce. Furthermore I suspect I&#39;m not the only one who feels this way, especially for those of us who frequently switch between different desktop environments distro hopping and testing.

It would be nice if Mousepad could be configured by default within Kicksecure to open new instances in separate windows rather than tabs. This small change could greatly improve the user experience for those who prefer this behavior.

After some research, I discovered that this setting is managed via dconf (org) rather than a standard Xfce configuration file. 

The following command can be used to set the desired behavior:

`gsettings set org.xfce.mousepad.preferences.window opening-mode &#39;window&#39;`

To make this change persistent across the system, you could create a drop-in dconf file. For example, you could add the following to a (example file `/etc/dconf/db/00_kicksecure-default-apps`):

```
[org.xfce.mousepad.preferences.window]
opening-mode = &#39;window&#39;
```

This would ensure that Mousepad opens new instances in separate windows by default. When I went to write notes on things inside of Live USB I couldn&#39;t stand it making new tabs. This is what brought me here and I hope you give it a consideration.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 17:03:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Development</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Sounds reasonable and probably easy enough to do. Thanks for the suggestion and the research, I’ll look into implementing it.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 17:03:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1107-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107.rss">Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[desi_fubu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I wanted to share a minor suggestion regarding the default behavior of Mousepad, the text editor included in Xfce. While the default tabbed interface works well for many users, I personally find it a bit inconvenient or more like annoying. Hope this post doesn’t come across as annoying cause its nothing on Kicksecure but Xfce. Furthermore I suspect I’m not the only one who feels this way, especially for those of us who frequently switch between different desktop environments distro hopping and testing.</p>
<p>It would be nice if Mousepad could be configured by default within Kicksecure to open new instances in separate windows rather than tabs. This small change could greatly improve the user experience for those who prefer this behavior.</p>
<p>After some research, I discovered that this setting is managed via dconf (org) rather than a standard Xfce configuration file.</p>
<p>The following command can be used to set the desired behavior:</p>
<p><code>gsettings set org.xfce.mousepad.preferences.window opening-mode 'window'</code></p>
<p>To make this change persistent across the system, you could create a drop-in dconf file. For example, you could add the following to a (example file <code>/etc/dconf/db/00_kicksecure-default-apps</code>):</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">[org.xfce.mousepad.preferences.window]
opening-mode = 'window'
</code></pre>
<p>This would ensure that Mousepad opens new instances in separate windows by default. When I went to write notes on things inside of Live USB I couldn’t stand it making new tabs. This is what brought me here and I hope you give it a consideration.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 23:10:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1107-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/set-mousepad-to-launch-in-new-windows-instead-of-tabs-by-default/1107.rss">Set Mousepad to Launch in New Windows instead of Tabs by Default</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
