<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
    <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359</link>
    <description>I don’t expect this to require any bug fix, unless one comes to mind, but just wanted to warn others of my ordeal.  Kicksecure seems an ideal OS for booting on a thumb drive for a very secure environment.  It seems more suitable than Tails for my use cases, as I’d also like to install some software to it.  To test it out, I burnt the live disk to a really OLD Kingston thumb drive of 8GB, and used it to install a persistent, encrypted thumb drive OS that I could e.g. install other softs on with SU privileges, a really old SanDisk 16 GB.  It booted and worked great.  I can even install other software by removing the split.

The Verbatim Seaglass drives seemed attractive, as they have lifetime warranties, which seems like a fairly strong expression of confidence in their shelf life.  I bought two 32GB and two 64, burnt the ISO on a Seaglass, and tried to boot it - this from the same ISO which previously worked.  It generated a bunch of errors and then said something like ‘Boot Failed’.  Note that virtual machines are enabled in both the BIOS’s I tried.  I then tried burning it without the extended volume name option in Rufus, and burnt onto a 64GB instead of a 32, and it worked.  I then plugged in the live disk in with another 64GB, and installed to it from Maint.  It seemed to complete quite happily, but it would not boot on any computer I tried it on, just like the first Live disk I originally burnt.  I compared it to the ancient SanDisk drive that worked.  I noticed in the boot order in the BIOS, I had a choice for the USB itself, and another for the same drive, with a Kicksecure name.  The one that started with USB wouldn’t boot, but the Kicksecure choice would.  Looking at two SeaGlass drives I tried to install to, neither show a Kicksecure choice in the BIOS.  It does not work with Secure Boot turned off.

These Seaglass drives SAY that they work for formatting in EXT4 on Linux.  I seem to have only one significant choice on how to create the installed version: EXT4 or BTFS.  I tried both on one of the drives, but neither gave me a Kicksecure boot choice.  I tried booting it on a port on a hub, and two different ports on my desktop.  No dice.

Based on the principle that if you try to install Windows on a machine, and you get errors instead of an OS, it is a virtual certainty that the HW is bad or incompatible  It seems like a foregone conclusion that the reason for the difference is the thumb drives; but feel free to make any suggestions.  I’ve had mostly good luck with Verbatim blank optical media over the years, but IMHO, this does not look good for them.  It seems like they are Kicksecure incompatible, as is.  I don’t know if it’s a bug in the design, M$ paid ‘em to be incompatible (which here seems unlikely, since they advertise Linux compatibility), or there’s a problem with USB 3.2 Gen 1; or maybe I’m missing something.  Maybe a bug in the KickSecure installer is more likely than Windows, but it seems less likely given that the prob. seems to show up depending on the thumb drive it’s installed on.  Implementing a thumb drive should under it all just be a big block of memory..

My machine is an ancient ASRock Tai Chi X570, with a Ryzen 5 3800X.  The SeaGlass USB drives are for USB 3.2 Gen 1.  This matches the specs on most of the USB ports on my desktop, AND on my USB hub.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 08:26:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Support</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[CodeLurker]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I decided to try using the drives that had worked previously again.  If I installed in dd mode, the created disk wouldn’t launch the maint menu item.  If I installed in ISO mode, I had two boot choices in the BIOS: USB &amp; GPT.  The USB choice resulted in “542: Index out of bounds” in a console window; but no maint mode.  I finally got the live disk to boot with Rufus only if burned as an ISO, and booted from it’s GPT boot entry.  Using the same ISO, and the same drives that previously had worked with Rufus, I was unable to recreate my initial success.  Burnt as an ISO, they all had errors about not being able to config the bootloader, which had timed out after 600 secs., not being able to run config_bootloader, or index out of bounds.  It ultimately failed on the hardware it previously worked on.</p>
<p>It looked very nice, the time it did work.  It seemed like just the thing I needed, the one time it did work.  It may take a while for me to install a Linux and give it a try there.  The point is, however, the problem was intermittent, and extended to all the thumb drives I tried it on.  It may well turn out that Rufus might turn out to be the problem, and just doesn’t burn it right.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/5">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/5</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 08:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1359-5</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss">Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[CodeLurker]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Further tests have shown that when I burn in DD mode in Rufus, I get a working Live setup on the original thumb drive that worked.  I burnt it to a thumb drive that worked for the ISO previously.  When I try install to HD on the other thumb drive, no matter if it’s the drive that worked originally or not, I get errors such as 'The bootloader could not be installed.; or ‘Failed to execute command /bootloader-config.’  It originally worked when burning it as an ISO.  I’m interested to find out the prob. now.  I will try it a little more before trying the “dd” command from Linux.  (I instolled PI-OS, and then switched to Technecium,  and have been meaning to get around to installing NixOS for the WSL Linux.)</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/4">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 06:20:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1359-4</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss">Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[CodeLurker]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1359">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>drives. Rufus might not install Kicksecure to a USB drive properly; the ISO is designed to be written <em>directly</em> to a disk,</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It’s worth a try.  Still, the USB drive it runs on shouldn’t make the difference, IMHO.  I’m not saying it’s not compatible with Linux, but rather that hardware was the only difference between the drives I created that did work, and that didn’t work..</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="arraybolt3" data-post="2" data-topic="1359">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="24" height="24" src="https://forums.kicksecure.com/user_avatar/forums.kicksecure.com/arraybolt3/48/88_2.png" class="avatar"> arraybolt3:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>the ISO is designed to be written <em>directly</em> to a disk, not unpacked into a filesystem on the disk.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I burnt an ISO onto a thumbdrive.  I did not unpack it.  Next, I left in the live disk, and added a blank one.  I installed Kicksecure onto the empty thumb drive.  I don’t see where I unpacked anything.</p>
<p>Thx for some great things to try, BTW.</p>
<hr>
<p>This question mentioned the use of DD is addressed here:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/SolusProject/comments/ly41ay/rufus_3141735_doesnt_show_dd_image_mode_option/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.reddit.com/r/SolusProject/comments/ly41ay/rufus_3141735_doesnt_show_dd_image_mode_option/</a></p>
<p>It says it has changed, so that you only get the option if it’s a hybrid ISO.  Burning again, I do get the question.  Perhaps I chose it one time, and didn’t another, heh.</p>
<p>I do remember that the Tails instructions have a notice there that said Balena Etcher used to be their recommended burner, as the KickSecure instructions still do; but that the app was found to be phoning home.  If memory serves, they are now recommending Rufus.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/3</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 23:40:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1359-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss">Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[arraybolt3]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Generally, USB drives themselves act like any other drive under Linux; it’s theoretically possible a drive <em>could</em> be compatible with Windows and not Linux, but in practice I have never seen this be the case.</p>
<p>You’re using Rufus to burn the ISO to the drives. Rufus might not install Kicksecure to a USB drive properly; the ISO is designed to be written <em>directly</em> to a disk, not unpacked into a filesystem on the disk. If you must use Rufus, try using “dd mode” to write the ISO. Better yet, use an existing Linux installation and flash the ISO using <code>dd</code>, i.e. <code>sudo dd if=./kicksecure.iso of=/dev/sdX bs=4M</code>.</p>
<p>(There is, of course, always the possibility that the drives themselves are failing. Drives are most likely to fail when they’re brand new and when they’re relatively old. There are command-line utilities for Linux such as <code>badblocks</code> you can use to check this, see <code>man badblocks</code>.)</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/2</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1359-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss">Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[CodeLurker]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I don’t expect this to require any bug fix, unless one comes to mind, but just wanted to warn others of my ordeal.  Kicksecure seems an ideal OS for booting on a thumb drive for a very secure environment.  It seems more suitable than Tails for my use cases, as I’d also like to install some software to it.  To test it out, I burnt the live disk to a really OLD Kingston thumb drive of 8GB, and used it to install a persistent, encrypted thumb drive OS that I could e.g. install other softs on with SU privileges, a really old SanDisk 16 GB.  It booted and worked great.  I can even install other software by removing the split.</p>
<p>The Verbatim Seaglass drives seemed attractive, as they have lifetime warranties, which seems like a fairly strong expression of confidence in their shelf life.  I bought two 32GB and two 64, burnt the ISO on a Seaglass, and tried to boot it - this from the same ISO which previously worked.  It generated a bunch of errors and then said something like ‘Boot Failed’.  Note that virtual machines are enabled in both the BIOS’s I tried.  I then tried burning it without the extended volume name option in Rufus, and burnt onto a 64GB instead of a 32, and it worked.  I then plugged in the live disk in with another 64GB, and installed to it from Maint.  It seemed to complete quite happily, but it would not boot on any computer I tried it on, just like the first Live disk I originally burnt.  I compared it to the ancient SanDisk drive that worked.  I noticed in the boot order in the BIOS, I had a choice for the USB itself, and another for the same drive, with a Kicksecure name.  The one that started with USB wouldn’t boot, but the Kicksecure choice would.  Looking at two SeaGlass drives I tried to install to, neither show a Kicksecure choice in the BIOS.  It does not work with Secure Boot turned off.</p>
<p>These Seaglass drives SAY that they work for formatting in EXT4 on Linux.  I seem to have only one significant choice on how to create the installed version: EXT4 or BTFS.  I tried both on one of the drives, but neither gave me a Kicksecure boot choice.  I tried booting it on a port on a hub, and two different ports on my desktop.  No dice.</p>
<p>Based on the principle that if you try to install Windows on a machine, and you get errors instead of an OS, it is a virtual certainty that the HW is bad or incompatible  It seems like a foregone conclusion that the reason for the difference is the thumb drives; but feel free to make any suggestions.  I’ve had mostly good luck with Verbatim blank optical media over the years, but IMHO, this does not look good for them.  It seems like they are Kicksecure incompatible, as is.  I don’t know if it’s a bug in the design, M$ paid ‘em to be incompatible (which here seems unlikely, since they advertise Linux compatibility), or there’s a problem with USB 3.2 Gen 1; or maybe I’m missing something.  Maybe a bug in the KickSecure installer is more likely than Windows, but it seems less likely given that the prob. seems to show up depending on the thumb drive it’s installed on.  Implementing a thumb drive should under it all just be a big block of memory..</p>
<p>My machine is an ancient ASRock Tai Chi X570, with a Ryzen 5 3800X.  The SeaGlass USB drives are for USB 3.2 Gen 1.  This matches the specs on most of the USB ports on my desktop, AND on my USB hub.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 09:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forums.kicksecure.com-post-1359-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forums.kicksecure.com/t/warning-prob-with-installing-on-verbatim-seaglass-drives-false-alarm/1359.rss">Warning: Prob. with installing on Verbatim SeaGlass drives - False alarm</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
